welcome to this Cuda programming course
where you will learn to leverage gpus
for high performance Computing the
course starts with an overview of the
deep learning ecosystem and guides you
through setting up Cuda and reviewing
essential C and C++ Concepts you'll
explore GPU architecture and write your
first Cuda kernels Advanced topics
include optimizing matrix multiplication
and extending pie torch with practical
applications like implementing a
multi-layer perception for the mest data
set Elliot Alid created this course so
what is Cuda or compute unified device
architecture by Nvidia uh my name is
Elliot and I'm an instructor on free
code Camp as well as a student studying
for my computer science degree so in
this course I bring to you Cuda for deep
learning but don't let that repel you if
you're not in deep learning because
there's still a lot that we're going to
be able to cover uh many other fields of
parallel programming so this is more
oriented for deep learning but not
specifically aimed at it um there's
going to be a lot covered here so uh
I'll show what the final prodject what
the final project is first um so that
you can get a feel forward and see kind
of what we're going to end up building
by the end um and then we'll just kind
of go from there so before we get
started with anything crazy I should
include a disclaimer um this course may
not be fully up to date by the time
you're watching this if you're watching
this 10 years years down the line from
when I've released it it might not all
be the same there might be things that
are updated the new uh compute
capabilities might be you know way
better there might be a bunch of
different stuff happening so I'm not too
sure where the ecosystem will be at in
10 years but as of 2024 this is pretty
much the best you're going to get so
just trying to include that and I
thought I'd try to make everything uh
not entirely centered around time so you
can go back into this version uh or or
certain Cuda versions and reproduce all
the same stuff it just might be a little
bit different down the line if you're
watching this later on so why did I
create this course exactly well a lot of
these performance and kernel engineering
jobs require a lot of knowledge they
require a lot of experience in the
industry uh and it's just really hard to
get up to that point where you're able
to compete with the top and the best of
the best performance Engineers so these
are the people that are writing the
training runs for like gbt 4 gbt 5 all
of this um you need a lot of skill to
optimize a massive neural network
training run and inference on a larg
data center or compute cluster so this
aims to prevent some of that manual
weaving on your part still encouraging
you to do so U on your own but prevent
some of that hardcore labor of going
through and really figuring things out
on your own from scratch uh that's one
of the reasons why I created this
another one is like generally speaking
the point of writing GPU kernels or
playing with code at all on the GPU is
to run something faster so if you have a
nested Loop um you know it's like 4 I in
range 4J in range four 4K in range
whatever however many you want to put uh
essentially what parallel programming
and Cuda allow us to do is unroll those
so if you take like for example four ion
range you could take each little thing
in that and run that instruction on a
different CA cor so if you have 10,000
cacor and you have 10,000 different
iterations in your Loop then you can
affect L do each iteration in a single
instruction or a single thread on on the
GPU so this is some of the things that
allows us to do you're going to use your
job of uh you're going to use your your
knowledge of GPU architecture kernel
launch configurations and a bunch of
other cool stuff we end up learning in
this course to make that code run as
fast as possible uh and then the last
one is really there's so much data
nowadays they say we have way too much
data but very little cleaned data I've
taken everything from all the other
video courses everything on the internet
and YouTube uh and I put them in a
single course so I filtered out a bunch
of the nonsense a lot of you know the
old stuff a lot of the new stuff that
maybe isn't covered as well and kind of
just projected into this one Masterpiece
so this includes topics covered by paid
courses as well I haven't actually paid
for them but I kind of just looked at
you know what are the chapters that they
cover and then include some of those
important Concepts in this course um I
do have links for YouTube videos and all
of these resources which I've gone
through only the high quality ones but
I've gone through a lot of these videos
and resources and these are all going to
be uh put in links inside of the um
GitHub Link in the description so
everything you need is going to be there
um and I put a lot of all of those links
in that um in that link so what are some
use cases for Cuda parallel GPU
programming what are some of the use
cases for this well you have graphics
and rate tracing so the computer
Graphics that you're seeing in video
games um you know user interfaces all of
this you have fluid simulation for like
physics um and modeling you know engine
Dynamics you have video editing so the
video that I'm editing for this right
now is using uh parallel Computing to
render uh crypto mining which a lot of
you might be doing already that's going
to be using uh you know your GPU
hardware and some of the advantages of
that to like mine through the the crypto
mining problems and then you have 3D
modeling and software like blender so
when you have a bunch of different
points going on and you have to render
things it's essentially the same as
video editing but just um 3D instead of
2D so the last one which you probably
guessed it already is deep learning so
the number one use case for Cuda right
now is primarily what I'll be covering
in this course which is deep learning so
we're not going to go as as deep into
like say convolutions but uh to kind of
understand how to optimize an algorithm
like matrix multiplication uh we're
going to go quite in depth with that
so now you might ask Elliot what are the
requirements or the prerequisites for
this course so there are some that are
more intellectual and academic and there
are some that aren't so this is strictly
for NVIDIA gpus in case you didn't catch
on to that earlier um if you don't have
one you can always consider renting uh
the cheapest ones in the cloud um I
advise you to look into the pricing
before giving a definite no on the
pricing for some of these Cloud gpus um
at first I was actually surprised how
low the cost was for some cloud
instances um especially the non-comp
compute demanding ones so if you have
like only a CPU or like a ram intensive
machine it might actually cost
significantly less than one with gpus on
it um the gpus one are still very cheap
you can use things like vast AI which
I'll cover a little bit more um you can
use this for actually getting really
cheap uh consumer grade Hardware that
you can SSH into in the cloud um and
then just do all of your experiments and
go through the course on that
you can continue uh you can continue
running with any you know NVIDIA GTX RTX
or data center level gpus so all of the
Nvidia cards are pretty much supported
for this uh maybe like the lower ones
that are like 15 years old those might
not work um but generally if you have
like a GTX like 1660 or something like
that it's like it's going to be fine
um as for course prequisites Python
Programming will help in understanding
while we're implementing in lower
languages so
um just understanding the whole
programming uh Concepts is really what's
going to be needed here again all these
different languages is just like a
change in syntax right so um you know
we're going to use basic differentiation
and Vector calculus uh that'll make
learning easier if you know it already
um it's really only required for
intuition behind back propagation and
some of the stuff we're going to use to
build neural networks from scratch um
linear algebra will definitely make your
life easier by not having to learn
fundamental algorithms from scratch so
like if you're not really intuitively um
you know into matrix multiplication yet
if you haven't really uh you know gone
into that extensively it might be a
little hard for you to catch up uh but
matrix multiplication is very easy it's
quite trivial in retrospect it's very
it's very easy to understand um but just
the intuition there and optimizing it
might be a little hard if you haven't
worked with it a lot already
um then if you really care I would
recommend just reviewing you know Matrix
uh transpose matrix multiplication chain
rule from calculus and then difference
between gradients and derivatives um
there's maybe a few more that I missed
but those are like the general ideas
that you're going to need for going into
this um and then just a heads up uh if
you are in a Windows machine this might
be a little harder for you so I do have
a little setup guide on Windows Hardware
um but I I do everything here on on
Ubuntu Linux so this is what I'm running
uh just on my local machine here and
this is what we're going to go through
the course with um you can always use uh
WSL on Windows to simulate a a Linux
system or you can use uh Docker so
Docker is an awesome tool that'll allow
you to essentially fire up uh a little
simulated Linux machine uh just in your
terminal on Windows and you can just do
everything through that uh I think it
supports Nvidia gpus directly through
Windows I'm not entirely sure yet I
haven't tested that but um if you're on
a Windows machine machine I would
recommend uh WSL or
Docker if you do run into errors or
issues throughout this uh I do suggest
you you check GitHub stack Overflow
Nvidia developer forums pytorch docks uh
if your issu is related to any of this
course material so you know you have a
lot of resources at your disposal if you
need to resolve an error that doesn't
come up in the course material uh you
also have really powerful language
models to use there's a lot of language
models that have been released recently
that are really really good at solving
and addressing coding problem s so I do
suggest you try those out um if all if
all goes wrong right um all the all the
code and notes for this are kept in the
GitHub repo in the description the
ecosystem is going to change all the
time so in case this video isn't up to
date uh the GitHub repo will be because
I'm able to push that and actually make
changes so if something is a little off
in here you might want to go check in
the repo and see like what it actually
looks like so that you can actually
write it properly and maybe there's a
more optimized version thing things will
change but you get the point uh I do
suggest following uh the repo for
maintaining a structured learning
approach I include excal draw diagrams
so this is going to help illustrate like
high level ideas how we're going to
approach things uh as well as how to do
things on the level of Kernel
optimization so all the way top down all
of it excal draw is awesome for
illustrating things and it's completely
free so all the diagrams there will be
included in the in the GitHub repo uh
and in the course too
um you know you can always uh reach out
to me through my Discord server which
will also be in the GitHub repo um and
you can reach out to me through there
and talk with the community there's
going to be a lot of other students
learning there's going to be a dedicated
set of channels for this so in case you
get stuck or wanted to discuss something
or just have a cool chat in the server
uh you can totally join that I do want
to note early on that this course isn't
on Cuda only so there's a few things
that I cover outside of it including
pytorch referencing uh going into like
Triton and c and C++ with like
externally not including Cuda just to
you know help illustrate things on how
how that the naive version of an
algorithm works but uh so there's
there's the code side and then there's
also um I'm going to provide some
prerequisites or not even prerequisites
but rather just uh a good understanding
about the whole deep learning ecosystem
so this is actually what one of the next
chapters is going to be about is how
does the whole ecosystem work and where
can I apply Cuda it would be a little
silly of me to say here's how you
optimize a kernel and make it run really
really fast on your Hardware but not
actually give you some solid use cases
for that so you might already know what
the use case is but in case you're just
trying to learn Cuda and you might look
at some ways that you can apply it I
provide that Resource as well so spoiler
alert but some takeaways you might get
from this course is that through
experiment experimentation and research
you'll learn that the main GPU
performance bottleneck is memory
bandwidth so in deep learning we have
these giant inscrutable matrices that
cannot fit into the onchip memory at
once so think about if you have like a
giant cluster of gpus and each of them
have really really fast tensor cores
these are like super optimized for doing
you know tensor operations in deep
learning um but if you're doing these
across many gpus you really have to
exchange and and and mix and manage
information between them so you end up
sending electrons uh you know from this
node to this node to this node to right
and there's a lot of this communication
that's going on so you really get a ton
of speed from the compute inside of the
chips but when it comes to communicating
there's actually a a pretty big
bottleneck there and that's you know one
thing that you might take away from this
um there's also on chip constraints too
so you have like GPU vram which is going
to be uh you know comparatively slow to
what the on chip stuff is so vram is
like off the actual you know cores and
all this and then it has to communicate
with the cores and all the the the
shared memory on chip and all the
registers and that ends up being a ball
neck too so it's not just the the
massive um the massive matrices
communicating across a lot of gpus it's
actually a lot of the onchip
communication too so there's multiple
bottleneck that that's arise or that
that arise um but these are just things
that you'll end up coming across and and
being able to address later on through
optimizations another key takeaway is
would be to take an existing
implementation and make it faster so a
lot of the times you'll see a new
research paper come out and you'll see a
really cool algorithm but you might not
know exactly how it works and so or or
you maybe know maybe you know how it
works and you just want to make it fast
and you want to integrate it into Pi
torch for example so this is something
we're actually going to do in this
course is we're going to uh we're going
to build up uh an algorithm and we're
going to optimize it and then we're GNA
actually Port it into a pytorch
extension so that you can call it in
Python which is super cool um but just
learning how to integrate your own
research into things to make them faster
to have it operate at production scale
um these are some really important
things that you'll have to do when you
start working you know very deeply with
Cuda um another thing is karpathy LL M.C
a lot of you have probably heard of this
um if you go search up LL M.C
uh LL M.C on uh on you not not on
YouTube on Google um you'll come across
guy named Andre kpoy and he pretty much
built up a giant gbt2 training run in C
from scratch so it uses C and Cuda and
all of it there's a ton of stuff in it
and I really felt like it's hard to
understand that at first um you know as
someone who's not like super super
enriched uh and have having done Cuda
for like 20 years um
it's kind of hard to understand that at
first so having a really nice basis like
this where you can actually understand
how to use Cuda and where the where the
real uh benefits are from it and how to
use it that will allow you to read and
approach kpoe lm. see a little better so
that was one of the reasons why I
actually made this is to make it easier
for people to go into llm Doc and
understand what's going on so in the
GitHub link and the notion document
inside of my GitHub repo uh you will see
this in the intro section so just a
bunch of cool videos on how uh Cuda
Works how Transformers work a bunch of
just really cool fun videos to you know
really get you motivated and upbeat on
uh all of this so got some technical
stuff we got some fun videos by fireship
um but generally speaking these are just
some cool resources you can check out uh
Cuda programming kudam mode is a really
good server actually I highly recommend
you join this it's just a Discord
community of a bunch of people who are
really into Cuda so I believe Andre gpoy
is in here A bunch of really cool uh you
know coders a bunch of Engineers are in
here just to discussing how to uh how to
get certain kernels working and and
generally just Cuda stuff um hence why
it's called cuda mode right so uh really
cool server I highly recommend you join
that as well as my server which is also
in the GitHub repo but that's
that so now we're going to go into a
little bit about the Deep learning
ecosystem right now so obviously this
going this is not going to be up to date
in five years so just you know take this
with a grain of salt this is not uh this
is not everything this is just what I
found interesting to look at and focus
on and and to be aware of in the
ecosystem and how you can sort of
interconnect things and understand
what's going on so this doesn't actually
go over anything highly technical with
Cuda but I thought it's better to show
you the ecosystem rather than just
entering technical details blindly like
if we just dump straight into Cuda
kernels um you won't know how to connect
the dots later on so when we uh when
we're actually building out good
algorithms it's like okay now you have
the skills to do this where do you apply
that so this is this is what that aims
to give you just a bit of background um
understanding the ecosystem will help
you map out everything properly and it
provides that initial motivation to
learn so some parts are going to get
really hard and when you have that
higher level motivation to see like okay
this is what I can actually build once I
learn how to do this instead of just
let's learn Cuda blindly that that seems
a little naive um so going into it with
like understanding what to do later on
or what you can do I think is really
important um again don't feel free uh
don't don't feel binded to just watch uh
watch me talk about a subject for 20
hours um you may limit your learning if
you just force yourself to sit down and
and just just watch and listen to what
I'm saying um I do encourage you to go
down rabbit holes so if you find
something that interests you in this
section or other ones just totally just
go down there that that's where you
learn a ton right um but anyways I've
I've organized this into several
sections so research
production um low level inference for
Edge
Computing ease of
use compilers and
miscellaneous so we start up at the top
here was the easy ones we have pytorch
we have pflow we have Jacks and fireship
has videos on all these These are very
well documented um I'll let you you know
you can kind of just like read through
these I'm not going to go over every
single bullet point cuz it's already
here um but yeah you have you have mlx
developed by Apple for Apple silicon
open source uh for Apple
devices P torch lightning is like P
torch but reduces boiler plate code so
there's a Reddit post here which was
interesting um when you do like when you
set like your tf32 Precision to do
tensor core computations in in pytorch
um like that's boiler plate code so pie
torch lightning is actually going to
reduce that and it's going to remove
that boiler plate so you don't have to
worry about like including all those
little optimizations and and and uh and
hacks so when it comes to production
this is there's typically two things
that fall in here so you have training
and inference and some of these will
support two of them together some of
them will just support one or the other
um so in here we have VM which is quite
interesting um
search a BLM on
GitHub actually go down and we can see
um where did it go yeah LM impr and
serving and then where did it go
performance yeah so performance
Benchmark againsts tensor rtln which is
the next one that I'll actually talk
about here um but they they Implement a
bunch of like very like essentially
Hardware GPU optimizations that we may
talk about later on um
but BLM is great um tensor RT is pretty
much tensor runtime by Nvidia and they
have a tensor RT LM so it's for like
inferencing language models with all of
these you know all these different
optimizations um specifically for llm
inference
now Triton is Triton is something we're
actually going to cover a bit more Tron
was developed by opening eye we go here
you can see
this uh it tells you about like what the
heck Triton is like what the motivation
was where it came from um but if we look
at this paper from Harvard this is
actually where Triton originated from so
try an Intermediate Language and
compiler for child neural net
computations child neural net
computations is the key here this is
where a lot of the performance comes
from and you'll see this later on when
we build fast algorithms tiling is where
you have like a giant problem where
you're you have to do linear algebra
operations like on tensors and you have
to do them fast on parallel uh parallel
processors like gpus and so what you can
do is you can tile The Matrix into a
bunch of little like squares like
subsquares and you can you can multiply
them together so this way you don't have
to do like an entire thing at once and
then reserve it and and worry about all
that stuff you can literally just select
blocks and the parallel processors in
Cuda are extremely good at processing
those blocks because of the Cuda
architecture which we will talk about
later um but but try is interesting this
is a whole paper which I'm not going to
dig into in this course but a lot of
interesting uh both compiler and um you
know speed ups that you get from
approaching things with a with a tiled
um
philosophy
now toor just some other optimizations
we'll get in performance is torch do
compile so you do torch do compile and
then Open Bracket model close bracket
and this will literally just increase
performance 30% out of the box it'll
take that Dynamic graph that P torch
builds and it'll statically it'll snap
it into a static representation for
production because we're using it for
production uh and it'll just apply
optimizations all all around um which we
will dig more into this course like an
example would be like kernel Fusion
where instead of you know doing a
separate function for each for each step
you're like combining two or three
operations into one single function uh
and that like reduces some overhead comp
computation that you have to do there so
uh just a bunch of these little
optimizations that torch talk compile
does uh extremely recommend for
production uh torch script is a little
older but there's an article here on
Torch script
so torch
script um I haven't actually used but
there are some more discussions here
that you can follow um I know it's a
little older so I typically just resort
to Tor shock comp pile for most things
um but it's it's here in case you want
that and then Onyx runtime is also
interesting I should probably should
have put Onyx before Onyx runtime but it
is what it is um Onyx runtime is pretty
much on top of Onyx so you have this
this thing called Onyx which exports a
model from either pytorch or tensor
floor whatever you want down to this
Onyx format that's intercompatibility
uh it's like a Onyx file extension that
you use for storing neural net uh
weights and tensors so uh Onyx runtime
essentially takes that and allows you to
just run it faster so that was built by
Microsoft uh and then a cool little
project I came across and that chat jbt
recommended I put into this course was
detectron 2 so it's uh it's interesting
you might find it useful but um
developed by Facebook and it's
essentially a computer vision library
that uses uh image detection and
segmentation algorithms
so just a bunch of like really cool
computer vision stuff that it has bunch
of different neural net architectures
and hats that it employs and it's just
one of those fun things that you might
want to mess around with um then we go
to low level which is what this course
is based on in case you haven't read the
the the title it's on
Cuda uh Cuda is compute unified device
architect Ure uh programming language uh
programming platform rather for NVIDIA
gpus um and there's a bunch of stuff
which we'll dig into later
um rock M qu equivalent for AMD gpus and
then you have opencl so this is more
General um built for CPUs gpus uh dsps
other types of Hardware so just like a
general purpose Computing language open
open source um and then we have Edge
Computing and embed systems so what the
heck does Edge Computing mean l what is
Edge Computing um think of the Tesla
Fleet that Tesla has so there's a bunch
of cars that are maybe running into
accidents occasionally and so they want
to report this back to the Tesla data
center to train on and improve the
models so you'll have a bunch of these
this essentially this Fleet and the
purpose of edge Computing is to have
them own doing their each of them doing
their own local
computation and then whenever you're do
an update you're just going to send that
back and you're able to have like the
centralized entity that I guess the
centralized data center is our entity
here and it's just going to do some
training on all those on all that new
data and uh that that's pretty much what
it is it's just like a decentralized
Computing if you will um so you know you
have um you have like tensorflow light
which is like a a light version a
lightweight version of tensorflow and
then pytorch mobile is same thing um
what I mean there's always optimizations
you can do in Cuda and like just plain
pie torch that'll just make stuff run
fast either way but there is py mobile
for that um then you have corl which is
for Apple products so like the Mac OS
watch TV all this
um then you have ease of use which isn't
like entirely Cuda related but I thought
I'd still mention this because some of
these are really awesome so you have uh
you have fast AI which I'm not going to
talk about a lot but you can you can
look you can look into this maybe
separately um so they have their own
they have their own thing here but
um yeah I'm not going to I'm not going
to go over fast AI but they uh they have
some interesting
stuff Onyx which we talked about before
stands for open neural network exchange
so the x is capital and that's where the
X comes from um literally you just do
torsa onyx. export model um and then
dummy input and then just whatever the
the file name is so you can look more
into the torch docks and Onyx as to how
to do this on both P torch and
tensorflow and whatever else you want
but this is how you would export an onyx
format
um and then this is the tensor FL
equivalent so this is essentially this
like nice little image that I got where
like it kind of binds with everything so
P toor Tor flow carass um C Cafe which
was which was initially what P torch was
using um Cafe was one of Cafe was one of
those uh original parts in the pytorch
ecosystem um from a while back um so
that that just kind of shows how they
can interconnect together so you like
export in one of these and then you can
import back into any one of these uh
plus Onyx runtime which runs
faster and then you have weights and
biases so I got a little snippet from
the internet as to like what this looks
like but pretty much allows you to track
your training runs and a bunch of
different charts and statistics about
how your models are are performing so uh
when I'm doing like when I want to train
like a clo a clothing uh recognition
model I can literally have all of these
different ones so accuracy on sandals
shirts trousers pullovers boots right
boots is like kind of chaotic and
pullovers just kind of worked fast um
and then this one too so you can kind of
just track a bunch of things and
understand what how your models are
performing and then show that to like
maybe your maybe your uh employer
whatever or whoever is maybe your
manager and just kind of get things done
that way and document things easily
without having to use same matap plot
lib um it's all just kind of tracked and
imported and taken care of for you um
and then Cloud providers these are
actually quite important to know not
necessarily on the lowlevel part of like
Cuda but these are still good to know
because they play a major role in the
ecosystem um you have AWS so AWS is a
major one I personally use aws's
products and prefer them I'm not
endorsing like not sponsoring them but
um not sponsored by them but I do use ad
us products and uh the two main things
here for ML stuff is ec2 instances so
these are like used universally you just
fire up a like a remote machine you can
SSH into it and then do whatever you
want and you can use all the specs like
it's literally uh command line access
and you could do whatever you want um
and then you have Sage maker so it's a
little bit easier and more ml focused
but you can run jupyter notebooks on a
cluster so instead of worrying about a
command line and having having to fire
things up in like um in vs code like VSS
code
SSH you just uh run a jupyter notebook
literally like in the browser or you can
uh just SSH into uh The sagemaker
Notebook I believe um and then you have
the uh the data labeling part which is
very big in the world today so where
does all the data come from that we're
training models on well this is exactly
where it is um if you go AWS sagemaker
and then you find like the the labeling
part or mechanic Turk I believe is
believe is what it's called that's where
all of the labeling on AWS takes place
so uh you know big stuff there uh
typically costs like a decent amount of
money for people to label your stuff but
that's that's where you find it um and
then model training and deployment you
that's that's also supported by Sage
maker so you want to like deploy your
own llama 3 variant it's like go there
you go Sage maker um then Google Cloud I
don't use as much they have vertex Ai
and their VM machines which are like 2
equivalent then you have Microsoft Azure
which I haven't actually used that much
so um it's just like another top three
like these are the top three players in
the ecosystem and then you kind of break
down to open AI fast Ai and Lambda Labs
so open AI provides their own like
fine-tuning services and you can you
know everyone knows open AI you can
literally go on the website and just
navigate around there and figure out
what you want to do with models um fast
AI so I haven't entirely gotten a
picture here yet but if I go to
bass at
AI um I go to the
console hopefully it doesn't expose
anything bad um but like yeah I can
select any of
these it's just like a bunch of rigs
that I can rent for an hourly right get
all the specs on them everything um and
it's great so you know I set RTX 370s
which is like my graphics card and mine
costs about you know 1 cent per hour
which is which is embarrassingly cheap
but uh yeah this one oh this one is more
expensive but yeah so so vastia is
awesome you can use these like any GPU
you can pretty much select it and just
use it on the Fly and it's like hosted
by someone else in the world that you
SSH into and do stuff from
um then you have Lambda Labs which I
sech set
up actually find Lambda here Lambda
Cloud y so
uh data center dgx systems like
literally you have the Blackwell gpus
you have the
h100s um yeah just pretty much GPU
infrastructure specifically um and it's
like I believe a bit cheaper than the
big three providers like AWS Google and
Microsoft so uh Lambda Labs is commonly
used but typically you would rent things
in a cluster so you're paying like
multiple hundreds or thousands or tens
of thousands of dollars per hour for
these so if you're in a company and
you're trying to get like cheap cheap
gpus that are data center quality you
might want to look at Lambda
um and then compilers so I'm not like a
compiler expert but mainly you're going
to have things like xlaa so this is what
is powering Jacks um you're going to
have lvm which I'm not an expert I hav't
build compiler so um I'll let you look
into that there's a ton of resources on
lvm
um it is it stands for low-level virtual
machine I believe
um go to lvm
project
um a toolkit for the construction of
Highly optimized compilers optimizers
and runtime environments
um multiple components um component
compiles C C++ Objective C and objective
C++ code into lvm bit code um and then
into object files so it's essentially
used for developing stuff in cc++ and
compilers and
general then you have ml ml which is
what is ml look at this
again multi-level intermediate
representation so this was uh ML and lvm
were mainly developed by Chris flater
which um I also have a course um on on
the on the programming language that his
company built called modular the
programming language is called Mojo you
can search that up on free code camp and
go learn Mojo too U but it's like a
pretty much just an AI programming
language for doing like Fast tensor
operations
um so this was moved um it's part of the
lvm project and uh there's some
interesting stuff there it's it's
somewhat newer so there's you
know interesting interesting changes
it's not it's not like super ancient
um but uh the main ones that I'll be
able to talk about are like nvcc so
that's like the Auda compiler Nvidia
Cuda compiler
um and you know there's an architecture
here which I haven't like fully
memorized yet but uh the Nvidia Cuda
compiler is what we're what we're going
to be using to essentially compile our
Cuda scripts and kernels and have them
you know into binary so that we can run
them fast so uh you know these are
interesting interesting compiler
infrastructure I'll probably add to this
with some better descriptions on like
what these are but uh this is like the
general overview and then for
miscellaneous I had I could not leave
out hugging face so last but not least
it's like hugging face right um You
probably already know what it is
but I'll look at it up just in case so
on hugging face you have a bunch of
things um you have models data sets uh
and then spaces and that's like pretty
much all you need to know so if you go
to models you
can oh maybe it'll take a second to load
um
here we have multimodal computer vision
MLP audio tabular reinforcement learning
and then graph machine learning so
there's a bunch of cool stuff you can do
here but most of it is language models
right now um I know like recently
released some of
their I believe it's like image Maybe
video Generation stuff I can't remember
specifically but this is where you'll
see all like the new open source models
uh that you can just pretty much
download and run run in P torch like
that uh you just need enough Hardware
you just need good enough Hardware to
run these and it'll just it'll just work
um and then you have the actual data
sets for these models that that you
train them on so um you know you can go
like 3D data sets which is interesting
um a lot of it is just going to be text
so um if I remove
that yeah Vision data awesome Auto math
text so just all these all these data
sets are here that the models are
trained on um and then you have spaces
which is where you can actually use
models um this is where people will like
host things or get sponsors with custom
Hardware setups uh and they'll be able
to just essentially host these models
and you can try them out and use them so
hogging face is awesome it's a major
player in the whole ecosystem and I
could not leave it out
but uh yeah that's that's pretty much it
for the Deep learning ecosystem I'll see
you in the next
part so doing the setup on Windows we
just need to open up our terminal and
run as administrator I'm starting with
Windows uh we just enable permissions
ensure that it's the system 32 directory
going to navigate get over to the turn
Windows features on and off um we're
going to scroll up and look for
hyperv um ensure that box is checked off
and then we're going to look for virtual
machine platform ensure that is checked
off and then or checked on rather and
then you have a Windows subsystem for
Linux make sure that's also checked on
um in order to get this working you will
need uh to enable virtualization on your
machine
so uh you know once the windows
subsystem is on you can do wl. exe and
you'll see you know a bunch of options
so install distribution and we see an
example there WSL install distribution
Yu we can go ahead and enter enable and
we'll just wait for that to complete
I've sped this up a little bit because
it takes some time uh realistically it
takes more than you know a few seconds
to do this so I'll speed some of these
things up
um you has been installed
awesome changes will not be effective
until system is rebooted um yeah so we
run it again um we have this command
that it's asking us to run so WSL exe
install no distribution that installs
correctly um and we get the same thing
again so we just do a system
restart now after we've restarted you
might be greeted with this
terminal uh your BTU and then uh the
other command prompt so when you're
greeted with that if you're just greeted
with the command prompt you do
WSL uh and you can get into here and
just enter a username and a password
that you're going to use now you should
be logged into your uh little simulated
uh Linux environment so once we're in
here there's a few commands we need to
run so we're going to update and we're
going to upgrade everything so just type
in the commands as you see them there's
some that we're going to be able to copy
and paste in so just end that password
you set earlier I've time-elapsed this
not time-lapsed but I've sped this one
up again so that was just a bunch of
things uh updating um if we go and
install some other packages that we'll
need later like WG curl and git we'll
see that those are also installed as a
part of the update and upgrade
commands um and then we just install
Python 3 pip uh this is just going to be
python essentially for our machine and
uh that also runs too so that does not
come by default apparently um so we just
need to install that manually but that's
okay we navigate over to Chrome and we
search Up Cuda toolkit this is what
we're looking for Cuda toolkit download
so you just navigate to the latest one
it might be 12.5 it might be 12.6
whatever it is for you go to Linux pick
your architecture and use WSL you to
remember we're using uh WSL and then
just do the run file it's the easiest
one least amount of instructions you
have to do um so so going to do the
first one so w get uh you can just right
click in the terminal if normal pasting
doesn't work
um let's maybe highlight the whole
thing awesome so that's going to take
some time to upgrade and uh I'll see you
guys on the other side okay so now we're
in the little accept part so just only
check off the to Cuda toolkit there and
then you should be good to install
now we've done the runsh file which was
the second part of the command and it
tells us in the summary that we need to
add some things to our path so I've just
pulled up this here um but this wasn't
really working too much so I went off
and generated some other uh you know
more upto-date commands with chat GPT uh
and figured out uh the act the the
proper ones
so you'll see those in a second here
once I pulled them up but this is just
the this is just a reference so this is
one of the things we have to do so we
could just Vim into our bash RC file um
and then I'll just just pretty much type
along with me here and then we'll we'll
save this file so feel free to use Nano
or Vim whatever whatever you feel
comfortable with I'm using Vim here but
uh you know Nano isn't too hard either
so going to set a Cuda home um user
local Cuda and then we're going to
export another one uh called path and as
a part of that path um we're just
essentially going to include Cuda home
and then the binary for
that and then last but not least um
we're just going to export the LD
Library like it also said in the
summary and then lip 64 to end it
off awesome so now we can just contrl C
contrl W and contrl
Q or col w q we exit that um and then we
can oh I noticed we missed something so
Cuda 12.5 instead of just Cuda um so we
can go ahead and go back into this and
then just find that part and add
um and just right click and paste that
back in and then just delete the last
Cuda part awesome
C 12.5 sweet now we can just exit that
again and
Source then we just do nvcc uh-- version
which is the Nvidia Cuda compiler so
that's working and then Nvidia s SMI so
we can actually track our GPU stats as
long as these are both working um we've
done the job correctly so if you're not
get if you're getting errors with nvcc
or
nvmi uh that's that's not good you need
to figure that out uh I don't of course
cover all the errors but
um that aside we're going to go ahead
and set up a little Cuda test just to
make sure that everything's working
properly and that we can execute a docu
or Cuda script so I just made a
directory called cuda setup test and
we're going to just Vim into um that
that directory and we're going to edit
and we're going to make a new main. cuu
file and inside of here I'm just going
to go ahead and paste uh some functions
so uh we include the Cuda runtime header
we include the io stream which is a part
of C++ that allows us to use things like
C out we declare the namespace STD for
for standard and then we see out hello
world in our in main function so if we
do nvcc um out main binary and then
main. cuu we should uh be able to run
this binary and get Hello World
awesome so if this works first try for
you that's awesome if it didn't that's
not so awesome but but you should be
able to figure it out just by navigating
uh forums so like GitHub the stuff I
recommended before just navigate around
and figure out how to install the Cuda
toolkit for Windows um it pretty much
applies the same to yuntu I'm going to
go over some brief instructions here but
I'm going to switch over to Ubuntu
because that's what my whole thing is
based on that's where I do all of my
stuff and where everything is set up and
optimized for so I'll see you on the
other side if we can go ahead and open a
Chrome tab here and just type in Cuda
toolkit downlo
mod so we go to this one on your BTU
same thing we go Linux x64 is mine might
be different for you um
YouTu this
one run file local um you can do this
you can also do Network or local so for
me I did network but that was a little
while back and having to uninstall it
and then reinstall it again just gives
me a bunch of weird Graphics uh errors
so I'm not going to do that and mess
with my operating system too much but
you should be able to just plug this
directly into terminal so you should be
able to just pop into here and uh plug
these in W get the uh the Debian file um
and then just the rest of this and
install the Cuda toolkit and then just
get the the Legacy Cuda drivers I just
did this this Legacy Cuda drivers if
that doesn't work do this one um and
then you would of course want to just do
do um nbcc version and then Nvidia SMI
and you should see uh some useful stuff
pop up here so uh if that if these don't
work for you right away um you know you
might want to just restart your computer
that's usually the best option and then
try something again um if you do already
have these installed you don't even have
to worry about it so I would probably
check these first probably should said
that first but uh yeah Ure uh the Auda
compiler works and then Nvidia
SMI so now we can finally get into some
coding um in order to really understand
how to use Cuda you need to First cover
C and C++ so this course isn't actually
about C and C++ so I'm just going to
provide some resources for you guys to
learn this stuff and then I'll jump into
more some more advanced topics uh just
to watch over and and review the
subjects so for those of you who are new
to this stuff for those of you who are
new to lowlevel C C++ Cuda programming
um I have some resources for you some
good articles some good uh things to
manage through and if you are already
experience uh just pretty much skip this
part or even even still look at it to
maybe touch up on the basics and I'll
cover some more advanced topics right
after this so learning C and C++ is hard
and so you really have to Define what
the best resources are and how to
actually learn things properly what is
the best use of your time right this is
a common dilemma that we have so I came
across a Reddit article on best
resources to learn C++ and it it pretty
much said learn C+ plus.com plus a bunch
of other links that you might like so
learn C+ plus.com is good I've never
used this before so I don't know how
comparatively good it is um so that
that's an option of course and then
there's best way to learn C so looking
through this I pretty much found that
Everyone likes the um the modern C this
one C programming a modern approach so
it's a it's a newer book um but that's
how people found best way to learn to C
um if you are just trying to learn this
for free and try to you know just go
through the syntax and understand it as
quickly as possible um there are some
resources I would recommend and have
looked through a little bit so freed
code camp has some good stuff on this um
C programming just a bunch of uh blogs
essentially on how to just pretty much
just learning the language and then you
have
C++ uh just you know maybe some more
advanced things um you know
libraries a bunch of modern C++ stuff um
so free code Camp is a great resource
and then the one that I've personally
stuck with for a long time and continue
to use is W3 schools so it's pretty much
like a nice easy to read easy on the
eyes documentation on or just an intro
rather on how to use C and C++ so I have
both here um I'd recommend if you're new
to this just look over each of these and
do do a bunch of practice questions on
every single one of these um all these
are super important there there's some
of them you might not actually use
explicitly in the course but it's still
good to know it regardless just for you
know having that uh you know lowlevel uh
brain so that you can dissect problems
with uh on Cuda applications that we may
not cover in this
course so I'd recommend just like
looking through all of these go down all
the way to like these examples um like
everything and then same with C++ as
well so all all your Basics your
functions your classes um and then down
to examples as well so uh that's that's
pretty much all I have for the basics of
CN C++ now we're going to go ahead and
touch on pointers
we're going to start off with pointers
if you go to github.com
inosi Cuda course um and then pop over
to well you're not going to pop over to
Dev this is going to be all pushed up
and ready once you once you're seeing
this but uh essentially you're just
going to get C this into a directory of
your choice uh and then we can go and
get started with the c and C++ review so
I have this all in my vs code here and
it's all zoomed in and nice for you to
see but um we we'll start off with a
symbol pointer example
so uh we initialize an integer integer X
to 10 this a data this is the data part
of X um and then we initialize a pointer
type so this asteris uh that means we're
doing a pointer to an integer uh and
we're setting that we're setting the
name equal to pointer and then this uh
Ampersand is saying we're going to get
the memory address of X so we have X
here which is 10 and the ENT says uh
we're going to get the memory address of
of X which is um which is going to be
the pointer to 10
um and then we can we can just print
this out so if I go GCC and we do
Z 01 and then run that you'll see that
we get an address so I have the pointer
I have the pointer type here there's
there's an index where you can find
these um if I pull up a tab here and go
uh Point uh print f
uh like in for
example so you have all these different
things here on C+ plus.com that you can
use um and these are just like the
formats and stuff
so we have uh we have a
pointer it's this value that we're
returning uh we get a memory address to
the value 10 and to get 10 we're passing
in pointer and then we do the asteris to
dreference it so dfference means uh we
we have this essentially we have this
data thing which is 10 we have the
memory address to 10 which is the level
above and E reference is just going to
go downwards just going to go back to
back to that so we have this memory
address just dreference and go back to
10 um the next example here is a little
bit tricky um but it's fine it's it's
relatively intuitive so I don't expect
it to be that hard but essentially what
we're doing is we initialize a value to
42 and then we make a uh a pointer an
integer pointer type called pointer one
and we set that equal to the memory
address of value so it's ersan memory
address of value um so it's going to be
like 42 and then we create pointer 1
which is a memory address or a pointer 2
42 and then we do the same thing so we
make a pointer to a pointer which is
what the double asteris is for uh and
then we do again Amber sand of pointer
one so memory address of this pointer so
then you have 10 you have 42 and then
you have memory address which is the the
you have the pointer to uh 42 then you
have another one above that which is
pointer to a pointer to to a value and
then we just do that another time so
it's pointer to a pointer to a pointer
to a value um and uh this logic checks
out and when we print this out we're
going to return the integer type so D um
and then we're just going to Triple D
reference it so we have these multiple
different layers so we're going up a
pointer like level one pointer level two
pointer level three and D referencing is
just like going down a level so we go
down one two three levels and back to
back to that value of 42 which is an
integer and we can safely return that so
if I just go GCC and then compile
02 we go and run that and we get a safe
output value 42 awesome so now I pop
over to number three which is where
things start to get a little bit weird
uh and initially this was kind of a
funky topic for me as well but this is
this is void pointers so void pointers
are a little funny and they actually
allow us to do a lot of tricks that uh
allow for things like polymorphism and
stuff um but we're not going to go over
that a ton that's that's like other uh
that's not covered in this review uh so
we initialize an integer called num to
10 we initialize a float called f num
equal to
3.14 um and then we have this this void
pointer so what this means is like if
you had an integer and then an asteris
that would mean it's a pointer to an
integer but void is no type so it's like
a pointer to no type and that means we
can actually change which type it is
pointed to which is a cool little
feature that you can do in C um so we
say um void pointer is going to equal
the memory address of num which is this
right um and then what we can do here in
this in this print part we essentially
uh we take this we cast it to an INT
pointer type that's what this part is
for these brackets and then inside the
int and then after the Asis the the
pointer cast and then we dreference that
so we have a void pointer which we cast
to an
integer we cast to an integer type it's
originally holding the memory address of
int
um and then we dreference that after
it's casted so it's going to go up to
this memory address then it's going to
go back to 10 which is the value of
num and then we essentially just do the
same thing for this F num here um I I
have nice little descriptions here that
you can read on your own uh and and then
a fun little fact so Malik actually
returns a void pointer but we see it
point to a specific data type after the
cast so
what you typically see Malik as like
these these opening brackets uh these
this brackets and then you have the
actual cast inside of it so what we did
over here is what you see in Malik so
it's actually returning a void pointer
and then you cast that to a specific
like integer or a floating Point uh
pointer um and and then you can use that
for something like like an array um so
if we go ahead and just GCC compile this
and then run we get our integer which is
uh integer type of course and then we
get our our float 3.14 which is a uh
which is a float type so void pointers
are not not void pointers sorry null
pointers are really interesting and you
probably found void pointers interesting
as well um but these are a little bit
different so null pointers can actually
make our code more robust through if
statements um going remove those binary
files for now to clean some space up um
but we we initialize a pointer to null
um if we try to print this out um it's
it's going to essentially return like
there's nothing right there's like no
space actually here there's nothing that
you can't you can't use that pointer for
anything because it's null that's the
whole idea here so what we can do is we
can check if the pointer is equal to
n um and then we just essentially just
report that maybe we throw an error
message or we we we put a warning up uh
cannot dreference this right if the
pointer doesn't have anything you can't
dreference nothing to something you
can't do that so uh we actually change
that up and we we allocate memory uh to
pointer so to this pointer so that we
can use it safely later on so uh I'm
just going to actually compile this so
you can so you can see what it's
doing um initial pointer value is nil so
we have the pointer type we cast to a
void pointer which is going to be n null
of course so n that checks out pointer
is null cannot D reference good so this
this was
true after allocation so this is where
we get into this part Malik is going to
return uh a void pointer the size of int
so that means there is actually
something there now there there is
something there it doesn't have an
explicit data type but we have something
there that's like in I think 32 bits so
four bytes um and then we check if
pointer is equal to n again um and it
doesn't print memory allocation failed
so that's that's good and then we get to
number four after allocation pointer
value is this so we cast this to a uh
void pointer uh and we can actually see
this this this memory address we can
actually see that it works um and then
we can you know we we know that this
exists now so we can use it for
something so um we we essentially check
it for null safe to use now uh and then
we have this uh we have this dreference
pointer so you dreference that memory
address back to the data part and we set
that equal to 42 so now you have this uh
safe to use um you have this you safe to
use memory address and the data
associated with that memory address and
then we can free that pointer um set to
n after freeing uh and then we see that
it's it's it's null again so uh yeah if
pointer is null so we we know that it is
null safely avoided use after free
awesome so the the whole point here is
that we can use no pointers to uh do
little tricks and we can make our code
Mar
by checking if it is null we can avoid
running into unexpected errors like seg
faults and other weird things that are
hard to trace back right sometimes you
don't want to have to go through all of
that just to figure out an error so it's
better to just uh write more robust code
in the first place and ensure that it
works properly so in this example
there's quite a few things going on here
but I'll try to I'll try to explain this
as best as possible so we have an array
uh we just declare an integer array five
numbers and then we have an uh pointer
an integer pointer equal to array so in
C because we're just leaving it as AR
Ray alone it's going to point to the
first element uh because that's that's
how memory is lined up right it's going
to point to essentially where does this
thing start uh and that's going to be
that's going to be 12 of course but we
know that an array is a pointer on its
own if we don't dreference or if we
don't index that array um it's just
going to be a pointer alone right so if
I if I print f
uh and then we go we just go
array sure I'll let get up co-pilot
complete
that not not correct
yeah we'll see that this array if we
don't dreference it uh just just on its
own it is a memory address it's a
pointer to this array um so we set We
Set uh let me just delete that we set
uh an an integer pointer equal to that
so that's a that's a memory address that
we have um awesome now we look at our
position one which I printed out that's
going to be 12 so we have that that
start of the array in memory uh and then
we just dreference that number so it
goes back to
12 that's what this asteris is for and
we print as the the integer
type awesome now we have a for Loop
going on here so what the heck is this
doing we have we have I starts at zero
we want to stop it uh uh when whenever
it go whenever it equals 5 we stop it
and then we increment by one each time
so inside of here we have an integer
type and that's going to be the D
referenced pointer so whatever pointer
is we're going to dreference that back
to the original value that it was um and
then in here we're going to do the
pointer type of the actual pointer
itself so this is the memory address
that we're seeing um and then we're just
going to increment this each time each
time this for Loop goes we're going to
iterate it once and we're going to
increase we're going to increase uh
pointer which is the memory address
we're going to increment that
so uh I had a little example here that I
wrote out um these obviously won't be
like the same examples every time uh
they're going to be different but uh
notice how this pointer is incremented
by four bytes right so this is is not in
uh bits this is in bytes so if we do
eight bits in a bite times 4 bytes we
get 32 bits which is the integer 32 type
the classical integer
32 so hopefully it makes a little bit
more sense now about how memory is laid
out uh at least on the CPU so yeah we
just have these essentially skipped by
four bytes every time uh 4 bytes time 8
bits per BTE is 32 bits and we get our
n32 from that I also make a point that
uh well right now pointers are not in 32
bits in size but we'll see why having
them as in32 right now can be a major
issue so if you actually do um if we go
Python and we do 2 to the 32 we'll get
this number so look how big this is this
is uh 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 uh 9 so that's
that's about
4.2 that's about 4 GB um in po of 2 of
course that's 4 GB so if you have say 8
gab of memory which isn't actually that
much on this machine I actually have 64
so I have 64 GB of memory taken up by
like a single array I mean that
obviously wouldn't happen that's a
really large array but let's just say I
have like one that's like you know 64 GB
long well we're actually going to get
overflow when we try to index that way
so you're going to see later on that
it's more useful to use uh a certain
type for these pointers so if we do 2 to
the 64 so u a double Precision integer
so N64 you'll see that this is like
extremely massive um this is
like I don't know somewhere in the
exabytes it's like ridiculously high
um yeah just we we're we're going to
deal with this later but right now this
is the general intuition for how uh how
these pointers are printed out so if I
scroll up a little bit you'll just see
uh we print out the dereferenced pointer
um at that uh essentially take that
memory address and then we dreference it
based on the index that it currently is
so we just bump up the index one we we
jump ahead 32 bits or four bytes and
then we print that that value out uh
each time and you see that vertically
here um I just
maybe run that again after it's cleared
you'll see that it's it's just like
vertically just skips ahead as we'd
expect and then this pointer uh which is
just the that memory address and then I
just put this out for testing sake you
don't need to worry about that um but
yeah this is the general intuition on uh
how how these things are laid out in
memory so number six is an interesting
one it kind of goes back to example
number two where we have this uh we have
this value and then pointer pointer
pointer just Stacks up uh that that's
essentially what sixes so we have these
two arrays array 1 and two and they're
essentially just these vectors or these
these these arrays 1 2 3 4 and then we
have an array to uh 5 6 7 8 uh and then
we just have an integer pointer uh to
those arrays um and then we store
another you could say array I just name
it Matrix to differentiate and we store
those pointers uh essentially on top of
each other so what it looks like is we
have this we have this Matrix so it's
pointer one and pointer two pointer one
is the uh it's the it's the pointer to
that array the array one and then
pointer two is the is the memory address
for for array two so essentially what we
have it is if we if we look at this uh
this array of of like this Matrix it has
pointer one pointer two if we flip it so
instead of like this and this we we
stack them on top of each other so it's
pointer one then pointer two it actually
looks like a matrix so you'll have your
array one which is 1 two 3 4 and then
one underneath which is five six seven8
and so it actually is like a it's it's
like a grid right uh and if we iterate
through this
um
oh you'll actually see um we just
essentially iterate through these so uh
we we we do J and four uh and we we
print out the D reference Matrix at
position I so that position I is going
to give a memory address for
uh it's going to be you know number two
uh which is going to be these two arrays
um and then we're going to dreference
that which is going to give us our
actual values and then we're going to
iterate this each time of course as the
for Loop goes on um and then we just do
a next line so that it looks nice nice
so that's uh that's pretty much all I
have for pointers we're going to jump
into custom types now which is more what
I was talking about for this for these
weird pointer sizes um we're going to
dive into
this so now I'm going to show you pretty
much the equivalent of the torch dot
long type so you might have seen this
before if you're you know I assume you
have some knowledge of python and
pytorch so I figured that's the best way
to illustrate this we have this size T
this size _ T this is typically how you
you write this out in C is you'll have
uh whatever the type is and then you'll
have underscore T to say that this is
like a custom type that you made T is
for type um and this is specifically for
U like big big numbers right so the idea
here is this is going to be an unsigned
long so
uint uh long
so int it's going to be a uint 64 that's
what it's going to be um if we do this
in in torch you'll
see I python import torch and then we
can make
X this just an array of integers uh and
then we go x. dtype we'll see a torch.
N64 so it's just like that 64 uh bit
Precision that we want to store really
big really big matrices right so
especially in Cuda when you have uh like
really really big tensors that are
occupying like multiple gigabytes um
like on my GPU I have 8 gigabyt of
storage so if we're using
in32 uh that you might get some overflow
errors or you might get some just some
some unexpected bad behavior that is
going to like mess with things so you
don't necessarily want that and that's
the whole point of the size type um I
kind of wanted to show you that this
isn't so bad after all so you know just
to step through this we have we have the
same array that we went over last time
we do this size T type um we use size
and then size of array divided by uh
divided by the size of an individual
integer so it's like the total size of
this uh entire thing divided by the uh
the size of each individual thing in it
so you get the total length of the array
um uh and so if we go 01 I already
compiled this uh you'll see we get that
five right so there's five elements in
here uh we print this size out um I'll
go over this this Zu part in a second
here um but we get that output five and
then this eight um we print out the size
of this so that's in uh that's in bytes
by the way we we when we do a like size
of int we if we do like let's see print
F uh we'll just say int
size uh and then we'll
go uh sure in in bites we'll do that uh
if I just compile this
again we'll see int size and bytes so
this is an
int32 this just just an in32 and it's
four bytes or 32 bits so when we have
this that means it's 64 bits just to put
that in perspective there so uh when we
go to this size T we'll see it's an
unsigned type def so we do a type
definition unsign so it's a it's only
going to be positive because we're
storing like a you know you can't have
like negative size that's the logic and
then we have this long which means it's
going to be uh it's going to Lally tell
the operating system where we we want 64
bits not 32 we want it to be long um and
then just the the size T type so we can
actually go into this and we can see oh
type def size type and then we make this
we declare this thing where does this
come from oh right here long unsigned
integer boom just like that super easy
right
um and uh I guess to sort of clarify
like what the whole deal is here we
could just pop back to this link if I
just open it on my second screen here
and pop it over
oh uh we can search for
the I'll make this a bit bigger I don't
know can I make it bigger there we go so
if I go up uh we'll see that we have
this uh we have this we have this Z and
then we have the U so Z is
uh Z is just going to be uh I can't
remember exactly what this was for but
uh then we have this U which is
essentially just the unsigned in right
so it's U is unsigned um and then we
have this size T type which is what the
which is what the Z is for um and then
we just we just map that out so uh you
know if we had a uh if we had just a
regular integer it would still be size T
because you can have you know it's still
an integer you can do stuff with it but
when we have a u uh then you know it's
just kind of explicitly you're going to
have this size T type so that that's
kind of how we M things there and we can
use the Z followed by the U uh to
properly print that out to print out the
type of that so you know you have all
these other ones too like uh pointer
diff
type uh but that's that's generally the
intuition
there and then next up I just wanted to
cover uh declaring your own custom types
so you know we saw one in the in the
standard uh C library the standard iio
uh uh C library the standard definition
Library whatever you want to call it the
headers um and it's also important that
we can declare our own because we might
even we might need to use these and we
actually will use these later on in the
course so typically how it goes is you
do this thing called a type def uh which
is a type definition and for let's just
say we're going to make a point for
example it has an X and A Y and their
floating Point values so we do this
struct which is going to have some
elements inside of it it's going to have
some it's going to have some of these I
guess objects you could say these items
uh and it's going to have a float X and
a float Y and then we declare we we say
this is going to be a type point we do
type definition uh it's going to be a
struct and we're going to make that a
point type essentially and then inside
of our int main here since this is
already declared we can say a point type
like you know you could like you would
do an INT P or something we're just
replacing replacing int or whatever that
type is with point and we're making that
variable named p and then we're
populating it with some values here so
this is going to be our float X and our
float y um and then if we go uh you know
size of Point here if I just compile
this and then run uh you'll see size of
point is
eight so 8 bytes is four bytes plus four
more bytes so each of these is a float
32 number that occupies four bytes in
memory so when you add these together it
occupies a total of eight bytes so this
point this point uh type is going to
cover uh 8 bytes or 64 bits in memory um
and then just this other C++ script is
literally the identical to this so you
can you can declare things the exact
same way in um in C++ except you might
just want to use like the io stream
instead of uh like you maybe in C++ you
would comment this out and you would go
uh include uh IO
stream and and then you would use uh
using namespace
STD and then you would uh then you would
see out
that
oh identifier SE is
undefined okay I guess not I don't know
why that's not working um but but you
get the point so very minimal changes so
now if we pop over to type casting uh I
have two files in here so just a just a
single C file and then a read me so
inside here I have uh static cast
Dynamic cast uh constant casts and
reinterpret cast so we're only going to
be covering these static cast because
these are the safe ones these are mainly
what you're going to end up using if any
um so in here it it's it's very simple
you have just a like say a floating
Point number
6969 and then we have we just declare an
INT and all we do is just have this F
and then we do brackets int
we we put these we just literally put
this right in front of it and that'll
statically typ cast uh the float 69.6 n
to an INT and what this will do is it'll
just truncate that last part so in
memory in essentially in binary and bits
it'll be laid out as um it'll have that
first part so the first uh the first
integer piece and then it'll have the
decimal and then it'll have the uh it'll
have the it'll have the decimal bits
afterwards so it'll it'll be like that
decimal and then after so what it'll do
is when it's when it's typ casting it'll
just uh truncate this part and then give
give us more Precision for these uh for
these essentially int 32 bits so uh it
that that's essentially all it's going
to look like it's it's just going to be
69 uh it's not going to have any decimal
places it's going to effectively round
down you could say um so if I just pop
into
uh type
casting
and run
this you'll see uh we get this integer
format so just truncated and then when
we do a character um this is actually
going to convert to uh asky so if you
remember your asky tables I'll go ahead
and bring this up on the side
here asky table
uh oh it's right literally right there
okay ask.com
um we can
see that this one right here is an
uppercase E
right
so uppercase
E uppercase E look at that how how easy
was that right it's not not crazy doing
an integer to a character conversion so
that's that that's all type casting is
I'm not going to go over this
extensively cuz it isn't like a crazy
piece we end up using in Cuda but just
to throw it out there and remind you
guys of how how simple this type of
thing is another topic I thought was uh
briefly worth touching on was macros and
Global variables so we can we
essentially have these these basic ones
like uh you know if if defined if not
defined L if else and then end if uh so
it it's we're essentially going to use
these later on to declare
hyperparameters and uh just different
Global things that we'll need access to
that we don't want to just pass in as an
extra you know bloated function argument
when you have like 20 arguments in a
function you might want to reduce that
and just declare some of those locally
so you can use them wherever you want as
long as they're not changing or you're
not doing anything weird with them
you're you're okay right so like in this
example I do uh Pi like uppercase pi and
then we set that equal to uh a double
right so
uh we can do these functions too so it's
kind of like a a Lambda function if you
will a Lambda function in Python we do
this area and then we we pass whatever
we want in so R is our radius and then
we do essentially the the radius is piun
r^ 2 so we just do PI * R * R and we get
that so it's just a little Lambda
function you can do as a macro um and
then we have if not defined radius so
radius isn't defined here if and DEP if
not defin um theine radius and we set
that value to seven so it's going to be
an integer seven we end the if we end
this this whole block and radius is a
now a declared maer equal to
seven uh and then we have some if logic
down here so if radius uh you know it's
bigger than 10 which is not we Define
this so this this is like grade out um
it's not smaller than five also grade
out and then else U so it's just going
to stay at seven and then it's going to
end if so we can do if logic in here as
well
um and then if I just go ahead and pop
out of this to uh macros and we go
GCC like
this we're going to oh
double we'll do uh
perfect so area of circle with radius 7
um is going to be this much and that's
that's a floating Point number which we
have here so uh this radius I I was not
careful there this radius is actually an
integer type so we just set that back to
D um and then it then it works Bel ly so
uh that's that's how you do uh macros
pretty easy this part is where my
understanding gets a little bit fuzzy I
haven't worked with compilers
extensively but I have found some really
good resources on uh the C and C++
compilers so I've just provided some
links here for you to go learn um GCC is
the most popular C compiler so that's
gnu uh C compiler um and then g++ is the
same thing but for C++
so uh you know I have different articles
on here from free code camp that you can
go and look at so uh there's there's
this one and then we have the other one
as
well what does a compiler explain for
beginners um so like an analogy
essentially just converting uh
converting your machine code down to uh
down to assembly and and you have all
these representations in between that
that the computer work with to help
understand things better uh and then
it'll convert that assembly code down to
uh essentially the uh CPU instructions
in uh in bits and bytes so binary ones
and zeros uh and that'll get sent
through as as essentially electrons and
charges through your through your
circuitry in the computer and that is
what actually executes this stuff um and
then just the C C++ compiler is a little
bit
uh might be a little bit higher level I
know C++ is a higher level language than
c um but this these are just like really
good explanations that I can't really
top myself without messing up so I
provided these links here um hopefully
this all makes sense but uh we won't
really need to understand too much about
compilers Downstream it's good to know
what they're doing but in order to debug
code you just need to know kind of the
architecture of what the compiler is
what it's doing like where it's where
it's stuff not necessarily like all the
math and representations happening um
it's good to know of course but it's not
needed to write functioning code so uh
we'll see that later on like we're just
going to essentially type in these
compiler flags and and all this and that
that's what the next section on actually
is uh it's on make files so make files
are really useful they're going to help
you uh be more efficient about
developing C C++ and Cuda code so
instead of going into here and just
typing uh you know GCC every single time
and maybe maybe you have autocomplete
like me but either way you just want
this to be a faster process and you want
to be able to automate and and have more
control over what happens uh and just
manage things better make files is what
you want so inside of make files it it
looks really complicated and it's like
learning this new language but it's
really not it's not that bad um you can
Define variables so like GCC equals GCC
and in order to use these uh I can just
do dollar sign and then brackets and
then put that variable inside the
variable name inside and it'll just
pretty much reference this when it's
called um this is a command by the way
so you'll we'll see this in a second um
I'm going to do a little experiment with
the Cuda script here but we just have
this nvcc maaps to the Nvidia Cuda
compiler and then we have Cuda Flags so
this is just a little thing that's like
my GPU architecture we're going to see
this later you don't have to worry about
this now but this is just like U my GPU
architecture is a uh 8.6 compute
capability uh or
compute compatibility I think it's
capability um either way this is just we
could just have flags and we can just
have more variables that we plug into
this stuff but if I go back to the read
me for
this we have these targets prerequisites
and then our commands nested inside of
that so how does this work exactly well
I'm going to show you this um just by
pretty much example so um if I
go if I go I can actually delete this
line if I just go make
01 see how it makes a binary here and
then I can run this binary and it'll say
boo this this print F just it just
prints boo like it works um just from
make 01 so what we're doing is we have
this make Command which is for make
files kind of maps the there and then we
have the 01 part which is the target so
this this is the target this is left
side of the colon and then after is
their prerequisites so notice how I I
removed that that other part the
01c so this essentially means we're
going to uh either confirm that this is
that this already existed or has been
done um and if it hasn't we're going to
do it so you'll see that in these
examples down here but
just to fill in the rest so we have a
bunch of things happening we have this
we have this variable GCC which is just
saying you know it's it's essentially
just going uh you know
GCC um it's just doing that and then we
put this at sign in front of
it which means don't print this out in
the terminal so if I just uh remove this
and
go uh and just remove the at
and go uh
clean I'll just I'll just remove this
for for so that it makes the most
sense and then I go make uh 01 you'll
see that it actually uh shows us this in
the terminal um but if I put an at there
then it doesn't right so that just
removes it that just makes things more
clean and just it's like a best practice
just easy to see things um you want to
maybe like look at the ones that uh
might do weird things and you just want
to like ensure that all your variables
are correct um but this is a very simple
you don't need to print this out um and
then just jumping down to uh like number
two here
so uh number two is uh essentially the
same thing
so uh I'm not even going to execute that
we don't we don't even need to run this
um and then 03 is just the ca compiler
so we do nvcc and then the Cuda Flags so
which essentially what it's going to
look like is it's going to go
nvcc Das Arch
uh get rid of that and then um it's
going to pass in
O
03 CU that that's the binary we want it
to be and then
that that's going to run and we should
be able to go 03 C and it's going to say
boo from here right so just just the
same thing um we just include like Cuda
runtime and all this just to be fancy
but it just it just outputs the the boot
the boot
command
um yeah this this is a this is very
simple example so it's essentially just
converting uh it's converting these
variable names and not printing anything
out
um we just go make 03 and it'll do the
exact same thing see it takes a little
while
same exact thing um we have this clean
command which is going to actually
remove all these binaries so when we
want to clean up everything uh and just
you know make it nice and presentable
like we haven't done work like what I'm
doing with you guys is I'm deleting
these binaries before doing the lessons
uh because it looks ugly when I have
more files so I can just go uh make
clean gone right um so that that's just
like a very very simple example and it's
just it's just like make and then
whatever the target is uh going back up
to these
ones these are a little interesting
so 01 uncore obj which is for object
this is going to uh
GCC uh comp uh it's going to take in
this C code and it's going to Output uh
this o or this object file so it's going
to it's going to essentially this but
it's just going to do object file
instead of a binary um and then this 01
uh obj so this object uh execute
run that's going to take in this this
previous one as a prerequisite so that
means this one has to already be
complete and if it's not complete we're
going to run it and make sure it's
complete in order for this to work so uh
we're going
to uh compile this object file into a
binary so you have the this like the C
the C representation and then the object
file which we do uh here and then this
one takes that new object file and
converts that into a binary and then we
execute that binary on this line so if I
go uh make and then 01 uh obj ex uh
execute
run and we don't have any of these files
in
here it's going to
it's literally going to uh ensure that
this is called first because it hasn't
yet um so it's going to it's going to
convert this C file into object and then
it's going to convert that object into a
binary and it's going to execute that
binary so this is just I probably overe
explain things a little bit but this is
this is pretty much the idea on how you
uh how you can automate uh just C
compilation C++ compilation we're going
to use this more for uh Cuda scripts
down the road
uh but that's that's the general idea
and then this phony part at the top
might look a little weird but this
essentially means uh we're not we're not
going to uh it's just like a a a way to
make uh things easier to use make it so
you don't run into errors I had a decent
explanation here so um say we had a make
file make file with a Target named clean
so in this in this cleanup command that
that makes everything nice again suppose
we have a directory named clean in the
same directory as the make file so here
if we had something named clean um if we
run make clean make will not run the
command um it will not run the command
in the Target clean because clean
already
exists instead it will see that the
director clean already exists will not
it'll not run it so in short we
essentially take a bunch of mappings
from Target names to
commands um that's that's where this
phony thing comes from so it's like a
it's like a phony if you will I don't
know what the philos was behind that
naming but that's that's how it works um
and then we have some just some other
stuff in here so I already went it over
the at symbol and then there's this one
too so the the colon equals um I don't
think we use this in here but uh equals
is used for dividing variables or uh
it's called a recursive assignment so
both used for dividing variables both of
these are this one is a recursive
assignment so value of the variable is
reevaluated each time it's used um and
then this one is a simple assignment or
immediate one it's evaluated only once
at the point of definition so this is
like typically the safer option you want
to go down if you get really complicated
make files you might end up running into
weird things with these recursive
assignments so generally it's safe to
use these ones but it it looks it looks
a little funny so I didn't include it in
this example um we will we will use it
down the road though so last but not
least uh we have debers so debuggers are
awesome for just uh an alternative to
just adding print lines print just print
this print that did we make it here yay
we made it ah we failed whatever just
adding those just blows your code up so
having debuggers makes that a lot easier
on you uh you can actually go down to
literal assembly and see where the
electrons are in your code uh like in
your in your script like what is
happening on the hardware so uh
debuggers are super useful and in
particular we're going to be talking
about the GDB debugger for C and C++ so
you use them for both um I'm not going
to like explain these super intensely I
don't feel comfortable in my own
explanation for these because there's
just a lot happening um but there are
some commands that you generally want to
be familiar with it's mostly just
commands and knowing uh what to look for
in your script so I have these in the
readme file just just with some
explanation
um but a really good uh overview is here
so this is done from lowle learning has
an advertisement here but uh essentially
it's just it's just a really good
overview on uh GDB uh just going into
assembly and doing a bunch of cool
tricks and and debuging C code that way
so I do recommend you watch that
video okay we can finally take a
breather now that was a lot
uh but I really hope that this is going
to sort of just ease that uh this is
designed to be a more passive part where
you can kind of just sit around and
listen and watch and just kind of enjoy
it uh there's no coding involved here at
all um so I thought I'd provide some
context on different types of Hardware
what the whole purpose of gpus are I
mean you probably already know what they
are but I just want to provide that
background just so that we're on the
same page entirely um and just to
provide some kind of internal I guess
preparation uh for for the next part
it's good to have these braks just to
you know slow your mind a little bit and
uh give yourself some time
but first off we have these CPUs okay
you already know what a CPU is it's
general purpose High clock speed per
core very few number of cores the on
chip memory is very large so maybe you
didn't know that the the caches on the
chip are actually quite large compared
to the GPU um this is because you know
the memory band with from uh the CPU to
the the ram slots on your computer those
are going to be uh like that transfer
speed is going to be very slow you have
to move the electrons all the way from
this part of the motherboard to this one
and that takes time right you're you're
just constantly waiting for data to
arrive and that's like what takes up
most of your time right so you have
these big caches for just purposely like
load pre-loading things on so that
they're ready to use um you have lower
latency so the whole idea of a CPU is to
just just complete this task as quickly
as possible and just return the value
just complete it complete it fast um and
then they have low throughput as well so
low throughput means um it can't do as
much comparatively it can't do as uh as
much operations per second as a GPU can
if you're talking about simple
instructions if they're more complex
ones like managing and loading data and
doing like file reads and wres like
that'll be faster but if you're talking
like math and matrix multiplication
uh it is going to be significantly
slower throughput is more talked about
as like operations per second so if I
have a bunch of cores running at say uh
2 billion clocks per second and I have
6,000 of them versus six cores that are
running at 5 billion clocks per second
do the math right how many operations
are you going to do on this one versus
that one that's the whole point of a GPU
way more cores a little bit lower clock
speed um but way more cores it's is
completely outnumbered CPU and that's
why it's faster um and then on
gpus we have the 90 hasn't been released
yet but I thought it was funny to put
there um gpus are very specialized so
they can accomplish simpler instructions
easier to handle ones hence why they
have smaller controllers on them which
you'll see in a second um they have a
lower clock speed like I said way more
cores and a lower cache so because you
have that on chip memory because you
actually have this vram that you can
access that is on on the GPU and that
this all of the Nvidia Hardware
Engineers has essentially optimized for
accessing that um you're able to get a
lot higher memory bandwidth that way up
in the like a high 100 gigabyte per
second range um so it's like it's it's
in the hundreds for sure um you have
higher latency on this remember it's not
for you know minimize the amount of time
it takes to complete this task and then
just done right it's it's more optimized
for throughput so we already talked
about this but um then you have these
tpus which came across recently and
these are for modern deep learning
applications so tpus are for literally
just processing tensors like you do fast
matrix multiplication fast linear
algebra that's that's what it is tensor
is linear tensor operations is linear
algebra um and it's just specialized for
doing that so tpus are faster but way
more expensive and specialized in
typically not consumer grade Hardware so
that's why we learn how to you know
build on top of infrastructure with gpus
cuz it's you know you can actually
afford it you can have one at your house
and for fairly low cost um and then you
have these fbt which I don't expect you
know what these are but these field
programmable gate arrays are very
specialized pieces of Hardware that
essentially say uh instead of having to
write like a or build a custom Hardware
configuration uh like for a certain task
for making something that you need to
run really really fast
um you can just program these you can
just program the actual chips to do uh
something more more fine grain on what
you want so there's more control over it
very expensive very low latency very
high throughput uh high power all this
right they're these are these are more
expensive but uh they allow for
modularity if you
will um and then just for some
background on GPU history so you know
back in 1993 when Jensen started Nvidia
they had the uh you know they the
GeForce cards all of these I wasn't
alive during this time um but you have
uh then you start getting into you know
after after the g47 you start getting
into uh these these better ones so like
the Tesla cards the fery uh the Kepler
Maxwell Pascal and then volto is when
things really started taking off the
Pascal and the Volta cards then you have
taring and then a which is what my card
is based on and then you have Hopper
which uh in case you didn't know Hopper
cards are really really fast like the
h100s and the h20s and even the recently
released Nvidia Blackwell chips yeah
those are ridiculous um this is this is
a little bit outdated of course so there
are actually uh like chips on here uh I
just got like a an outdated screenshot
but you get the idea this is how it
progressed uh and then you have like the
relative clock speed per core on here so
you know some of these were like really
really high but didn't have very many
cores um and then Nvidia kind of figured
out like okay we should just put more
and more cores on these things right um
and then you get the the overall uh I
think floating Point performance is what
this is so
uh yeah you once you get to Volta it's
it's starting to get uh it's starting to
get really high so I think this is uh
double Precision Giga
flops so
uh you know six essentially six Tera
flops of compute on the FTA architecture
which is pretty good um and then it gets
better and better from there on mine I
think I have right now it runs at a high
of around
23 uh 23 Tera flops on kuas so kuas is
the fast linear algebra library that
multiplies matrices really quickly and
I'm on there I'm about to get pretty
much like 20 uh 20 gig flops of single
Precision compute um so that's that's
that's that's quite
good
um what makes these things so fast for
deep learning I didn't actually cover
this um on the CPU you have very little
cores you have these big control units
that are taking up a ton of space you
have all these caches everywhere that
are flooding the thing um
and like there you you're you're not
giving that much uh leverage to the
course right like the course can do
Advanced complex instructions but there
aren't that many of them so you can only
do so much whereas if you have this
other architecture where you have
simpler instructions simpler controllers
simpler uh registers smaller ones uh but
a ton of cores like see how most of this
is taken up by cores and then just
caches and RAM um that's that's ideal
for gpus so on here you're too
essentially the the IDE the idea here is
you're trying to put together a puzzle
you're trying to put together a jigsaw
puzzle and the point is is it doesn't
matter which order you do it in so you
you don't have to do like this row and
then or you this column this column this
like it doesn't matter you do this piece
here this piece there do like a block
like a chunk there it doesn't matter as
long as it's all assembled together
properly in the end that's what you care
about and that's what the GPU is really
good at so typically you'll do things as
like uh you know one like multiple
puzzle pieces at a time or multiple
blocks of puzzle pieces at a time so
you'll have like a 2 by two or like a
4x4 thing of Jigsaw pieces that you'll
maybe do at a time that that's like the
that's the intuition behind uh Cuda and
how how you program gpus to run fast and
solve these problems quickly um on the
CPU you might be able to only do like
see there's only four cores here so you
might be able to only do uh four given
pieces of that puzzle at the same at
once uh whereas GPU you you know let's
say you have like 6,000 cores right uh
if this if this puzzle has like I don't
know say like
12,000 um if it has if it has 12,000
pieces well you can effectively do that
in two operations because you're able to
do the first 6,000 in one and then the
other 6,000 in the second so it's
effectively two operations that you do
it in but if you divide 12,000 by 4 four
meaning number of CPU cores um you
actually get 3,000 operations see you
can see how that can be drastically sped
up um that's that's why gpus are so fast
because you can because you can do that
um now there there are some there are
some common terms that we refer to these
things through so CPU is the host you're
going to see this in Cuda once we start
writing kernels uh the CPU is called the
host which is pretty obvious and then it
just kind of just kind of makes sense
for that to be named that way and then
the GPU is the device so you have the
host CPU and then GPU which is the
device um the CPU is going to uh mainly
the performance there is going to be
latency in seconds so you're looking at
latency how quick can I do a given task
and the GPU is throughput in tasks per
second so for example if you're doing a
rendering task it's like how many pixels
can I render per second um or how many
uh I don't know how many pixels can I
can I yeah sure render per second that's
fine um in a typical Cuda program you're
going to allocate at uh some memory on
CPU memory so it's going to be a
classical like C Malik that's what
you're going to do and then once it's
allocated on CPU or host you're going to
copy from host to device or or CPU to
GPU um and then once it's on the GPU you
can actually launch a kernel which is
what these parallel functions are
essentially so on a CPU you have a a
function then GPU you have a a kernel
which is a GPU function that can be
parallelized
um and that's that's the main intuition
there is you you start off with CPU move
everything do everything really fast on
GPU and then once you're done with the
results you move them back and then do
whatever you want with them from there
you might even continue to just feed it
more into into more and more kernels
until the whole thing is done right uh
but that's like that's the that's the
ideal workflow is you have CPU and then
this GPU thing is like an intermediary
which you have to convert back to CPU to
do something useful with um
the kernel looks like a Serial program
so if you we're going to look at these
in a second here when we jump into
actually writing these but uh it's it's
going to be a very simple
function and it's going to it's going to
have a very few lines uh it's going to
it's going to look like this basic
serial script except it's going to have
some key terms in it um these are mainly
threads blocks and grids don't even
worry about those terms right now we're
going to get into those I'm going to
explain the philosophy behind them uh
I'm going to explain uh pretty much the
whole Cuda architecture for you and just
help you understand what the heck these
things are for now some common terms to
remember before we actually start
jumping into this stuff are uh well
first of all kernels so kernels is like
a weird term um you might have thought
like popcorn kernels like like this is
what I thought I was like what popcorn
Kels why are we using those on on
computers that doesn't make sense um and
then I jumped over to convolution
kernels which is like uh when you do
like a convolution operation you might
have seen this in like cnns if you've
done a lot of stuff in like maybe
pytorch and you've like look through the
intuition on that it's like a a sliding
kernel that does a that does like an
image processing thing on on yeah just
images um that that the filter that
slides and does calculations that's
called a kernel so I was like uh is it
that no no it's not it's not a
convolution kernel uh it's also not a
Linux kernel either but enough so
there's lots of different kernels we
have there's actually four kernels
popcorn kernels convolution kernels
Linux kernels uh but the best one is GPU
kernels so that's the ones we're going
to be working with um there's actually a
little keyword that you highlight you
goore Global uncore uncore and that
defines a a kernel on the GPU so there's
actually a way we can explicitly say
that and uh yeah not not an external
story I thought the same thing too it's
like which one is it um but yeah so
we're going to go into two threads
blocks and grids that's going to be one
of the main things in the next chapter
um and then two more like sort of just
lingo terms are gem so G mm uh this
stands for General matrix multiplication
so what this generally means is uh you
have it's not just multiplying like a
and a * bals C it's not it's not a mapal
um entirely you actually do a ml um and
then you have this Alpha you have this
Alpha parameter which you scale the
result of that by uh and then you add it
to uh this beta scaler times this times
The Matrix C which is the shape of the
output Matrix so that's that's like a
lot of linear algebra which I'm not
going to cover right now but in case
that's like in case that makes sense to
you it's essentially this Alpha time uh
time mL of A and B and then you add that
to a scalar B * C which is the shape of
that Matrix um that that's what a gem is
so it's it's a mmal but with more uh and
then you have S gem so that's just
general MMO but with but with uh single
Precision so it's explicitly single
Precision um you can do a a half M Mo so
like an
fp6 uh you can do double mol you
typically don't though it's like FP
fp64
um but yeah so generally speaking um gem
s gem those are important then you have
the CPU which is also called The Host
which runs functions versus the GPU
which is called the device and it runs
kernels
um and that that's pretty much it I hope
I hope that wasn't too hard uh we're
going to dig into some kernels now this
this part's going to be uh a little bit
it's going to be a little bit intensive
you'll need to pay attention a little
bit but uh it's going to be fun and I
promised by the end uh you're going to
be really enlightened you're going to
like the first part of Cuda isn't
actually that hard we're just going to
cover very very basic kernels like
vector addition it's not going to be
that bad at all um but just to introduce
you to the philosophy and the whole
design principles of like basic uh Cuda
seat
programming okay so now things are going
to get a little bit more technical but I
figured we would kind of enter smoothly
by just doing a fun and useful activity
so I pulled up a bunch of Wikipedia
articles on various GPU architectures
then we're going to dive into what does
your GPU actually look like like what
what are the stats of that um so just
like looking at these in general let's
you know we're just looking for things
that are like useful to know some maybe
some little history kind of like the uh
intro to GPU section that we previously
did
um so like Pascal was an older one that
we used to have um there's a bunch of
cool stuff about this so like the 1080
and the and the and the 10 and the 10 70
uh we both based off Pascal um you know
you have a bunch of information about
you know where it's from all of this um
but what's really cool is um if we
scroll down you have all the technical
details on these things it's crazy how
much Wikipedia has um but yeah like you
we have these
tables that
will that will essentially tell us like
which which generation which Generations
had what so like you know texture cast
per SM which we'll go into later
um dedicated shared memory per uh SM or
streaming multiprocessor L2 cach per
chip right so you have all these
statistics and you can sort of compare
these over time so if we jump up to
emper which is actually what my GPU my
RTX 3070 is based off of
um you scroll down and uh you get the
same thing right so like L2 cache um and
then L2 cach so like 512 kilobytes and
then this one is um 40 megabytes right
so you get some interesting comparisons
here but
um yeah these this is just kind of the
stuff you want to be looking at uh when
it comes to like GPU specs especially if
you don't have one right you're going to
find a lot of useful information here um
you know going to Ampere like you have
these a100 s that have been used to
train very big models uh and that's it's
Amper 100 right that's that's what it's
called um
so bunch of cool statistics um which
different precisions and data types do
they support so
like the uh like for example
Volta um Volta
supports Volta doesn't support brain
float 16 but a100 does support brain
flat 16 so interesting stuff like that
which you can sort of just do a side
comparison of AD love lace this micro
architecture is what is used in the 40
series cards so ere is like the 30
series um I believe if we actually go to
Volta
architecture uh Volta
microarchitecture um I believe this is
used in the the 20 series
cards the 20
it's going to be
somewhere okay maybe
not
anyways you can find a bunch of cool
statistics on these a love La is the 40
series cards you get a bunch of info on
that like the the L2 cache it's again
bigger instead of 40 megabytes around
here it's 96 which is great um L1 cache
is actually what matters more so you
know like 18 megabytes and and and so
forth um then Hopper which is actually
what the state-of-the-art gpus right now
or close to state-ofthe-art is well the
state-ofthe-art is actually the
Blackwell uh micro architecture but the
hopper is like also very like second
most recent one and these are what the
h100s are based on these are used to
train models like gbt 4 Etc uh so you
can you find a bunch of statistics on
those without actually going and using
one um but if we actually want to uh
print some stuff about our GPU I'm just
going to open a new terminal tab here um
I'm going to drag this to the side if we
pop over to um Cuda samples
GitHub this is going to print some stuff
about your
GPU
so if we uh take this and we just just
get clone
it it's going to take a second to do
that but we can scroll down in the
meantime and we can see uh if you're on
Linux you would you would say CD into
your whatever directory you desire and
then and then make uh to actually make
the binaries for running stuff with it
so if we print this out here let me
actually make
this bit
bigger
um we can CD into Cuda samples and then
inside of here we have uh samples so we
go into our sample directory as seen
there so CD into samples
and then we have
um we have a bunch of different ones so
there's things you can experiment with
here I don't know how how easy these are
to use I haven't played with them yet
but we're going to CD into utilities and
notice how we have this device query
thing here so this is actually going to
turn into a
um we can't execute that yet but if we
make then we actually can and we can see
a bunch of details about our GPU so I
recommend you to do this on your own
system but uh one cuicable device so
there's one GPU plugged into my
motherboard that GPU is the GeForce RTX
370 the Cuda driver version is 12.5 as
well as the runtime version uh Cuda
capability so this is actually very
important this 8.6 here yours is it
might be different um you might have the
same GPU you might not but this 8.6 is
actually very critical in how we uh we
know like what is supported on our GPU
so there might be some operations that
work and there might be some that aren't
so if I just drag this um over to the
side here we we don't need to worry
about the rest of this as of right now
maybe some of maybe some of this later
but uh I'll just I'll just give you that
information
so if we go to the uh
Cuda uh
capability compute capability
[Music]
um what's it
called sure GeForce products um see 8.6
just like
that uh I have to go back to the Cuda
docs to actually get useful stuff about
this uh
Cuda Cuda
docs so if we go to the
uh Cuda C we'll just sure we'll do Cuda
C++ um no we're not going to do Cuda
C++ we're going to go down to uh Cuda C
Cuda search Cuda C programming guide and
inside of the cudas C programming guide
yes
um capability
so like this for example this is what
I'm looking for so thread block clusters
in in uh two and then you go to
2.2.1 it's thread block clusters
um you only get these if you have a
compute capability 9.0 or higher um so
the higher the compute capability the
better uh
so I cannot actually use thread block
clusters on mine because the
architecture doesn't support it these
are critical things you're going to
watch out for and you know as you you
might actually be able to take advantage
of some features that someone else can't
like if you have an a100 and someone
else has a v00 you can actually do
things that they can't and you can do
things faster and more efficiently
because of things that the architecture
actually supports so these are these are
things you're going to watch out for um
but anyways uh with that being said we
can actually jump into uh some stuff
about the just essentially how does the
Cuda architecture work how does how how
do we write code and and how do how does
that whole thing fit
together so now we can actually get
really into what Cuda is doing and the
whole hierarchy of that so inside of
here I've pulled up chapter 5 writing
your own kernels um and then Cuda Basics
and then just the readme and the ID
exing or indexing file so if you do I
believe control shift V on this
or control I don't know what keybind it
is contrl alt V contrl shift V there we
go okay um and then we pull up this one
on the side here just uh just for
reference let's go through this sort of
hand in hand
so I'm going to zoom
in we just printed this out we just
printed out device query so we don't
need to really cover that um but when it
comes to sort of the more easy stuff to
get a grasp on I mean we already went
over this so you have the host which is
the CPU and uses those RAM sticks on
your motherboard and then the device or
the GPU uses the onchip vram or video
memory um for desktop
PCS the the surface level run time
typically goes um you C you you define
some input on the host or the CPU uh
which you then later want to run on the
GPU but in first you have to actually
Define it on the whole system memory
and then you would copy that over to GPU
memory um and then you would uh and then
you would execute using that on GPU
memory you would execute you you would
launch a Cuda kernel and that Cuda
kernel would use that uh GPU memory and
do stuff with it and maybe do do some
useful computation and then once that's
done uh you would ensure everything is
all synchronized up like nothing is
nothing is still waiting you would you
would synchronize everything and then
you would transfer it back to CPU so
that or or the host so that you can you
know print it out or do something useful
with it this is typically how the the
runtime goes um and you'll see this in
our later chapters um the naming scheme
like how we actually um what what we
actually name our pieces of data is
quite critical so typically what you'll
do is you go host or H and then
underscore whatever the variable name is
so if it's like Matrix a you do hore
Matrix a that means it's defined on the
host so you're going to do your your
Malik your your your C Malik um with
this and then you're going to do a Cuda
mem copy which we will see later in a
second um and that that's where you take
this host and you you essentially
transfer it over to this other to this
other variable uh device so device a
that's the GPU uh version of of that so
it just exists on two different pieces
of memory um and this is just for the
set variable name a now we have this
Global which you might have seen already
um this is visible globally and this is
very broad this is this is typically
what a kernel is going to look like uh
unless you are calling uh say a separate
uh calling a separate kernel inside of
another one you would use say device um
but in this example we'll just stick
with global um you know you can read a
littleit little bit more into this if
you want
but we're going to use Global for the
most part device we might see that later
in the
course and then host uh is only going to
run on CPU so uh don't don't really
worry about that um it's it's kind of
just telling Cuda that you're going to
run on on the on the CPU but you you may
not actually need to because you're just
going to use you know like the void
instead of instead of global void right
um now this this Cuda malic
term memory allocation on the GP vram so
that's the global memory on the GPU
itself so in this example you do you
know Define a bunch of uh a bunch of uh
essenti essentially arrays so a pointer
to a device uh a float array which is a
pointer on the
device uh and it's for a and then the
same thing for B and C now you do kudam
Malik meaning you allocate it on the GPU
so you do the memory address for that so
you put in the memory address for for
this thing
um and then you go essentially whatever
the you know let's just say you have a
size defined above right uh like it's
maybe it's like a matrix for example and
it's size it's like a you know Square
Matrix size n byn and all you're going
to do is say you know we want to
allocate this much memory uh this memory
address and that's just going to be a
square Matrix of let's say you know 128
* 128 time the size of whatever a float
is so in that case I think it'll be four
because a float is uh four bytes where
each B is eight bits you have a floating
Point 32 number do the math and then you
end up with the total amount of uh bytes
that you will need to allocate for uh
this device uh a matrix and so on
through b and c as well
um now Cuda M Copy can copy from both
device to host host to device or device
to device for edge cases so um you know
you would you would slide a little term
in here camem copy host to device or CM
copy device to host um and that's that's
how that would go um we're actually
going to see usage of this in a second
here but um understanding camm copy is
just going to just going to copy things
around and then Cuda free is obviously
just going to free memory up on the
device so when you you're done with
something or you don't need it anymore
just you know free that up if it's a big
if it's a big uh you know if it's just
like an integer or whatever like just a
float um like a float a equals 1 or
something it's like you don't need to
free that um but if it's a big array
like this you're going to need to free
that um
now the nvcc compiler is something we'll
dig into maybe a little more in the
future um but this is all you really
need to know so the host code is uh
essentially the these nvcc will compile
all of this down into uh something that
the GPU can actually execute but the CPU
is going to run it so uh CPU is going to
interpret what that is saying and it's
going to launch things and and tell the
GPU to do things it's not just going to
compile directly down to GPU right so uh
when it needs to run on GPU when when it
actually needs those instructions as to
what to do it's going to get compiled
down to PTX which is parallel thread
execution instructions so that's like
the GPU equivalent of x86 or assembly uh
you know as it is for um CPU or host um
and and then it's further going to
compile that down to Shader assembly
which we're not going to worry about um
and this is just and this is stable
across all of the different Nvidia gpus
so you don't need to worry about that um
and then just in time is just a type of
compil
so
um Cuda hierarchy yes this is this is
where things start to get a little bit
intuitive
so imagine you have like a imagine you
have this giant 3D like a cubic volume
uh and and this volume is called a grid
right inside of this grid you're going
to have a bunch of these smaller Cube
cubic volumes those are called blocks uh
and those those blocks are organized
uh you know you can make them whatever
size you want it's just like essentially
uh can think of it like a like a like a
prism or something uh and you have a
bunch of these organized in this giant
3D Volume which is the grid and those
individual blocks have things inside of
them called threads and those threads
are going to do your math operations for
you so there's there's a lot to unpack
here but the the individual threads um
can communicate inside of these blocks
and that's an important part to remember
for later when we're optimizing stuff
but essentially the reason why we have
all these different pieces inside of
this massive grid is so that we can get
the parallelism of gpus so when you have
this block doing this you know doing
this piece of the puzzle and then this
doing another piece of the puzzle and
they all kind of do their part and at
the end if they all do their part
successfully and they're all like
synchronized and you make sure that
everything works correctly um you know
it's it's better than having a single
CPU thread going through each individual
thing in that problem and doing it one
by one oras you have like a bunch of
these blocks or these threads inside of
blocks which are uh doing you know
little independent operations it's doing
a smaller number of operations and they
have a lower clock speed uh but they're
it's going to solve the problem much
quicker because it's in
parallel so that that's the whole idea
here is you have this this 3D Volume
called a grid inside of it you have
these other uh you have these other 3D
sort of Cubes or rectangles whatever um
and inside of those you have threads and
those threads are going to also do
things so I need to breathe but we'll go
into uh some more technical terms in a
second here so going to these technical
terms we can see this grid dim exists
here in our kernel in our Global uh
kernel we have a block idx which is you
know these these three um
and block dim exists uh here and here
and here and here and here right you
have all these uh and then thread idx so
this grid dim is the number of blocks in
the Grid at you know say like grid dim
dot X is going to be uh in this in this
volumetric uh grid what is the X
dimension of that so like what is the
length and then grid dim doy is going to
be like what is the height and then
maybe grid dim. Z is going to be the
depth of that right um and then the
block idx is going to it's not actually
uh about the block itself but like where
is it where is the block within the grid
so the the grid dim is like how long is
it how what is the what is like the size
of the grid itself that is run on the
GPU and then the block idx is where uh
each individual block is so a block will
have a block idx in both the uh maybe x
y and Zed dimension and that'll be
essentially its coordinates within that
grid uh and then the block dim is how
big that block is so grid fits a bunch
of blocks into it a block fits a bunch
of threads into it so the block dim is
like how how big is this like smaller
Cube or this or this rectangular prism
um and then the thread idx is like which
which thread is it within that block so
you can see how this like spatial
hierarchy goes down you have this 3D in
the grid and then this 3D in the block
so it's like kind of 6D if you think
about it that way um I don't want to I
don't want that to be intimidating
though like six dimensional I don't want
that to be intimidating it's just kind
of how the it's it's it's an efficient
way of of running things in parallel and
a way of visualizing it as like a
software abstraction right uh that's
that's the idea there
um and
then threads like I mean I I I assume
that this kind of this this spatial idea
sort of makes sense now so now we can go
into like why this works um and sort of
like the more nitty-gritty of that so
each thread um itself has local memory
on it so registers which are very fast
and is private to that individual thread
so for example if you wanted to add um A
and B where it's like 1 2 3 and then all
the way up to n which is like the length
and then 2 4 six so like counting by
ones and then count B is counting by
twos um each thread would do a single
add so like thread at index say zero
would be like a at the at the thread
Index right and so the thread index
itself tells you how to index into data
and then you can use that element that
it gets like from its own index from the
thread index in that whole space and you
can actually do operations with that so
it's like a little hack of uh
essentially both both getting the right
elements of data uh and adding and doing
math operations on them at the same time
so we end up doing you know uh 1 + 2
right with a single thread and it's in
and it's accessing this index uh that
the index the data based on its based on
the thread's index and it's adding them
together uh and then same thing for you
know maybe thread thread two right um so
that's just like kind of how the whole
that that's how the whole like uh
indexing thing pans out that's why it's
so cool um and then warps and it's kind
of interesting if you if you look at
this Wikipedia article it's
like warps warps and weft right so you
have um you have these warps that are
going through so like these these
uh these these warps that are going
through it like up and down and then the
weft is like uh what the the warps are
weaving through so they're like
interlocked like this and so uh you you
you could sort of think of of the uh
warps as the uh as like what is what is
going forward so you could say like a
warp is a group of threads
um warp and weft uh the vertical warp
Yarns uh plural are held in stationary
um and the horizontal we is drawn
through them so you essentially have all
these War like a bunch of threads
essentially it's a bunch of threads that
are that are going in and out and and
you can think of these threads as like
doing their own math operations and you
have a bunch of them grouped together in
a warp right that's that's the whole
idea there
um so you know like I said in
the in the in the Wikipedia article warp
is a set of
Yarns um set of Yarns or other things
stretch in place on a loom where the
weft is introduced during the weaving
process is regarded as the longitudinal
set in a in a finished fabric with two
or more sets of elements I I don't
expect you to understand that it's just
like the idea of threads are grouped
into warps um and then the the whift
kind of like it's that other uh
perpendicular
part um so warps are inside of blocks so
remember we have the like the the grids
and then blocks and then threads um
inside of blocks you have warps which
take care of threads so the blocks
themselves aren't entirely handling the
threads it's actually the warps that are
doing a lot of that work
so you typically organize a warp as like
a group of threads like uh I believe the
maximum is 32 threads so a warp will
handle 32 threads at once within a
block
um there is no way of getting around
using warps the warps scheduler makes
the warps run so uh you could think of
like maybe the warp scheduler as the as
like the weft
right so um it's it's sort of like going
through and making sure they don't get
like disentangled and all this and and
ensuring that everything like works out
properly you can use whatever analogy
Works um but the the warp scheduler
ensures that the warps which are group
of threads run um and then you would
have typically four warp schedulers per
SM and SM is like the smaller like the
the streaming multiprocessor on chip
that's what those are and you can have
four rep schedulers per SM so
um you know do the math that's 128
threads per SM
um then we have blocks so blocks are
interesting each block has shared memory
um visible to all threads within that
thread block so all of these like you
know thread one can see the same stuff
that thread 32 can uh they can or or
even thread like I don't know like 500
for that matter um
um they can all see the same data so
like within a warp they can they can
kind of see their they can communicate
faster but within a block they can still
communicate very fast uh through this
shared memory which we call the L1 cache
and I'll dig into that in a second here
when we go into the next section but the
L1 cache is very important for Speed and
optimizing uh kernels so uh
yeah essentially just the same thing
what I said uh shared memory shared
memory is is more efficient um it's
faster I think the maximum memory
bandwidth you get with shared memory is
like on the order of uh like 15
terabytes per second and then uh Global
vram so like when I do Nvidia SMI uh
like
this you can see that I get
um like this this this is my this this
is actually going at like maybe 6 or 700
gabes a second Shar shared memory is
like 15 terabytes so it's like really
fast um and and blocks use uh shared
memory which is you know uh on an
individual SM so the SM will handle that
um and then grids um during the chronal
execution the threads within the blocks
within the grid can access Global memory
um so that's just like universally
applied
um you can you can make things you know
more advanced if you want to use threads
but it's going to default using the GPU
V Ram that 8,192 megabytes that you just
saw um it's going to contain a bunch of
blocks um and the whole idea here is
that with with grids and blocks and
threads is that you you just have to
worry like conceptually what is it doing
you don't have to worry about how things
are handled on the hardware because this
whole Cuda this whole Cuda hierarchy is
a software abstraction right so the so
the hardware doesn't actually look like
grids and blocks and threads like it
doesn't objectively look like that it
looks different and is compiled down to
Shader assembly which doesn't actually
look close to
uh close to what this what this is right
now and that is actually run on the
hardware right so there's there's
various different levels here that it's
hard to sort of navigate through but
this is a lot of this is kind of why I'm
showing you this stuff if to give you a
better grasp on that
um so let's dig into what this uh ID
exing script is actually doing now going
into the actual Cuda indexing scheme
like we saw with threads uh except we're
going on the level of grids blocks uh
and threads so everything uh this this
script in particular is designed to
print things uh useful things out for us
so as we can see uh ID you know all
these different block idx um all of
these and uh oh I'm going to go into
these in a second here but essentially
like you you have the um if we go down
um we we have we have all these terms
that we Define right
so
uh block X block Y block Zed right so B
and then T is for Threads so what I
particularly mean here is uh this is the
this is the block dim so inside of the
grid you're going to have uh X like the
length of the X Dimension is going to be
two and then the height Dimension is
three and the depth Dimension Z is four
right so you're going to have this grid
uh volume and it's going to be of that
shape and then in in each individual
block inside of that inside of that grid
um you're going to have these thread
dims uh which this is essentially the
block Dimension this is the um this is
the grid Dimension and this is the block
Dimension um so the you're inside of
each block you're going to have
essentially four long four high and four
deep right so it's going to be this this
perfect Cube essentially um and
so we go down we calc we can calculate
the total number of blocks per grid so
just essentially base time width time
height your classical formula and same
for Threads per block and we can get the
total number
in each of these and then we can go ah
and print them out right so blocks per
grid threads per block um and then total
number of threads so we have a certain
number of threads per block and then if
we times that by the number of blocks we
get the total number of
threads now we have this other type down
here called dim 3 which is specific to
Cuda but this is essentially just the
same thing as we saw before so blocks
per grid so we have this these um these
these grid Dimensions X x y and Zed and
then same thing for uh threads within a
block so the block the block Dimensions
um meaning x y and Zed and so we plug
these into our kernel which is called
who am I we have this Global uh we have
this Global header
and we do these three um we do these
these three symbols I can't remember
what these are called it's like the less
than or greater than symbol uh and then
you put the uh total number of blocks
per grid um or the grid Dimensions as
the first parameter and then the threads
per block as the second and then there's
some other ones which you can do after
and you'll see those in a second but
these are all all you have to worry
about right now so the grid dimensions
and then the block
Dimensions uh and then we c a device
synchronized to ensure that everything
is caught up and we can continue with
whatever else we need to do um that this
that would be used like practically um
so now when we actually go up to here
this is where things get a little bit
spatially intuitive okay I'm not going
to lie this part might be like one of
the hardest to grasp but I'm going to
try my best to explain so this block ID
what is this well this is essentially
you you can think of uh a bunch of
apartments in an apartment
complex um a bunch of floors within each
apartment and then a number like a room
on that floor right and so we're trying
to find where we are within that apart
apartment complex right so you can think
of it as
um you know your apartment is like a
like a paint right it's like a singular
pain in this in this volume um and so
you in this one you uh in in the
apartment complex you essentially do
um grid dim dox so this this length part
and then the Y
component uh and then times whatever Z
is so the block idx doz is wherever the
block position is it's not any it's not
like how big how big something is it's
ual index or the position so you have
this pain which is x * Y and then a
depth which is z so it's like however
big the pain is and then go that deep so
it's like these panes that are like
layered on top going depthwise right
it's going deep and so you have these
panes that are like going that way um
and then you have
the uh block idx doy time grid dim dox
so you can think of this as uh like the
the grid di is is like this like a floor
right a floor within that apartment uh
building and the block ID x.y is like
which Which floor is it so you have to
go up that number of floors to get there
um so it's like you essentially start
from the bottom you go like this many
and then this many and then this many
it's like each of those is like a bunch
of rooms that you go through to get to
the next floor right you eventually wrap
up to this one and then you uh and then
once you get to the actual X position
which is like the x is the length you
actually stop there so it's it's like
you've went through like a number of
pains like paines deep um rows High
which is the number of floors um and
then you end up with like this this
final part which is like okay well what
is the offset at this floor which I
which my apartment is and it's like like
right here it's like depth and then goes
up depth goes up number of floors and
then like this is where I am and that's
how you uh that's how you find your
block ID um like which apartment complex
or which apartment building are you in
with that that entire city or the
empowerment complex right in a 3D
scenario this block offset is
essentially the number of you you take
the total threads per block so the block
Dimensions how many threads is in each
you know this this many threads in X
this many threads and Y and as many
threads Z you you you multiply all those
together you get the total threads per
block or say people per apartment um and
then times our apartment number so it's
like uh the total number of threads up
to your like essentially which which
thread index um does your like how many
threads are before your UH apartment how
many people uh are before your apartment
uh your apartment number that that's
what we're saying here so we calculated
this block ID from before and then we we
just find like that but on the level of
threads instead and that's the block
offset for um calculating you know which
thread we're at and then we can continue
that and use the same analogy that we
used in block ID except for thread
offset so you know it's like thread ID
x.x block ID x.x it's like these are
just like mapped essentially except it's
like a lower level in the hierarchy it's
down to threads instead of
um instead of uh blocks right and so you
can you can calculate which person you
are within that individual apartment
like if it's like a if it's like a big
apartment with like multiple floors and
there's like multiple layers in it you
could use that but you you get the point
it's a it's a 3D anal ology um and we
can find which person we are within that
or which which thread essentially in
that block it is and so when you add the
block offset so the total number of
threads leading up to your apartment
plus which one you are within that uh
within that apartment number then you
can actually find which thread you are
in the entire grid and then you can do
stuff with that right and that's what we
say sign the global ID to so Global
person ID in the entire apartment
complex um
and that's that so there's a lot to
unpack there feel free to rewatch some
of this or even try to visualize some of
this on your own maybe write it out um
but when we actually go
into when we go into our terminal here
and go into five um then cud to
Basics if we go um nvcc d o we go Zer we
go 01 and then 01 like this
um it'll compile this binary which we
see here and we can just go ahead and
execute that and it'll show us uh
precisely all of this that we just that
we just unpacked so I mean I can't I
cannot put all of this on the screen but
uh like for example if we look
at like how it counts upward right
so um you have you have all of your
different Dimensions here and you can uh
at the very end I believe it outputs the
uh the particular thread offset so we
notice that it's like 63 and then it
jumps to 32 right so it's like 32 and
then it goes for
um it goes
for uh
32 numbers so if we go 30 I mean it's
it's technically like minus one uh but
the the best analogy you can use here is
this is 32 threads right um that is a
warp so when we talked about 32 threads
in a warp this is exactly what it looks
like so go back to here as well you'll
see it stops at exactly 32 and you'll go
up from there so it'll be like 0 to 31
so it's like 0 1 2 3 4 so it's like 1 to
31 it's 31 elements and then you'll have
the additional zero which makes it 32
that's just the indexing scheme right
and then when you go from 32 to 63 it's
it's the same idea um because you go
from 0 to 63 instead of 1 to 64 so you
do actually have 32 elements uh 32
threads per warp in there um and then
you can just see the global thread ID in
the entire grid so when we when we
actually multiply these up we have you
know in the in the grid we have 2 * 3
which is 6 and then that * 4 is
um 24 * 4 * 4 so that that is 16 and 16
* 4 is is
64 so you can see 1536 in this entire
thing right and so um if we scroll like
backwards we can see uh
1535 it ends right there and that is the
final one so um like for example block
um it's this has two elements so it's
going to be zero and one and then this
is going to have three elements so it's
going to be um 0 1 2 and then this is
four elements so it's going to be 0 1 2
3 is four right uh and then the threads
because those each go up to four it's
going to be 0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 um
and then you end up with um essentially
whatever that number is in the end so
you can see how this kind of all adds up
and how this indexing scheme works and
how we can use these to index pieces of
data um using like the actual thread and
block indexes and then and then do
really fast parallel math with that um
that's the whole idea here let's go
ahead and jump into kernels
now okay so now we're going to do a
little bit of our math and we're
actually going to you know see what
these kernels are actually doing and
seeing how they work under the hood so
it's actually very simple this is the
most simple it gets um but essentially
we're just going to do some vector
addition as a practice so adding these
two together element wise 1 + 6 2 + 7 3
+ 8 Etc and we get all this um very very
simple and easy to understand we can we
have a CPU example here which is obvious
and easy to look at
um we have a GPU example which is
actually a little weird it's a it's
different than this because here we have
a for Loop and here we have this this it
term which is ID block idx time Block in
plus thread IX and I'm going to explain
this in a second here but this doesn't
have a for Loop and essentially what
this is doing like I talked about before
is it's just unrolling this Loop so you
know CPU is going to like do this
iteration and this one and then this one
and then this one the GPU is going to
take all these individual iterations and
distribute it across a bunch of blocks
or or caor you could say uh and it's
going to parallelize that operation and
make it really really fast so instead of
doing uh separately like 10 million
different operations like in order order
it's going to take roughly 10,000 time
units um say you had you know 10,000
cicor to split this across it's like
well that's that that's actually a lot
less now that's only about a thousand
times depths you have to do so that it's
it's sped up uh an insane amount just by
Distributing it across and that's
theoretical of course but um you know we
initialize vectors this should be this
should be very intuitive if you've
written like any random stuff in random
gens in C before it's going to
essentially take
uh a random integer between zero and
Rand Max so Rand Max is this um very
easy to understand it's going to be a
floating Point number um and then a
timing function just to measure
execution time again in this script we
are benchmarking so perform War warm-up
runs get things you know fired up and
then Benchmark CPU to GPU and see how
well it does um but this isn't really
the important part here what I wanted to
mostly expand on is what's what's what
things specifically here apply to Cuda
and what do you really need to
understand so we have this Cuda Malik
which is the same as Malik except it's
on GPU so it's going to do that it's
going to allocate memory on on the
global Dam or the vram on the GPU and uh
all this really has is a device pointer
and a size so we have this we have this
device a this device a vector or array
is uh declared here which is a pointer
um and then we set the size for that
right and this is just the memory
address of that so uh we we allocate
device memory with Cuda Malik um and
then when we actually want to move the
stuff that we've created on the host
because remember we initialize these
vectors on a global or or just a just a
regular void CPU function so we actually
have to copy these over now and how we
do that is we just literally look at
this destination source how big it is
and what what kind of copy do we want to
do so destination is device hence the d
The Source is
host it's size big um like we declared
here and then CM copy host to device so
CPU it's going to move to GPU and that's
it very simple
um we Define uh this numb blocks which
is a little bit different than what we
did in this indexing thing uh because
it's not actually this dim 3 type as we
saw before um it's it still works though
the whole idea with this is that uh if
instead of say uh if instead of having
like 2 three 4 if we just wanted it to
be like a length of uh what is this this
is 24 2 * 3 * 4 is 24 so you would you
could essentially set this to 24 and
then set these to one and just having uh
numb blocks and then putting this in in
that uh in the kernel launch actually
just converts the integer to like dim
three and then it's like it's like numb
blocks and then one and one so it's just
like a it's just length only and it it's
still like it still looks like
volumetric but it's just laid out
linearly so it ends up looking like a
line and could interprets it as a line
in Hardware
um then you might ask okay well how
exactly do we calculate num blocks well
this is very interesting
so we have a bunch of things going on
here and this seems a little funny so we
have n plus block size minus one and I'm
going to illustrate this out here now
just to clear up what the heck is this
numb blocks things means I actually laid
out some calculations for this so block
size is the number of threads inside of
a block it's the size of the block
itself which threads are going to fit
into right so so if we have let's just
say instead of 10 million elements like
we have up here let's say we have 1,24
elements right uh if we're trying to fit
1,24 elements across uh 256 threads per
block that means we're probably going to
want four blocks right it'll split it
evenly because 256 * 4 is 1024 um and so
we have to actually calculate this
manually but we have to keep in mind
that we are doing uh like we there are
more things things we have to keep track
of in case say this number ends up being
like 1025 right so I actually wrote out
a script that does that does this math
uh perfectly for us um so let's first
look at this so you have this uh 1024
plus 256 that's that's the length of the
array plus the block size right number
of threads per block then you're going
to do minus one and whatever that is
divide that by the block size uh and
then
uh the the compiler is automatically
going to floor this answer it's going to
truncate those those decimal places off
so if you get like 4.99 or whatever it's
going to take that 0.99 and just
truncate it off so you're going to end
up with four so if we were to do for
example like 1,00
um 1024 plus 256 well what's that 1 1,00
+ 200 is 1200 and then 56 + 24 is 80 so
we get
1,280 um and if we divide this by
256 we end up getting around what's the
answer divided 256 we get
um we get this number but remember we
have the one here which I actually
forgot for a second there we have have
the one so it technically is uh 79 so
you end up with this N9 part and it ends
up just being four because you truncate
that off however if you end up having
this as like
1,25 then this number is actually going
to end up as 1,280 because you're just
adding one back to you know 1279 and you
end up with five so in case you end up
adding an extra element you want to
allocate space and resources for that or
else you will not get the answer that
you want so that's all this is doing up
here and we make sure and this is just
like a careful calculation to make sure
that everything goes as as we want um
and so this is just a a little script
that I wrote up to test this but I don't
need that
anymore
um
so going further um
we essentially in this kernel here let
me slide up so in this kernel we have
just this this x Dimension laid out
right so what you're doing is you have
this blocks block idx which is which
block it is in that in that line of a
grid and then you're multiplying that by
the size of the block so how how many
threads are there per block times the
number of blocks uh and then plus
whichever whatever
thread we're at right so this gives us
the thread um in that in that like line
of a grid right and so we end up with
whatever place we're at and we use that
thread index to then access elements in
A and B and C uh and then we just do an
an add operation so whichever you know
it might be in some cases this might be
like you know 2.5 million and in some
cases it might be like three uh in which
case they're going to be the same number
uh and then they're going to add and
we're going to get the answer that we
expect it just might not happen in the
order that like a a loop might right so
instead of doing like uh the first the
uh the first index and the second index
and the third it's going to like scatter
and distribute these and it's just going
to be fast right so that's what the
whole idea is there
um and if we go ahead and actually run
this script
um go 0 0 and then we could just so 0
Vector ad and then enter we'll just run
this file performing oneup runs uh C
Benchmark and CPU Benchmark and GPU so
the CPU average time is uh about .14
milliseconds which is really fast
however the GPU average time is
significantly less than that about 143x
speed up almost 144 uh and the results
match up when we compare them uh index
index wise or element wise so so we just
verify the results here um we ensure
that the the absolute value of the
difference between those two is greater
than uh 1 * 105 which is just a common
verification thing so you'll see that
when we're comparing things uh you know
more like as we go more into Cuda it's
going to be this idea of you Benchmark
uh you get like an average time across
all the runs and then you make sure that
you're getting the correct results by
having this tolerance Factor so
sometimes this might be like super low
or it might be like super high um but
that's that's typically how we'll do
it then we have the second example of
vector addition which is uh very much
the same however instead of just having
this uh one dimensional like x axis
thing where we have one two three four
lines um we have a lot more so going
back to that example from indexing where
we had you know three dimensions um if
we actually apply this to Vector Edition
we get a noticeable slow down so the
first thing you'll notice is that this
has way more lines but you're like
Elliot certainly this is going to be
faster right it uses up the whole Space
instead of just uh instead of just a
little bit right um well the issue with
this is that it Cuda is not really going
to struggle with uh scheduling things
and making them run fast and and
compiling down to something that's going
to like really work at speed um it's
more so like what are the calculations
that you're actually doing in a single
uh thread right so this is a this is
what's going to happen in a thread
notice how we do 1 2 3 4 5 six
operations so um three adds three
multiplies and three stores so equal
sign as well and then this one it's like
you have a bunch of these comparisons
and and it's just like a bunch of math
you it's it's like hard to read right
and the point is this does
one one multiply one store or one
multiply two stores and two ads
significantly less than this one so the
point is um only use the 3D aspect when
you absolutely need to when it is like
dependent on your algorithm and you
don't need to uh when you when you
actually have something that that's like
uh spatially 3D then you can use
something like this because it might
actually work a bit easier and you w't
have to do all these calculations to end
up laying out this 3D space into like
this onedimensional thing um and you
have to worry about like things wrapping
around and and strides and all this um
so that's like that's mainly the
bottleneck there and I just really did a
comparison between the 3D and the 1D
Vector Edition kernel so we can go ahead
and actually compile this
here
um so we notice that they're both a lot
faster however um the speed up CPU
versus GPU 1D like the GPU 1D is 106
times faster but the 3D is only 102
times faster so this is actually faster
than the um than the GPU 3D um not by a
crazy amount but you know by by like 3
4% maybe and if you scale up your
numbers it might grow but you get the
point um there's a lot of unnecessary
calculations there um and it's just kind
of simpler to go down this route with
the 1D
kernel now we dive into something a
little bit more intuitive
algorithmically called matrix
multiplication you might have already
done this in which case you know this
might just be some simple review you
might want to skip ahead it's it's up to
you really but I'm going to go over this
be no matter what because some people
may not know and sometimes it's good to
get a little refresher on that so we're
essentially going to write the naive
version the naive version of the matrix
multiplication Cuda kernel which is the
slowest one but it's the most basic and
intuitive to understand um
so a matrix looks like this you have
rows and you have columns right um let
me actually zoom in a little more here
so rows and columns um for example a is
a 3 by two because it has three rows and
two columns right so it's like three
high and two long it's like width by
height you could say or height by width
and then we have B which is a 2x4 so
it's two row rows and four uh four
columns right uh and the idea is is that
as long as these two inner numbers are
the same then uh then we then it
actually works we're allowed to do that
matrix multiplication um and you'll see
why in a second here and then these
outer Dimensions these three and four
would end up being the new size of the
new output Matrix C uh so we have you
know 1 2 3 4 5 6 and 7 8 9 10 11 12 13
14 and what we do here is is it's very
is it's very simple you essentially go 7
and 11 you you take this you have this
uh this B it's like this and then a is
like this and so you take the seven and
11 in in B and you rotate it and you do
a DOT product with uh one and two so you
take the seven and and the 11 you flip
it over and so the seven is going to
multiply with the one and then the 11 is
going to multiply with the two right so
you're just like it's like sideways uh
and then when you multiply one with one
with the seven you get seven and two
with uh 11 gets 22 and then you would
add those together to get
29 um and we can see that right here as
the first
element so notice how it's like the
First Column and the first row aligned
together and so it's like they're
they're like pointing at one spot it's
like the first it's like the first row
up here instead of down here first row
and then the first column column and
they meet together and you get this top
left corner thing um and that's and
that's where we end up with this 29
value and then you essentially just do
this for the rest of them so you go uh 8
and and 12 and then you you flip that
flip that sideways and it'll multiply
with the one and the two
um and then you put that
here you have the the second column and
the first row so it's going to it's
going to meet in the second column and
the first row right um and then you just
continue doing this for the rest of them
until you end up with your final answer
so you're essentially just like flipping
the column of B onto a row of a and
you're doing a do product operation
where each uh each of like the like
element wise you're going to multiply
and then you add all you reduce and you
add all of them together and you squash
it and then you end up with this final
Matrix uh which is of shape uh 3x4 so
three uh rows three three rows High by
four columns wide and then and then
that's how you do a mat mole um so when
we go into the I mean typically when
you're writing out you know hard to
understand algorithms like this when
you're trying to fit this all in your
head ideally you want to write it on the
CPU first if you just jump straight into
GPU and try to optimize you're probably
going to mess up you're probably not
going to get the answers you're looking
for and things are going to be weird so
you write out the maybe even go back to
Python and write this out in Python
first so you can visualize it um and
make sure that yours matches like P
towards or nump or something and then
and then you write this out in C and you
say okay well how do we do a a m Mo on
the CPU here so you have your a and your
B and your C Matrix um and then your
shapes m k n so m is uh this this how
high a is so m in this case was would be
three k would be two so two and two and
then n would be four right so you end up
doing this like
um M yeah just just like this
autocomplete M * K and then you multiply
that with a K byn Matrix and you get an
M byn Matrix just space this out so it's
easier to look
at uh and and that's that so when we
look at our our nested for Loops here we
can see that we iterate over M so that's
the
uh that is the height of a right that's
the number of rows we have and then
we're going to I plus plus that each
time and keep in mind when this is laid
out in memory it's not actually going to
be a matrix it's going to be an array so
you're going to have like one 2 3 4 5 6
instead of 1 two like as an array and
then another array below it and then
another it's it's not like that it's
just laid out at once so you have to
actually manually consider like the
wrapping over so you have to actually
keep that in mind when you're writing
these and that's a tricky part too
um so then you have J which is going to
iterate over um n which is uh n is uh
the number of columns
here and then we plus plus that
like each iteration we we make this
accumulation sum so we're going to
accumulate into the sum right because
you're going You're essentially uh
accumulating things as you're like when
we do the add operation and we have all
these multiplies and we fuse and add
them together that's what this
accumulation sum is for uh and so when
we iterate through um when we iterate
through k um which is K is uh the
the the X Dimension you could say in a
or the number of columns and then K in B
is going to be the height or the number
of rows right and and so you iterate
through that and when you do your sum
you essentially add it and you do um you
do essentially this is where the dot
product comes in right you do a so
that's I where like whatever I is let's
say I is like um I is zero right so I is
going to be um
I is going to be whatever this is right
it's going to be the first the the first
one times whatever K is and K uh K in
this case is going to be well two so
when you have zero the zeroth
um when when I is zero and K is whatever
number it's still going to end up
equaling zero and so you have L
afterwards and that's going to be
whichever spot at what whatever it
wherever it is through through K that's
where it's going to end up at so like
the offset through the row um and it's
going to multiply the same thing it's
going to do um l so L is where it's at
through K which is going to be um the
going up and down instead of left right
it's going to be up and
down and then you have this n term which
we could say is uh maybe also uh zero if
you're just doing the first one here
like the top top left corner and then
say j in this case is zero so it's just
going to end up hitting the it's going
to end up in hitting the same value so
you end up just getting the first the
first points uh and then you you
multiply them together and then you add
that um you you you multiply them you
multiply the first the one and the the
seven together in the first one and then
you end up hitting the second one which
is the two and the 11 um and that gets
summed up together and you're do doing
this every single time uh this for Loop
this second uh for Loop triggers right
so every time this goes through an
iteration you're hitting n and n is uh
just n is just whichever value uh
whichever value is essentially coming
next right and so you're just getting
this one and this one and then this one
and then this one and so on so forth
until the end and then you end up just
writing this out so you you essentially
assign to Value C to whatever that sum
is so that you can compute the next dot
product so uh this this is like very uh
visual I encourage you to I mean if this
doesn't completely make sense if you
haven't like taken a introductory linear
algebra course I completely get it um
you might want to just pass us through
you know language models or look at some
some intuitive videos on the internet
and just sort of understand what's going
on here try to understand uh what like
how things are wrapping around when they
when they do like a dried or something
um that's that's very important to pay
attention to like this like the K when
the K is wrapping for example K is uh K
is here and K is essentially this this
length so it's going to be like
whichever whichever whichever uh row you
want you want to wrap around that entire
row so you want to go to the length of
it and wrap and then your offset is
going to be that and then same idea here
except instead of rows it's going to be
like columns column offset right
um and that's that's the whole idea
there um and then we go into the GPU
implementation which is a little bit
different but we're essentially using
instead of just an i or an ID a single
idx term we use a rows and columns so in
this grid we have the block ID x.y *
block dim doy block idx is you know
where the where the block is at in um
where the essentially where the block is
vertically um and we're just getting
essentially the the vertical thread like
which thread are we do we want within uh
considering like this vertical grid and
all the blocks that we have right uh
going back to what I said before and we
do the same thing with X so we have this
we have the thread in the uh vertical
and the horizontal
Direction uh and then we as we want to
this is actually very this is actually
very uh this is required you actually
have this you need this if statement
here because if things go off track or
if you have like too many threads then
they might go and compute values that
you don't want like it might go access
other parts in memory it's not
restrained right so it's not going to
stop when you think it should stop you
actually need to put careful restraints
on it and say okay well we we want to
stop it once the row gets to M because
there's no other values outside of that
and then same for column as well right
so um like when we go up here we
have we have M by n right so m is the
um m is this
part which is the uh where did it go
yes m is row so row is y right this this
y this height part and then n is is that
uh the the width the horizontal part X
and so that's that's columns which to X
right and so you have to this is just
the kind of thing that you have to be
careful with um Cuda handles this very
well but you just have to include this
if statement and then you essentially
for each thread um because this is
itself in a thread you're going to uh
just do a essentially a a DOT product
between elements and you're you're going
to do like essentially a a row of a row
of a and a column of of B and this is
going to be done per thread
so each different thread is going to
have a different maybe a different uh
row and a different column of B to to to
compute so you have this um you have
this K term which is from here um and
you're you're cycling through that and
you you just essentially apply the same
wrapping but instead of worrying about
all of these nested for Loops you worry
instead about um the rows and columns so
these are your actual uh these are the
you know the way we index with threads
as I was talking about before
um but yeah this is uh I'm going to dig
more into sort of the in intuition
behind this later in the course when we
end up optimizing matrix multiplication
this uh this is this is called a naive
kernel it's it's very it's very limited
it doesn't have a ton of optimizations
it's not like it's not fast it is like
it's like aunds the speed of what
state-ofthe-art is it's actually quite
slow comparatively um and we're going to
optimize this later on and this is going
to be the most intuitive thing you will
probably learn in this entire course is
matrix multiplication in Cuda so don't
worry if it this doesn't entirely click
right now um just kind of worry about
where these threads are how we're
getting how we're getting the row and
column values and then this wrapping
that we have here and then the the
offset part right wrapping and
offset offset um and yeah that's that
that's pretty much all you have to worry
about for now um and then we just do you
know the same route perform warm-up runs
Benchmark it across 20 benchmarks or
across 20 runs um Benchmark CPU versus
GPU and then return the average time in
micros seconds so if I just uh open up a
terminal here and go
nbcc out to two and we go and run that
forming R up
runs okay this is very I actually made
very large matricies maybe we should
shrink these a little bit
um we can
go let's see maybe
256 yeah the CPU is not going to like
that
one uh and so it's benchmarking CPU and
so that takes 89,000 micros and this
takes 88 microc so we get just like out
of the box with these small matricies we
get a 1,000x speed up with using Cuda
um and that's that so this is uh this is
this is uh this is kind of how we test
stuff but yeah now we're going to go
ahead and jump into like how do you
profile these um I know we haven't gone
extensively into um like how Cuda
actually works under the hood completely
there's still more to do but um in a
little bit we're going to hit up
profiling I would like to cover uh
actually some more stuff before we do
that let me close this
out we pop into the read me here just
close this close this um going
to just zoom out a little bit
sure so again we have these these dim
these dim three types um which I was
talking about before these should make
sense already these these should not be
like too hard to grasp
um this is what it normally looks like
right you put in you put this
in you put this in like I said before
it's going to simplify to a dim three so
this is going to look like a 16 by one
by one uh tensor you could say and it's
going to add that to the kernel launch
configuration this is the kernel launch
configuration there's more stuff we can
add to it um already covered this stuff
already uh and then you have more stuff
you can add to it um so we have the grid
dim the grid dims uh in you know 1 to 3D
block di in 1 to 3D and then this uh NS
so this is the number of bytes in shared
memory that is allocated per block for
this call um so you're going to
explicitly allocate memory for a block
um in shared memory which is really fast
so typically you would omit this uh
however if you have a specific uh
production like you're trying to deploy
a CTIC kernel in production to run
something really really fast you might
actually want to capitalize off of this
because it'll give you more explicit
control over what happens and you can
measure performance a bit better and
you'll get maybe get some some little
some little performance gains out of
that and then there's this s term which
is uh the stream it's in and I'm going
to cover streams actually number five so
don't worry about this too much but but
streams are pretty cool they let you do
some some interesting stuff
um and then this I didn't talk about
this entirely too much Cuda device
synchronize and sync threads so Cuda
device synchronize ensures all the
kernels or all of the uh threads for one
problem are all of the like all of the
all the different parallel computations
for a problem are done before you begin
the next so when you when you launch a
kernel it's going to have a bunch of
blocks in parel and a bunch of threads
in parallel run this massive problem um
and they might not all finish at the
same time like some of them just like do
to physics they're they might like not
finish at the exact same time and so you
have to explicitly synchronize them you
have to add this little barrier this
this ume essentially preventing a a race
condition
so if you have a bunch of threads um
like for example in this one when you're
bit shifting when you're like moving
this one over here and then this one
over here and then this one over here
it's like well ideally you'd want to do
this in a certain order and not like
store something before it's not supposed
to be stored like if um for example if I
do this one um and then this one is
supposed to happen after but it ends up
doing this one first because we didn't
synchronize properly um you could you'll
end up with the wrong answer right so
you have to purposely synchronize the
thread so that all of them regardless of
like this one might be like way ahead
you have to wait for all the other ones
to catch up in order for them to hit the
same spot so you say okay this one's
done but these ones aren't we're going
to wait for all these to synchronize up
together and then we can continue the
next step right that's what uh Cuda
device synchronize synchronize will do
uh after you typically put this after
launching a kernel and then sync threads
is put with in a kernel um for threat
execution inside of it so one is like
out like when you're trying to
synchronize the whole grid and then one
is like synchronize all the threads
within a within like
a within a warp so as you might have
been able to tell I was a little bit
unsure about that last answer so I
decided to look it up and sync threads
is actually on the level of uh thread
blocks instead of warps so you can do
syn warps instead of sync threads
actually pop back to here and we go at
sync the sync threads you can actually
do um if you want to do warps you can
do stin
warps
um to sync all of the threads within a
warp and then this one will do that it
the same thing but a thread block
instead
all reds within a
war
um and then this is for an entire thread
block so just just a piece of
clarification there one other cool thing
I came across when uh studying Cuda is
how you can actually add in uh explicit
flags and you can you can actually
convert something like a log to log f
using compiler Flags
um and I know that there's a little bit
to unpack there but if I just go back to
uh this compilation here actually no we
don't even use we don't even use any of
those M functions but if I were to say
do like log inside of a kernel um that
would go slower than if I were to use
log F so log f is like a device
operation and log is a host operation so
designed to run on CPU on CPU course
right um so we can actually do do use
fast math as a part of the compiler
Flags I can go um
use use fast math like
this and of course we won't really see
any difference
but um yeah like same 1006 X same thing
um but this will actually convert this
to this in case you don't in case you
haven't done that uh yet on your own so
this actually comes from the Cuda math
API reference manual so uh if we look at
say like some of the single Precision uh
intrinsics yeah so uh single Precision
intrinsic functions that are supported
only in device
code right notice how it has like Co F
uh x uh uh exponentiate with base 10 f
expf um and then like you know F add um
round toward zero right all of these
These are these are designed to execute
on device um and they have F at the end
but if you were to just do like just
Coast for example from the math.h librar
and C that wouldn't that wouldn't run as
fast so this is another little thing you
could add to your kernels if you're
trying to say do like um if you're
trying to do like soft Max or something
in a kernel or if you're trying to um
maybe do like uh like some Digital
Signal processing right you can add
these and and get uh some benefits and
performance- wise out of those um and
same thing here like if you wanted to do
a fuse multiply ad um this will like
tell the actual uh this will
actually like pour this into the
instructions where instead of doing like
separate uh multiply and add operations
you're fusing them together so you can
do little tricks like this and just to
speed things up performance wise but
uh yeah now we can uh now we can
actually dive into uh
profiling I actually forgot to do the
tiled matrix multiplication by hand so I
figured I'll just squeeze this in now
and and let your mind sit on this for a
little bit before we actually start
using it and applying it um but before
we had this this idea of a matrix
multiplication which was um you have
like a
you have like a matrix
a and can you see that maybe not I'm
going to move this
down switch Mark
here a matrix
a you with some numbers in it maybe
and B and the whole idea here is we do
product this with
this this with this this with this do
the same thing and we bring it down
here right all the way till the end um
that is one way to do matrix
multiplication however you can actually
make this more efficient by using
something called piling
so I'll provide some examples on this
later in the course but this is the idea
here
um you have these uh you have these two
matrices A and B so I'm just going to
you have to look at this a little bit
different
but this is what it looks
like
so we have say
um let's just say this is a and this is
B okay and then you have this C Matrix
and how do you compute like the first
element right well you would you would
typically take this row and then this
column and then you would put that there
because that's where they intersect
right um but what you can do is you can
actually take a chunk you can take a
chunk like an actual square or rectangle
of a so like maybe this I just put this
into like separate
pieces say this is like a like you know
maybe a a 9
by9 right and this is also a 9
by so technically each this each of
these is technically like a 3X3 tile or
a matrix on its own right and so we're
just splitting up splitting this up into
tiles and so what you can do here
is you can as I've lined out here you
can you can go one time you could do a
Matrix Matrix here times The Matrix
there um Like A and B respectively like
you do a * b um and then you add that to
the Matrix multiply of two and two A and
B respectively and then three and
three you start with these and then you
then you add to these and you add to
these so it's like
A1 A1 *
B1 you multiply those and then you add
it to A2 * B2 and then add that to A3 *
B3 and then you end up with this with
this C1 here and that's the output and
this is exactly what I've written out in
a sort of cube format is like you've
you've laid out some Matrix a right here
um which is like a a row and then you've
laid out some M Matrix B here um and
you're just you're
doing this times this and then add to
this times this and then add to this
times this um and that's and then you
just end up with C1 and so what you can
do with like the reason why this is so
effective is because you can you can
actually put these tiles and you can pop
them over to a faster memory like like
shared memory uh and then they'll end up
running like ridiculously fast and you
can end up doing these computations like
way faster so if you split it into
little tiles
and let each little like streaming
multiprocessor on the on the chip
actually take care of the individual uh
tile or multiple tiles um then you can
actually get a lot more useful uh you
get a lot more a lot higher uh compute
throughput you could say um but don't
worry about this too extensively this is
just the intuition behind tiling like
the difference between this and the
normal version we were doing where we
like take a whole row and then we take a
whole column and then we dot product
them together
this is different than that so that I
just wanted to put that in your head for
later so that it's not a complete
surprise when we try to make this
faster now we dig into how can we
actually profile the performance metrics
of our own kernels so how do we optimize
these right and we're going to use
Nvidia andite compute for this um if
you're on Windows you might you might
not have this it might look a bit
different I haven't tried it on Windows
yet but this is what we're going to use
on Linux here so this is kind of what it
looks like at the end you can see a
bunch of details about things um it's
very very interesting but we're going to
dig into this in a second here just
going to close these off and uh we'll go
ahead and get started so let me close
these here we'll see in this in this uh
number five kernels chapter in profiling
we have a bunch of files so we're going
to start off with this one the mvtx
matmo so what is what the heck is mvtx
you guys already know what matrix
multiplication is I'm not going to go
over that nvx is like the the custom
profiler for uh Kudo kernels right and
what this allows you to do is it's
actually quite straightforward if you
look at what's happening here like it's
it actually makes a lot of sense what's
happening so we're able to push this
into a range like essentially the
timeline um push matrix multiplication
push memory allocation right so we're
doing the
um this is the whole this is the whole
matrix multiplication thing from start
to finish um we push things into a range
so memory allocation and then we pop
that we pop that out um we copy pop that
out so it's like start and finish uh and
then we we do our our dim
threes we start kernel execution and
then it's going to stop that once we've
launched the kernel run it and then
synchronize all of our um like our
everything in our
grid and then copy back to host right uh
so this is like very straightforward
literally all you need so I mean keep in
mind like when we start this one we we
have another one afterwards so this one
is only going to Target the recent one
that was put up right so it's not going
to jump back to the first one that was
ever pushed in it's going to be like
kind of uh like brackets right so you
have the uh one layer of brackets on the
outside and then one on the inside it's
like um it kind of that that's kind of
the structure of these of this nbtx tool
um so when we go ahead and
nbcc um this we want to pass in the uh
link NV tools extension that's what mvtx
stands for so Nvidia tools extension
we're going to compile that we can go
ahead and you know run this it'll it'll
run as expected good um and then we can
actually if we pop back to this read me
file um we can do NYS profile
uh stats equals true on the um it's not
mammal it's 0 but if we go ahead and run
this we will notice that there's a bunch
of cool stats that pop up now if you're
running from a remote machine you could
you could use this you could just look
at this directly from the terminal
however the uh Nvidia ight compute app
itself is actually a bit more
informative than this so
what we can do is is type your Windows
key and go windows and then type ncu and
then press enter and it should bring up
um eni compute and
it it it popped up on my second monitor
I just brought it over here but this is
what it should look like um and what you
can do from here is um I'm just going to
put this on the second one and then drag
the uh report NIS rep file so not the SQ
light the SQ light is for for a
different thing but we drag this uh into
the into the sidebar
here now it's in we can see it at the
top and now there's a bunch of
interesting things in here that we can
look at so this this text might be a
little small if you're on a phone but
just bear with me here so we have bunch
of stuff on threads um you know nbtx
what is like what is happening
sequentially here we can actually zoom
in and see um you know the memory copy
kernel execution takes about 2
milliseconds and we can see everything
right so all these are actually pushed
into the range and we can see what's
happening um and then of course the you
know the memory allocation takes a while
uh and then the matrix multiplication
from start to finish like we highlighted
in the code um so that's that's how
that's what mvtx does you can push
things into a range and you can see how
long it actually takes you can see like
when it's happening on the timeline and
you can look more more in more detail as
to like what's happening there right so
um anyways if we go to the Cuda Hardware
at the top here we can see uh it
consists of kernels and memory so
there's like um copying so cud M Copy
and then there's the Matrix M kernel
that we can see here and if we click on
this we go show in events view we can
click on this down here Zoom to selected
on
timeline we can rightclick we can go
profile kernel
and there's a bunch of interesting
things here and this might be a little
might be a little overwhelming at first
but there's common filter metrics PM
sampling warp sampling other so we're
just going to use PM sampling right now
um PM sampling is performance metric
sampling so it's going to give us very
detailed metrics about things and we'll
be able to optimize from that so it's
going to use this binary 0 file that we
that we made before during compilation
um and it's going to bring up this new
menu here which is different than the
timeline one um so this timeline view
and then this is different so in here um
you know we can see all of our Kernels
at the top so in case we were like maybe
profiling two different matrix
multiplication kernels they they might
both show up here like the the the
runtime the lifetime of our program that
that's what would pop up here uh and all
the kernels inside of that so uh if we
go to you know say summary there's
there's some interesting stuff here
maybe we don't maybe we don't care about
this too much there's there's details um
so you have uh throughput so overview of
throughput for compute and memory
resources um PM sampling so uh
performance metrics we can bring this
down and we can see things like SM
throughput uh pipe throughput um a bunch
of the a bunch of metrics I don't even
understand yet but uh we have things
like cach hit rate which is really which
is really useful um but if we go to like
speed of light throughput for example um
this is this this is for the memory
resources we have the compute throughput
as a percent so that's at about 90 97%
and then memory is also at about
97% so um you know we we get we get to
see cool things like this and and it'll
make more sense in a second here we go
down
to uh memory workload analysis we can
see memory throughput in it like very
detailed memory uh I guess memory
metrics so gigabytes per second how much
how much are we able to transfer back
and forth right bytes um Dam bytes per
second so that GPU vram how how fast are
we accessing that um and that that speed
is about 41 gabes per second which um
which is not super high and then we have
like uh L1 hit rates L2 hit rates all
this and we can see a memory chart here
there's just like a whole bunch of
metrics that we get access to um and so
if we can we can we can look at we can
pay attention to like this number 41 um
we'll we'll keep this number in our head
for now um there's also a source too so
uh you can look at the actual assembly
instructions and see um you know how
many registers is it taken up uh a bunch
of very lowlevel stuff um which I'm not
going to dig into right now um but yeah
there there there's so many settings
that to dig through anyways we're going
to keep this number um 41 in our
head
[Music]
now we close this out we'll just put on
the side for
now we have some other we have some
other uh scripts as well so I have a
naive mmal so this is the one that we
wrote previously this is the exact same
just our direct copy and paste uh and
then we have a tiled ml which I'm going
to cover a little bit later it's a bit
more advanced against um
but we're going to compare the
performance metrics of the naive versus
the til ml
so if we go ahead and pop into here we
go
nbcc uh 01 and then 01 and we link uh
Envy
tools we run successfully and we can go
n this profile and then put in 01 right
there and I'm going to go ahead and drag
this so we pop up another one I'm going
to go drag this into an Insight
compute
and if we check out our uh Cuda Hardware
go to kernels Matrix multiply this is
the night version remember uh show an
events view Zoom to
selected
profile uh we run the PM sampling again
it's going to run that and then we take
a look at our new stats um you this is
this is the exact same thing without
mvtx but just for context
details memory workload so we get you
know 30 37 it's it's pretty close to
what we had before right um maybe a
little bit lower um but when we when we
compile the til MML
it works as expected and say
profile we're going to get a number
three
here I'm going to goad and drag this
into Insight
compute we open this
up pop over to our
kernels Matrix multiply optimized show
in
events assum to select it on timeline so
we can see the length of this by the way
this is how long it takes it's going to
go from you know 430 milliseconds
43024 millisecs all the way to
[Music]
431.073 is significantly higher than it
was before so these are the types of
things you want to look out for when you
see your memory throughput drop after
you change something it's like uh maybe
we maybe we shouldn't do that um you
know from here it went from uh the naive
it was at 37 and here it's at 60 right
so that's making a a better use of
memory um and we'll we'll we'll see more
optimizations later on especially in
this in this um faster matal chapter as
to how we can seriously get this number
up
um but yeah this is this is how you
profile there's a bunch of cool things
you want to look out for here um it
really depends on which algorithm you're
working with with matrix multiplication
uh there's some more like there's some
more um fine grain optimizations that
are just proven to work so we just we
can just run those and and kind of
compare the difference uh but the you
have you have all the resources at your
hand here there's tons of things that
you can use and learn from so uh yeah
this is uh this is how you profile Cuda
kernels using Nvidia andite
compute I have a readme file here with
just pretty much everything we went over
so um the NS profile command
um you can profile python as well so NS
profile and then um you can do you have
a like an MLP script in Python you can
profile that funny enough and it'll just
use the whatever whatever Nvidia
libraries is you that python file is
using
um then we have just you can do this
some stuff over the command line like
this
so uh ncu kernel name you can you can do
stuff over the command line um but yeah
there's there's a bunch of useful tools
here uh so this will this might be
updated later on um it's not in like the
the best format yet so this might look a
bit different when you when you see it
but uh these are kind of the the main
ideas and then just to just to I guess
leave it off on an end note um cupti or
Cuda um Cuda profiling tools interface
the PTI at the end this is for like
creation creating your own uh the
creating your own custom profiling and
tracing tools that Target specific C
applications so you can you can like
design your own profiling tools with
this um if that's something that catches
your interest you might want to look
more into it so I'll leave this here uh
but that's that's how you profile cutic
kernels next up we have this thing
called an atomic operation and atomic
operations are used in very specific
cases so I'm going to try to cover these
as best I can by atomic we mean the
indivisibility concept in physics where
thing cannot be broken down further
right so you have an atom it's like oh I
mean technically there are quarks and
stuff but you don't worry about those
it's just like the indivis
indivisibility concept of this thing you
you cannot cut it in half right there
are Parts maybe inside of it that that
make it up but you cannot you cannot cut
it in half um and that's that's what
this Atomic operation is and it operates
as a software abstraction for us so the
hardware and the Cuda compiler take care
of all this for us um essentially an
atomic operation ensures that a
particular operation on a memory
location is completed entirely by one
thread before another thread can access
or modify the same memory location this
prevents raise conditions so remember
before when we were talking about how
there are like multiple threads that
like one might end up being faster and
hit the goal before this one and it's
they sort of need to like not modify
each other's uh they not they need to
like not mess with each other's things
so that that's what this idea is
referring to um
so cannot access or modify the same
memory location of another thread that's
very it's a very key point right um and
and we're going to see a very Crystal
Clear example of this in a second um
we might lose some speed
so if we limit the amount of work done
on a single piece of memory per unit
time through put an atomic operation
we're we're going to lose some speed
from that right if we're locking things
down and limiting how how fast the
program can finish by just having
everything like not wait for everything
else then it just finishes faster right
so uh when we use atomics things will
slow down but it is guaranteed to be
Memory safe um and that that's
ultimately what you might care about in
some cases it might be better to get the
memory safe aspect instead of instead of
the performance gain um so there's a
bunch of different Atomic operations
that we have I'm just going to make this
a bit easier to see um you have Atomic
ad so essentially what this is you have
a you have an in uh a pointer to an INT
some some memory address and you have a
value and all you do is adds value to
the value at address so when we when we
pass in like for example say the number
four and then we get the memory address
to that which is some hex code we put
that we put that hex code in here and
then we put a Val let's say like two and
so what that'll do is it'll say okay
well we have the memory address let's um
let's get the value for that memory
address which is four and then we're
going to add the value to that so it's
just like this memory address stays the
same there's nothing new being created
it's just you're taking this value and
you're adding it on top um and that's
that's kind of the whole philosophy of
everything in here so
substitution um exchange and and and the
return value will always be the old
value so when we do like Atomic add and
then we say like put int equals Atomic
ad or of of of whatever is in here it's
going to return the old value of
whatever this was so it's going to
essentially return um the value at
address right um so we can sort of
compare and contrast it's it lets us do
that um or you could just not like
return anything that's fine you could
just if you just want to add Val to that
to the value then to the address value
then you can just do that um but these
are all of the uh these are all the
operations that come with atomic uh
these are all the atomic operations
um there's also floating Point Atomic
operations
um so you you you can think of atomics
as like a very fast
uh Hardware Mutual exclusion operation
um and I'll I'll dig into mutexes in a
second here but essentially how this
goes is you lock down a memory location
um you set old value the The Returned
value equal to um like d referencing
that memory location so like the hex
code and then you get the value for that
you set the old you set this old value
that you're going to return equal to
that um that that D reference value
um and then we set
the we set the D referenced memory
location so that value that goes with
that hex code to the old Value Plus the
increment which is which is Val right
this is int Val um and then we unlock
the memory location we return it so it's
just like during this part where we're
incrementing and we're storing the old
value we're going to lock it down so
nothing else can interfere with that
it's just this has to complete this is
priority and that'll that priority will
exist through however many core threads
we we have right so that way they can't
interfere with each other so one has to
finish before another one accesses it
um and then we just return that right
so um in terms of mutual exclusion
there's a nice YouTube link on here that
I found which was very good um Mutual is
is like a like a shared relationship
between entities so all of us threads um
we're going to the act of keeping
something out or preventing ACD
so we're going to exclude uh everyone
else from accessing each other's thing
we're going to let each other finish
right that's that's that's Mutual
exclusion and this applies to atomics
right um so you don't have multiple
threads accessing the same thing at
once um and there's there's like an
intuitive example here of like what this
might look um at at a lower level what
this is actually doing so uh if we go
over to our Atomic ad over here
um if I if I nvcc compile this um we'll
see like first of all we import whatever
we need to the cudar
runtime. um we have a number of threads
so a th000 threads per block and then a
th000 blocks in the grid um these are
these are macros that we Define so if
there are a th000 blocks with each 1,000
threads inside of them then we're going
to have a total of a million threads
right um and then we have two kernels
here so one is going to increment count
counter non atomically so it's going to
take in a counter uh it's going to store
that old value as the D referenced
counter CU this is a pointer right um
we're going to set the new value to
whatever this is whatever that actual
integer value is plus one we're just
going to increment by one and then we're
going to um we're going to update
counter right um and then there's an
atomic version of this which does the
same thing except it locks instead so
this part here um this is actually like
you're adding you're essentially adding
uh not
locked and this is
not not
unlocked right so you're supposed to
lock here and then unlock there and
return whatever that is
so I'm if that's I think that's correct
yes
so we go down and everything here is is
fairly intuitive we have our numb blocks
and our num threads and it's the idea is
we're going to have a million threads
that are each trying to update this same
this same counter because we pass this
this counter this is a single variable
or a single pointer that we pass in um
and all of these threads have to have to
modify the same thing right so when we
actually run
this you're you're going to see
non-atomic counter value is 41 so this
means that all of these threads are
attacking the same the same memory
address and they're all performing
modifications on it at the same time but
Atomic it's going to take a little while
longer it might take a million
operations instead of 41 but it's going
to ensure that we get through this
properly so it's going to say okay well
this thread wants to access it so we
need to lock down uh only this thread
can access this value and then all the
other threads instead of racing to it
they're going to just wait because it's
an atomic operation right and so this
one gets to complete first and then
maybe this guy and then this guy and
then this guy and they and they all sort
of complete um and then you end up with
the actual true answer which is uh 1
million right because it increments uh
it increments from
uh increments from from
zero so that's that's pretty much
atomics
um they're pretty cool maybe you can
think of a way that you could use them
right now I don't know um but that's
that's just something that's super
important to cover because uh that's
that's one of the the risks with uh
kernels is that you have a bunch of
these a bunch of different threads
accessing the same the same thing and
making changes that maybe you don't want
to it um and not like getting any errors
or warnings about it right that's that's
a danger that you have so atomics helps
secure that and lock that down so now we
go into Cuda streams and Cuda streams
are one of the most useful things for
performance optimization uh in maybe
even large systems right so this
actually this especially Works in large
systems and you're going to see why in a
second here um so you can think of the
intuition here you can think of streams
as River streams where the uh direction
of operations flows only forward in time
so you have this this timeline and the
idea is normally you would copy some
data over from host to device and then
you would do something with that data
like a kernel launch and and then you
would copy that back from device to host
to do something useful with it um and
what you have here is you have these
little dependencies where it's like you
have to wait for the data to come in
before you actually start the kernel
launch wouldn't you always want to be
running kernels and wouldn't you always
want to be doing computation well
streams actually solves that issue for
us instead of just having one little
timeline you can have an extra layer
underneath it too and even even even
more you can have as many layers as you
want and the the whole idea is you can
copy some copy something over do a
kernel launch and then during that
kernel launch like when when that stuff
gets copied over you can start copying
the next stuff over in a separate stream
right so you can you'll be doing some
computation while you're copying stuff
over and then when this stuff is copied
over um you can do the next kernel so
it'll it'll look like sort of a
staircase and I have an example of this
in the uh Nvidia documentation here the
Nvidia streams and concurrency
slides um and essentially looks like
this so you have um this thing called
cuda mem copy async which is
asynchronous um and normally if you're
doing a Serial program which is what
we've worked with so far you'd be doing
you'd be going in this fashion where
you're you're not always doing you'd be
like C copy something over do something
with it copy it back copy something over
do something with back and then in this
example you like copy a bunch of stuff
over host to device and then you do um
maybe
uh maybe it's better Illustrated in this
example is like you you you copy some
stuff over you do you know you do like
say like three kernels in a row um and
then whilst a kernel is running you're
always copying new stuff over so you're
not like you're not you're always doing
work across all the Stream
right uh and this is super useful
especially when you have something like
um when you have things like training a
massive language model right when you're
trying to when you have this data loader
that is like constantly loading big
chunks of text in you don't want to be
waiting for that you don't want to just
do your your your training forward and
backward pass and then and then wait for
it again you want like you want it to be
loaded in while you're doing your
forward and backward pass like you want
it to be ready for you so that way you
can just start you can just do it again
so it's like non-stop forb back or right
just you never want to stop doing that
and that will that will greatly increase
performance and so this is where Cuda
streams come in right um so this this
whole idea that I'm talking about with
like fetching data um before before you
actually need it like it's literally
called prefetching software abstraction
called pre-etching um so you move data
around before it as needed and this
hides the latency of moving data around
like Cuda M Copy right um
so we have this we have this kernel
launch configuration seen this before we
have a grid size we have a block size
right and then there were two other
things that I talked about which are
here now this is the the number of bytes
in shared memory right so you're you're
doing stuff with shared memory which
don't even worry about that right now
and then there's this other one s which
is the associated stream right so you
can actually put a specific current on a
stream as we showed in here right um you
can have these are all the different
streams stream one stream two stream
three stream four so you have you you
launch this one on stream one and Etc
right so that's that's the whole idea
there
um and this this this is just a super
easy way to interface with the streams
when we do our Colonel launches so there
there's multiple things that come in
here when we're dealing with streams so
you get this this thing of uh priorities
so create streams with different
priorities and if we go into
[Music]
um I don't know if it's in this one
maybe this script we if we look at the
get priority range here we can see um
this takes in a pointer to a least
priority int just a variable and then a
greatest priority int and so it's like
this is the least priority we're going
to we're going to plug this in here uh
and then we have a greatest priority
which which we plug in here right and
that's our range and
so we can feed these in so that uh Cuda
will actually manage which ones get more
priority over others so if you want to
uh load in a bunch of data first and
that's your initial priority you want to
like get that part done as fast as
possible you can actually prioritize
that um with like least and greatest
priority right
um and then we go uh a little
bit a little bit further down
and we have some examples here so let me
just touch on the basics here so there's
some stuff that you may have not seen
before which I probably used earlier but
I did mention it these are macros uh
these are the error checking macros that
we have to essentially make sure that
operations go through successfully so
when when we do like a Cuda Malik we
want to make sure that that that that
went successfully right and that'll just
this will
um this will return a Cuda error type
meaning either success or error like
fail right just indicating whether that
went through or not um so that that's
what that is and
then if we scroll down a little bit more
and see where the actual streams are
happening um keep in
mind up here we we use this Cuda stream
type right so it's a Cuda stream type
and we Define two streams that stream 1
and
two we create the Stream So we actually
have to have custom uh handlers for this
to say like okay you made this you made
you defined it it's like now you have to
actually create the thing it's a it's a
weird context thing Nvidia has but it it
it ensures everything is safe um and
handled properly by the
compiler
so we get this other term kudam mam copy
async and this essentially just allows
us to um have like these asynchronous
copies I mean when you have these
ordered like if you go camm copy async
on stream one and then later on you have
like a like like a kernel launch like
right underneath it um it'll actually go
in that order so it won't just it won't
um it won't try to do like the kernel
launch before because it's asynchronous
um it'll just be asynchronous meaning in
the context of streams so you can have
things sort of um happening I guess
concurrently um but it'll still follow
that sequential order within that stream
as long as you assign them to the same
one um so then we have our thread for
block and blocks per grid configuration
we launch this on stream one and we have
this this B this uh this B uh array on
on stream
2 and we can do stuff with that as well
so and then notice how we have the
commment copy inputs the device
asynchronously so this is just a little
cheat where instead of instead of
copying copying uh a from hosted device
then copying B to from hosted device uh
sequentially you do at the same time so
a gets copied and B gets copied at the
same time and then you don't have this
extra barrier here where like nothing no
work is being done you can just get
right to uh kernel computation right um
so we we see that here we have a stream
one and stream two and this is all done
on stream one so all this all this
memory is going to be shared um
and uh we we go down further to this you
know we copy back we copy C back
asynchronously but there's only one so
it doesn't really matter which stream
that's on um we just do async because
why not and then the stream synchronize
so we're going to ensure that all of the
streams are then caught up and then we
can um and then we can do something with
that right so we're going to you know
free the device viice a BC and then
destroy both of the streams uh and then
it's and then it's done so if I go ahead
and actually compile and run
this test passed and we got everything
correctly and we did this vector
addition um so it's just kind of what
what we all we really did here was just
uh this is where the magic happens
instead of loading a and then B we load
and B at the same time um and then we go
into um what's it
called
Advanced so going to lower this a little
bit so you can see so when we go into
advanced streams things get a little
weirder uh but it's not too crazy so
there's a few things that I want to
introduce here we have pinned memory so
it's essentially saying on on the CPU uh
Global Dr it's going to reserve this
piece of memory we're going to we're
going to pin it using Cuda Malik host um
send it just saying you know this is a
part of Cuda it's reserved for uh the
GPU to use later so we're not going to
modify that we're not going to let the
operating system or anything play with
this we're just going to pin it nothing
can touch it and then we're going to
drag that over somewhere else for later
and we're just going to like reserve
that right um so we're going to use this
we're going to need this for later so
don't play with it is a good way to
think about this
um events are a critical part of using
streams so we can measure kernel
execution time given this uh given this
example here so we have an event type
start and stop so the these don't
actually time anything but they are um
they're part of uh the input to these uh
Event Event record functions so we go
and create these with the memory
addresses of start and stop and then we
can plug in whatever stream for example
just stream or stream one or stream two
we we do an event
record we do uh we launch our kernel on
this stream and then we do another event
record um in this
stream and we can take these values
start and stop and they might carry
metadata I don't know exactly how Cuda
handles this but start and stop we can
uh synchronize we can synchronize uh
everything and then we can plug it into
Cuda event lapse time which takes this
milliseconds float uh which is going to
be a milliseconds and then you have your
start and stop and that's going to tell
you how long your kernel took to run
right so instead of launching it in the
instead of going into the the ncu
profiler you can just do this instead if
you want to and this will this will not
have any computational overhead or it's
very minimal so this can be run in like
production environments it's not really
going to cost you anything um and then
you have the synchronization between
streams so um essentially these events
will synchronize they will be placed in
individual streams so instead of the
whole device or across all the streams
it's just one specific stream right that
that's the whole idea with these um and
then of course you can overlap uh
computation data transfer with uh the
prefetching idea which we talked about
uh before which I
believe pre fetching yes so events are
great for that um and then we have
callbacks which are used slightly
differently you you can essentially set
up a pipeline where the completion of
one operation on the GPU triggers the
start of another on the CPU so this is
going to have some more overhead but if
you want to log when something happens
when you want to log when something
happens on your GPU then you can use a
call back um so in in this context we
have a kernel uh and then you know in
like we have we have a like say say like
some stream like stream one and then we
place this call back right after the
kernel so in the timeline it's going to
show up as kernel and Cuda stream at
callback just as the way they are from
like top to bottom in the code and if
they're in the same stream um and we put
this this call back in and that's the
entally going to say when this finishes
when when this finishes we're going to
call this function
um and it's just going to print GPU
operation completed right so that's uh
that that's like one use case of
callbacks you might not use them all the
time you're probably going to use events
more if you're really trying to get
those optimizations out but let's go
ahead and look at the uh Advanced
section here so
um we have we have kernel one which is
going to multiply by two and we have
kernel 2 which is going to add one all
right very simple operations we have our
call back here stream call back
operation completed just print print out
when something happened right um and
then just sort of like flowing from top
to bottom here we do our our Cuda stream
type so we just declare some streams we
have our Cuda event type we're just
going to initialize an event um we can
print out whatever that event is I was
testing earlier so this that's why this
is still here um we do our Cuda malic
host for that pinned memory um we could
amalik our um our device
data we do our our greatest and least
priorities like I was talking about
before uh we create we actually create
the event itself using this previous
event type that we initialized here and
then we um we do our you know uh Cuda
Cuda M Copy async uh we we launch a
kernel and then this is where things
start to get a little tricky and I'll do
my best to explain so when we do Cuda
event record that's going to place a
little marker like a little tick right
in that stream so we have the stream one
here um you know this this is on stream
one this on stream one this is on stream
one so you're going to do your your copy
from hosted device and then you're going
to do the kernel and then you're going
to put a little tick mark right here um
and what that says is
um we we might want to do something when
when this gets reached so notice how
this is right below our kernel so when
the kernel is finished when it is done
uh this is going to this is this is
going to trigger right and then we have
this stream weight event as a little
dependency so it's essentially going to
wait for everything up to uh stream
stream one to finish and then it's going
to begin on on stream two so stream two
has to actually wait for this to happen
notice how we pass in uh a stream we
which is stream two so stream stream 2
will start doing its things like Colonel
execution and and the call back um we
have to wait
for where did it go we have to wait for
this event to trigger first and that's
essentially all this is is it just waits
for it and then it begins on stream to
when all of these previous ones are
completed
right or at least everything else in uh
everything else in stream stream one so
these two so then stream two comes along
after this is done after we've actually
done our kernel
execution and then stream two is going
to run this second kernel so it just
it's just kind of ordered in that way so
you have the async CM copy kernel one
and then it's going to wait for that to
finish and then drop down in stream two
it's going to start um it's going to
start the second kernel execution and
then when this is done so when when um
once we complete this point this is like
another marker in the timeline
it's going to wait for all that to
complete and then it's going to say okay
awesome we can now do a call back and
then it's going to go up to this
function here and it's going to and it's
going to run that um so that's just kind
of like stepping through uh one by one
what is happening there
um and then we'll just copy back to post
with Cuda Cuda mem copy async uh and
then to finalize we always want to uh
synchronize our streams so we have all
these streams that are happening we've
just added another layer of complexity
we need to synchronize those up too
right so there's the whole device
synchronized which is like you
synchronize all the threads in the
device and then there's this one which
is on the level of stream so you have
like maybe stream one 2 3 four and you
like wait for all of them to like finish
um before you before you continue right
you wait for all them to catch up by
adding a little barrier blocking um and
and that's what's happening here and
then we just destroy all of these we
just essentially remove all these
contexts and then we're good to go so
that's uh that's how stream work that's
how this Advanced thing works under the
hood um if I go ahead and run
this so we notice how when we when we
are printing out uh where did it go when
we're printing out the event the event
is just a pointer so it's like a it's
just like a memory address thing and
then we got our our operation completed
so that's when we do this with when we
do this call back and then we end up
with the test passed afterwards so uh
you know just referencing back to that
Nvidia diagram with all the all the
different streams like that that's
essentially what you care about
right so I hope the last part wasn't too
conceptually hard for you that that's
typically where uh people will sort of
break down and and question a lot of
things it it was probably hard but
anyways I'm glad you made it through
feel free to rewatch some parts that is
one of the most challenging parts of the
course there's lot to unpack it's very
spatially intuitive but this part is
supposed to not be very spatially
intuitive it is supposed to be just like
textbook examples uh this is how you
navigate things it's it's not supposed
to be very hard mathematically spatially
anything so this is this chapter is on
the Cuda API so this is chapter six Cuda
apis um we have a few to go through
kublos CNN Etc but I want you to
navigate over to docs. nvidia.com
Cuda so here we have a lot of resources
we have a lot of cool things to look at
um and I just kind of want to point this
out not that it's specific to uh the cud
API section but because there's a lot of
there's a lot of useful things here so
you have your installation guides for
like Windows and Linux right like this
is just like everything you need to get
started um programming guide best
practices all the different you know
Maxwell Pascal VTA Turing m here Hopper
Ada Maxwell um all these different
compatibility guides and tuning guides
uh for different architectures and then
you have like your PTX which is the
assembly instructions for Cuda that's
what it compiles down to uh and then
just like API references miscellaneous
stuff um and tools like nbcc uh GDB for
Cuda so when we covered GDB earlier in
the C+ plus review section this is the
equivalent for Cuda so when you're
debugging Cuda programs you'd use that
uh and then there's like Insite compute
which we used earlier um and that's yeah
just a lot of very informative tools
here what we mostly care about is the C
API references so in here we have
runtime API driver API math API you can
go through those if you want but mainly
what I'm going to cover is kublos and
cdnn which is over here if you go to
docs. video.com deeplearning CNN you can
find this and these are the main ones
which I expect to cover in this section
so you can think of these uh like kublos
and CNN as they're not you're not
actually writing you're not writing
things out
manually you're not writing out your own
kernels it's the the whole idea here is
you have like this this black box
function that you call or like a it's
binded to a shared object file like an
so and it's opaque so they use these
these this word called an opaque struct
type and what that is is is you're just
calling something that is compiled down
to to run on the hardware you do not get
to see it because it's you know in
encoded in some binary format that you
can't really read as a human and so you
have to refer to these opaque struct
types to be able to call those these are
highly optimized so like the
state-of-the-art algorithms in the world
uh for running you know deep learning
algorithms that these are the fastest
ones um sometimes you might get
something faster depending on the use
case but we'll generally assume that
these that the Cuda API provides the
fastest functions uh generally speaking
so when you're trying to figure out how
to get the fastest possible inference to
work on your GPU
cluster uh you might want to uh you know
use something like Cuda API um and then
going through uh you know just going
through and researching and figuring out
how to get it done by going to like
Google search perplexity Chad gbt um you
know maybe anthropic
models and then keyword searching in the
Nvidia docs like just a crlf like that
um but the the C API is going to give
you the fastest stuff right um You may
have seen this before how we did this
these like error checks um and these
essentially just just say like when you
call a function and say like kublos um
you're you're going to check if if that
return an error or not and if it does
you're going to print the error and the
line it was at right so these are just
custom ways of of printing out errors
and when things don't go according to
plan so I have these both for um kblast
and qnn so it just checks the function
make sure it went through properly
um
now kuas is short for Cuda so the CU is
for Cuda basic linear algebra sub
routines or subsystems I can't remember
which one but it's it's for it's for
linear algebra stuff like matrix
multiplication right and sgem which is a
short for single Precision General
matrix
multiplication
um and that's that that's like pretty
much what this whole like GRE me file is
about I'm kind of like reciting it as we
go down but um you know there there are
resources on this like proper error
checking Library samples um if we were
to go to this there's like a library
samples where you can test out each of
these um
but the the whole idea with kublos and
and how it's important to deep learning
is in in something like the transformer
or an MLP in the Transformer itself
you're going to use this algorithm
called matrix multiplication and when
you want the MLP to run really fast or
you want this language model to have
really really fast inference time you
want the algorithms to not really have
bottlenecks right you want them to run
as fast as possible on the hardware and
so using the sub routines in kuas you
can actually get that um there are other
ways where you can like combine and mix
things together but that's more advanced
for now we're just assume that the
fastest algorithms exist in kublos and
CNN for deep learning purposes um so
we're going to go ahead and start here
with uh
kublos
now basic linear algebra sub programs
um for accelerating AI high performance
applications like I said before
um industry standard blast apis and Gem
API so General matrix multiplication
with support for fusions highly
optimized for NVIDIA gpus I'll dig into
fusions in a second here don't worry
about that um but what what I've
essentially done with each of these is
I've laid them out into testing so
before I go into actually like uh
printing out what the results are and
and how well these work um and what the
differences are it's important to cover
what they actually do what is the
difference between these so kubalas
itself is just the super high it's it's
it's essentially the easiest one to to
use and get working it's just like the
the standard that you typically start
with um and it's going to support uh
your basic you know uh single Precision
so
fp32 um and uh fp16 matrix
multiplication right um kuas LT is a
lightweight extension of kuas that
provides a more flexible API primarily
aimed at improving performance for
specific workloads
um except this is more oriented around
larger matrices so kuas LT is optimized
a little differently and it can be
faster than uh just regular kuas in
cases so when you have when you have
something that's a lightweight ideally
it's going to be lower precision right
you can think of the L as like
lightweight or lower Precision whatever
you want and and essentially what this
means is is it's the same as kublos
except uh when you use lower Precision
like fp16 fp8 and 8 um they're they're
going to run way way faster and that's
what LT has designed for so same idea
just lower Precision bigger matrices um
different kind of
workloads and then you have XT which is
I don't actually recommend this because
it's ridiculously slow
um but you can you can interconnect
multiple gpus and CPUs together to solve
a problem so if you have a massive
Matrix uh you have a giant matrix
multiplication to do you can actually
split this across the CPU and GPU and
they will talk to each other and get
things done um however the the memory
bandwidth bottlenecks um really limit
the
compute because you don't just have this
super fast like uh this High memory
bandwidth on the GPU that you can just
go back and forth like it the memory
bandwidth between the CPU and GPU is
really low that's why it takes so long
to copy things over so you have to worry
about that uh your your solving speed
actually gets slowed down a lot um and
this is one of the the holdbacks with XT
um but you can run multiple gpus it's
designed to be thread safe ideal for
large scale computations from you know
in distributed workloads um large scale
algebra that exceeds GPU memory so if
you have like uh if you have giant
matrices that it's like
16,384 by 16,384 and you multiply that
by itself uh that might not all fit on
like an 8 GB card you know if I do I go
Python and I do 16 384 squared that's uh
what 8 m that's like
268 that's like 268 Million numbers
that's a lot of numbers um and if you
have three of these if you have an a b
and a c all allocated then that's like
700 that's like 800 Million numbers and
then if you you know kick this up to
like uh fp32 you multiply by the number
of um you multiply by four that's the
that's the size of the that's the size
of a float so four four bytes and you
get ridiculous numbers like 3.2 GB of
space so if you have a 2 GB card or it's
like an embedded system it's not going
to fit all that um or if you were to
bump this up to like say
100,000 that that's not going to fit
right like these type of numbers are so
massive that you just need to use
external CPU dram in order to actually
store them right um so you can there's
obviously other ways of optimizing that
but XT allows you to do this um so I did
a run of these um where the size was 16
384 and this all actually fit on my card
because um you
know I have uh 8 GB of gpv RAM which is
low but high in some cases
um kublos versus kublos XT so I did five
runs each it's about 0.59 seconds on
average and then this took about 3.5
seconds on average so the results ended
up matching so it was they were like
pretty much identical uh and then yeah
it's it's it's just like insane how much
of a speed up that gets when you just
stick with using the GPU right and so
that's like one of the examples why you
want to be careful when you use things
like kuas XT um kuas DX is we're not
going to be doing that we're not going
to be using that in this course um but
you can look more into it here with this
documentation um now cutless is
something I'll you know I'll cover in
the in the extra section A little bit
more but um
kublos and its variance run on the
host whatever comes with kublos DX isn't
well super documented or optimized um
and when we're trying to do things like
matrix multiplication in a Transformer
we may not want to rely on something
where the where the operations are
scheduled from the host when it when we
want to call like a Koss operation the
CPU tells it to do that right whereas on
GPU it's just like a kernel that's
launched and all the operations are are
done so they're a little bit different
in that regard
um when we do like matrix multiplication
along with like a r activation and then
another matrix multiplication and then
another value and then like a
convolutional layer it's like you you
typically don't have that in a single
operation you fuse those together and
that's this idea of fusion which we
talked about
before um and when when you when you
have something like cutless which is a
template library that is able to use
things together um you know you can uh
you can get a lot higher performance
so for example um like flash attention
it doesn't actually use cutless but it's
an example of what fused Cuda kernels
look like so flash attention was a paper
that came out you know I think two three
years ago something if we just pull this
up it's uh you know it's essentially for
the attention mechanism in Transformers
and it has a whole thing and the idea is
um you have this this this this
attention layer in the GPT it's like
matal drop out soft Max mask and another
mmal and if you feed these together with
custom handwritten highly optimized
kernels you can make this really really
fast and you can speed this up by like 5
to 10x on certain hardware and that's
the idea of fusion so cutless will allow
you to develop you know faster matrix
multiplication algorithms um and then
you would take something like fusion and
you would combine what you've maybe
written in cutless and you would you
would just combine everything so that
you don't have to rely on whatever
Nvidia provides and you can just do your
own thing right that's that's kind of
the reason why we do things like fusion
and uh and and we use cutless so
template uh template linear algebra sub
routines um but don't worry too much
about cutless we're not going to go over
cut list in this course uh there's a lot
to cover there uh but anyways that's
like the whole idea of that's the whole
idea of
kuas now we dig into these I'm going to
sort of go through this as best I can to
illustrate what's happening so we need
to import this uh kublos V2 right so
this is this is a new thing we're going
to add we're going to add F
fp16 uh inclusions and then just some
Matrix sizes right as macros then we're
going to include these these macers that
check for errors so we wrap those around
like for example here when we when we do
a Cuda Malik it's it's running on Cuda
so we have to make sure that doesn't
return an error uh we just do this
consistently for everything to make sure
that nothing uh just breaks everything
goes according to plan right um and so
in this example
um I'm actually going to go back to a
section there was a there was a point I
missed
um as we saw in the script I make these
arrays
and notice how these are small right
there's a few th there there's a few
other things like this that you want to
watch out for when you're comparing
things because what we're doing here is
we're essentially comparing the speeds
and uh how similar things are together
we want to we want to compare like the
fp32 with the fp16 see how they perform
make sure they match up in the end um
and so there's a lot of things you have
to watch out for so doing warm-up runs
is good because uh Cuda might encour
some additional overhead when you do
like the first few runs so you want to
get those done with um and then continue
with the Benchmark runs so make sure
that the overhead like just gets like
removed you want it to like just sort
that out on its own for like a few runs
and then you do like a 100 Benchmark
runs and you take the average time of
those and that's way you get an accurate
measurement of how long it takes to
execute a function or a kernel right um
without doing any marup runs you might
see like the first thing take like 50
milliseconds and then the next one take
2 milliseconds and it's like whoa what
happened there well that was the
overhead that you needed that that kuo
actually took over and required so
that's why you do the the warm-up
runs um so warm-up and Benchmark runs
you want to verify all of your results
so uh in in here where was
it maybe we didn't maybe we didn't
compare results in here but we do
somewhere else um
you want to verify everything so that it
all matches up and then the last one is
when you're testing things from scratch
instead of like randomly initializing
massive matrices instead of having like
thousand by thousand and just like
random distribution you want to populate
it with values that you can actually
calculate on your own like something
that you could take to your whiteboard
or do it in your head right uh so when
you have something that's laid out like
this you can go ahead and write out okay
well why did it not work right then it's
more more easy to break down the problem
and understand what went wrong there as
opposed to taking apart a
non-reproducible 1,00 by 1000 Matrix you
just can't do that um but anyways going
back to the point here did we initialize
some matrices so a 3x4 and then a 4X two
so they should have 12
elements right we scroll back up this
goes up to 12 and then this goes up to
eight that's a 2x4
we initialize uh these on the CPU so C
on the CPU the single Precision CU loss
output on the
CPU and then uh the the CQ loss output
uh for the for the half
Precision uh and then we do a CPU mapal
just to just to test the results just to
populate um because again the CPU might
be the easiest one to actually write out
for us if we're transferring this from
python our numpy we just write out the
CPU everything will be super easy to uh
compare back to it um so we just we just
do that first we have this kublos handle
thing which I'm going to go in into in a
second here um how like all of these are
how these how all of these work
together but you have this kublos handle
um which just gives like a kublos
context on like what you're doing you
just have to initialize this for safety
we create that with a separate function
um we do all of our our malx and then we
have this this new function here which
you haven't seen before this is called
This is called sjem so single Precision
General General with the GE matrix
multiplication and inside of here if I
control click on this in vs code we can
see where this come from we can see
where this comes from and I can right
click on this and see where the root of
this actually is
right so we look at in order what all
these are so we have the the handle the
operation these operations I'm actually
going to pull these up in a second so
this makes more sense we have the shape
so M and K the alpha term which will
make sense in a second we have a the
leading dimension of a so in this case
it'll it it would be M
um B the leading dimension of B which in
this case would be n because it's an MN
time n by K and so the first one going
to have leading M and then the second
one's going to have leading uh or sorry
leading K I mean leading k um B is going
to have a leading K the leading
Dimension is going to be a k and then we
have this beta and a c which we uh
element wise multiply by and then
leading dimension of C so there's a lot
of things you have to add to this and it
gets it gets quite bloated fast um so I
guess to just sort of illustrate what
all of those mean there's a lot to
unpack here if we scroll down to
um
sjem
sjem kuas sjem awesome so this is a
super important part um this is exactly
what we just
saw and look at this so this is this is
what the Matrix Matrix multiplication
looks like so we have a c and we do
alpha times an OP whatever operation
which is going to be like maybe a
transpose on a um Matrix multiply that
with some operation on B which might be
a transpose and then plus uh the beta
term which beta is a
um beta is just going to be a constant
float number so like in this case you
might want to have a as 1.0 and B as 0.0
just so that you're only doing um a * b
equals c right um but it does gener it
does provide this this abstraction for
you so that you can do more with it if
you want to like add something on later
like maybe a like maybe a bias right
um and then we have all these other
operations so kublos op n kublos op T
and kublos op C so
um we want to we want to worry about the
n and the T here so the n is
like no
operations the t is a
transpose
um and then you have this column major
format so column major throws a lot of
this off so to illustrate this
difference of column versus row major as
we saw in uh as we saw here so matrices
are stored in column major format with
these um with these Dimensions m m by K
and then K byn and c m byn um column
Major versus row major is very important
so it's actually a little harder because
it's column major but we'll make do
anyways column major
Matrix we'll just have
a well actually we make it row major
first that's a good
idea R major a equals
uh and then call
major
a and then the memory layout
so notice the difference here so we have
a we have a
uh a 2x4 Matrix right it goes 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 then here we have 1 5 2 6 3 7 4 8
right so the whole idea here is we
essentially transposed it
we the way this row goes from left to
right it is now going from top to
bottom and now we have to deal with this
so if we have something that's like I
mean typically when you're going to feed
a matrix into a matrix multiplication
you expect it to be in row major and
kublos kublos sjem expects it to be in
column major so there's a way to get
around this and notice how this not by
the way notice how this is laid out in
memory this is like a very simple way of
looking at it and then this is like okay
that's I guess so but a little
interesting because of you know it's
just like 1526 1526 and that order but
uh there's an interesting article I
found on how to uh how to deal with this
so this is why you see our dimensions
are a little messed up um but on this
pay attention to your shaping from stack
Overflow I found an answer to this and
how to make it actually work to your
favor
so where is
it this guy pretty much said
um kuas interprets matrices as column
ordered so when you execute this you are
correctly transposing uh cuz you're
doing an opt which is going to transpose
a and then an opt is going to transpose
uh B you're correctly transposing each
input um but KU stumps will result in
column major order so you want it to
come back in row major order so that you
can use it for something else so what
you end up having to do to avoid this
whole column major mess is Trick KU into
Computing differently um and so the way
that you the way that you call this is
you say handle op n OPN and you go n MK
instead of
mkn uh and then you go um Alpha and then
your your B Matrix instead of a um
because normally you would do a here but
instead you do
B um and then you do you're leading a
dimension so remember n n is the leading
a dimension now and then you have um
then you have your a and the leading
dimension for that is going to be um
it's going to be K I know it's confusing
but just bear with me and then you have
the beta which is just like that that
number you're going to multiply C by and
then the leading dimension for C is
going to be n so there's a lot there's a
lot of different there's a lot of weird
changes there but essentially that's
going to that's going to avoid the
column major issue so when we do this in
DS code you can see that I call uh Kos
sjem with that same idea so n n and then
go n MK When we put our when we put
device B Matrix we put n device a matrix
K beta device C Matrix then n again so
just exactly like copy and paste from
that um and this
works
so this this this concept applies to H
gem as well which is what we have below
so I've done a single precision and a
half precision as well um and there's
like a little casting operation that you
do here it's like a flow to half
function which um we we initialize these
as as half Precision matrices and then
we we do a float to have conversion and
store the result in those based on our
index
um camm
copy High Precision data to the device
so the host right this is a host sorry a
half
um and then we just copy back we we do
the hgem which is the half Precision uh
version of this and then we copy back
um and then we we can just print out the
results to make sure everything matches
up so when I go
nbcc and we have to add this little L
like link this is for link and then we
put kublos at the end of it that's what
that means cuz cuos doesn't come just
right out of the B you have to actually
manually link it because it has to has
to do that part separately we just go
ahead and run this we can see our
matrices so when we go up this is uh row
major right 1 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
11 12 and same one same idea with this
one it's you know it's a 4X two so it's
going to be four high and then two two
wide
um so the two the two uh width is one
two and then 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 right
everything is lined up as we want it to
um and when we do a a row major matrix
multiplication on the CPU we end up with
what we're supposed to get so these
inner Dimensions cancel out and we end
up with the three and two like we were
we were practicing before right and we
end up with the three and two here these
results these are these are our
verification results 50 60 114 140 Etc
we do the kuas sjem result we get the
same shape um same
numbers and then the HD result after we
cast back to single
Precision 3x two boom boom boom boom
boom boom right so that is just a very
uh clear concise example on how on on
like the differences between kublos sjem
and H gem there all all the differences
just half single versus half precision
and the key point of uh changing how you
uh set this up this is the most
important part of this entire script is
just what it what it is what it does and
then everything in between uh that we
need to pay attention to in order to
keep everything in row
majure so now we move on to kuas LT
so if we just pop over to um right here
Kos LT
so kuas LT is the lightweight version
and it's designed to hold much bigger
matrices and so I figured little
something to do with that out the hard
way and I was playing around um you
cannot have matricies without multiples
of four so if you have like a 3x4 um
like three is not a multiple of four or
a 2x4 both of them aren't multiples of
four uh those that does not work that
will not that will not return
successfully but if you do have like a
4X 4 or 4X 8 or like a 12 by 16 or
something like that'll work fine so if
we like right click on this just like I
found this uh in the kublos
documentation
um where did where did it
go let's search this
up oh maybe I should copy this part um
but yeah so if you plug if you plug that
string into here you'll see um in the
kuas LT matmo um it's going to be scroll
down data ordering so four by a line
leading dimens leading Dimensions must
be multiples of four um Dimensions M
andk must be multiples of four right so
it's just universally a good idea when
you're working with big majores don't do
like 4,091 do 496 it's just kind of like
makes logical sense to do that so uh
that's that's all I kind of I wanted to
say for that is to watch out there um
but let's go ahead and just dive into
like what the actual LT MCO is doing so
we have this new include header or or um
this new include that we have to do so
Koss lt. and then we have the regular
macros for checking Cuda and checking uh
kuas for errors we have the CPU imple
implementation to compare against um we
have the print Matrix so that's just
going to like conveniently print things
for us that we can look at them and make
sure everything lines up
um and then notice how I make the sizes
four four and four right so nothing less
than that just Square Matrix Square
matrices um I do also make sure to make
these uh these like different elements
so if these were a clone this was like
one 1 to 16 and then 1 to 16 like you
might not get the results you want so
you want to make them a little bit
unique so that you don't run into like
any weird cases where you think you have
the right answer but you don't so I
changed this three right here to a four
so it's four and then four and then
instead of 13 to 16 I did 17 to 20 um
just to mix it up a
bit now the actual magic I mean we have
a lot of stuff happening here where we
um where we essentially where we
essentially uh make like a like a fp32
matrix we cam malic and we we populate
those and we also have a half so this is
just the half of a float so it's fp16 is
what this is um and then we just
populate those with
uh we we we we populate these where are
we populating it I think
that's oh no we already populated them
up here I'm being
silly but we go down after we've like
CMM copied everything this is all on the
device now um we have this kublos LT
handle so this is this just the handle
that we need to create the context we go
and create that um and then we have this
new term called a kuas LT Matrix layout
type um so this is just there's a few
types we need to ensure that this goes
properly and this is one of them so
essentially just the shapes um and the
data type that we're going to use so
Cuda data type
uh and then this this kind of follows
the same idea as the whole column major
thing so if we I don't know where
exactly this was in the box but if we go
to uh
kuas what was it it was The Matrix kuas
LT Matrix layout create if we just enter
this
in we see it's down here and if we take
a look at the rows and columns number
and rows and Columns of the Matrix and
then leading Dimension leading dimension
of the Matrix in column major layout so
this is the same idea um and I'm going
to show you how to like get through that
it's it's a little bit EAS easier
intuitively to sort of see how that how
that pans out but yes uh we do need to
abide by that column major rule there so
popping back here um for for fp32 we
just use real um and then 32f so if we
actually look at this specific type like
where does this come from the Cuda data
type you can actually see a list of
these so we have anywhere from like um
like real num so R is real C is complex
and then this number is the Precision so
16 is half and then 32 is single and
then 64 is full and then you have like
the other you know smaller types that
you can use uh and then like just normal
f is uh essentially what what that
difference is is like normal fp16 will
have a like it'll have a sign bit that's
either positive or negative and then
it'll have a certain number of exponent
bits so how how big is like the integer
half like before before the decimal
place and then the mantisa bits which is
uh how precise can it be in the decimal
places right so fp16 is going to be more
precise in decimals and then bf16 or
brain float 16 the reason it's called
brain flow is because it came from
Google brain um that that is going to
have less mantisa and more
exponent exponent bits so that's how
that kind of naming scheme goes uh but
all we need to worry about in this case
is the um the real 32bit floating point
and then the uh real 16bit floating
point Point
um so we can see that we use those here
uh just for the 32-bit we use that and
then when we're ordering this we want to
do um so the first Matrix a is going to
be of shape n m m by K so we want to
flip that so it's going to be K by m and
then because we've flipped it uh we need
to put the leading Dimension here right
so uh leading Dimension is at the end um
and that's that's that so
Matrix B same idea we have it's normally
K byn so we flip that and then put the
put the new n as the leading Dimension
and then same idea here as well um then
we go to the fp6 which literally just
uses real but we replace the 32 with 16
and we do the same exact thing with
shapes um and then we go down to the uh
the map description type which we just
have to create we just have to create
that and essentially we we pass in this
this typ type that we Define the memory
address to that the compute type that
we're doing and then the data type so we
look at this it's going to be the map M
description with the kublos LT map M
description type like we had here and
then the kublos compute type which I'll
show you in a second here and then the
data type which we were doing before
which is just going to be um fp32 so we
go to this compute
type we actually see there's a few of
these uh you just do like control click
to look at those um but there's a few
here so we have like kuas compute um 16
F which is which is what we're going to
want for the the next one but we're
using this one right now um you can do
like fast you can do like fast so it'll
it'll like change I can't remember
exactly how it changes those inside but
it's something in the realm of like
accumulating and this and that um but
yeah so these can be uh you it kind of
just depends on like what you're doing
if you're sticking with brain float then
you can you could pick that type you
could do like Fast um up to you but um
yeah that's that's the whole idea there
so if we pop back to this one you notice
we're just using the compute 16 float
and then the the data type of 16 uh
16bit float as well um and then we're
going to we're going to set an attribute
and the parts of this attribute that
we're going to need are the M
description type which we finded earlier
um we're going to need a uh description
attribute which we uh which is if you
can literally go to these um and these
are these are essentially just the um I
can't remember exactly what this is but
it's probably like some transpose like
transpose a and then transpose b or
whatever that is um that that's that's
what I'd assume this is I haven't looked
into this in depth but um and then this
one is just going to be the kuas
operation so yeah so essentially just
like transposing or not and then the the
size of uh this CU loss operation type
so uh that's just like this essentially
so we're taking this this transpose
operations um and that we're just
setting what that that op is so when it
does like op and then in Brackets a like
that's what this is
um and then we go ahead and do the kuas
LTM which uh itself you know takes in a
handle um the map uh M description
type um an alpha a matrix layout B
Matrix layout for B beta C uh C Matrix
layout uh D and and Etc right
um You can pretty much just directly
paste these like there's a lot of these
that we don't actually need that we can
just set to null and aren't really
required so don't worry too much about
that you just kind of want things to be
in the right order and so similar to how
we did for regular kuas you're going to
do the B Matrix first and then uh and
then you're going to do the a matrix
after
right so that's that's kind of how that
goes then we just do the check KU blast
to make sure everything goes properly um
and then and then there's a there's an
important part that I kind of like
messed up here and it was a little silly
but I was trying to do this uh this uh
16 bit floating Point kuas LT ml with uh
with the regular Alpha types so um you
know notice how this is like this that
this is void it doesn't specifically say
float so I looked I looked at that and I
was like hm maybe maybe like we
shouldn't use a 32-bit number and
multiply that by a 16bit floating Point
number maybe that that's not how it goes
so I was like okay um I and at the time
I was getting a bunch of zero output so
I figured this might be a good fix and
it ended up working so uh you pretty
much just have to uh typ cast this so
float to half um and then you just set
you know your Alpha is going to be one
your beta is going to be zero you just
want to do a map that that's all you
care about so that's how you're going to
set them and then just have Alpha half
and beta half and just set these
accordingly um and everything will work
according to plan
so that's how it goes um once we're once
we're done those we copy the uh results
back to host uh we're not doing any any
like benchmark here we don't worry about
that we just want to make sure we have
the correct results um for both the kuas
LT uh single and the half Precision um
and so we just we essentially copy these
back we do a CPU ml to uh you know
essentially get a ver a verification uh
output so that we can compare it to
um and then we we do the actual
comparison itself so we use a standard
Library absolute value we go this minus
that it's going to get give us some
value that's like um you know hopefully
less than 1 * 10
^5 um and if that's false or or sorry if
if this is bigger than that number if if
it's bigger than what it tolers
tolerates then um they it says they
don't match and we end up returning uh
they they don't match um so if I go
ahead and
actually
uh run this we have to do link Coss and
Link C LT cuz remember at the top here
we did kuas lt. so we have to include
that and then if we just uh run this we
can see that uh we get a matrix a so row
major Matrix B um four four and then 17
through 20 as we as we wanted and then
we get a c output so 106 664 106 664 106
664 for all of these different
precisions and we can see that these
match with intolerance awesome so that's
just like comparing them and making sure
that they work the way we want them to
so we can like carry that and Port it to
something else
but then for actually comparing it for
measuring performance we have a
different script here so I essentially
did the same thing um don't like worry
about a bunch of what's happening in
here this is this is just a uh this is
just a uh a benchmarking script that I
wrote for for comparing very large
matrices so we do a 496 by 1024 Times
a24 by 496 so the inner Dimensions
cancel out the the K is cancel out and
then we end up with a 496 by 496 Matrix
um and so I pretty much do a naive
Matrix multiply because these are very
big the CPU will take forever to do
these so I I wrote a naive Matrix
multiply that still gives you know a
verifiably true answer in row major
order and then you know we have our our
our normal distribution uh random number
generator here that you know ensures
everything is is kind of just goes as we
want some essentially like when you do
torch. randn it's going to just do that
um it's going to make it nor like Rand n
is for normally uh randomly normally
distributed um that's that's what this
is doing and then verify results same
idea does it does the relative error
match with intolerance
um we do a timing so with it with our uh
with our our previous streams so we
don't actually like put the stream in
but we just want to uh record the time
and do this elapse time thing uh and
then just return that to measure it um
on the actual device itself uh and then
we Benchmark and we just have a bunch of
other stuff filled in in between here
the same as what you saw in the in the
previous script um and then we we just
end up printing out the average time
afterwards
so um it'll also return the max error we
get as well consider there is some error
with fp16 so we should know about that
too um but if I I just print this out
here two
compare we print this out notice
so okay so KU loss results match the
naive kernel with intolerance results
match results match and results match
awesome so everything is lined up um I
did give it some additional tolerance
here just because of some of the error
but here uh we notice that this error is
not super significant um it it's not
this is the maximum error so most of it
is going to be very insignificant
compared to this this is just like a
side edge case which might pop up a few
times uh very like not often at all so
when we actually look at the times we
can see normal CU loss gives us fp32
average time of 2.5 milliseconds uh kuas
LT gives us an an average of 2 point
about 2.8 milliseconds which isn't
amazing uh and then kuas LT FP 16 gives
us 63 milliseconds and then LT gives us
um about four
uh 46 milliseconds which is really fast
compared to this naive kernel that we've
written before so this took 28
milliseconds to right this is about the
time that it takes me to Ping the Google
servers about 28 Mill seconds for it to
run the complete naive kernel and the LT
took Point about5 milliseconds that is
insanely fast um like look at the if you
just look back at at at how we were we
were doing a matrix multiplication of
like taking the column and do producting
it with a row like you have a it's like
size uh
1,24 and it does that and it it does for
every single combination it's it and it
does all of that in uh half a
millisecond so that's that's about 5
10,000 of a second uh but yeah anyways
that's that is a kublos LT at this point
you might be a little upset or
frustrated about why I'm just uh showing
you code and then reviewing it and not
like writing it from scratch like
starting from the very top like let's
define these and then write this and
then write this the point is like all of
this it is a lot there's a lot of lines
I'm not going to type this all manually
the course is uh long enough already as
it is I'm not going to make it 10 times
longer by writing everything uh by hand
um but yeah you you you kind of get the
point you I identify the main the main
uh material that you need to learn the
most important stuff and I highlight it
um but I don't need to highlight
everything like writing check KU loss is
just redundant writing
um I don't know like writing the writing
this stuff it's just redundant like you
already know what that is um so that's
that's kind of why I'm sticking away
from that side and just trying to kind
of trying to make like Fast progress
here um we might write out some things
later on just just to kind of help you
understand it when it gets more
intuitive and and you're actually like
building stuff but right now uh we don't
this is not very conceptually hard so
we're just kind of flying through it but
this next part is on kublos XT so it's
essentially the same thing as what we've
just done except it's a bit different we
still do the handle um we still create
it we do this new thing called device
select which remember when I talked
about um how you can have multiple gpus
and and do a computation across multiple
gpus in the host that's what this is so
we we essentially just do this little
hack um and we just device select
whatever the main GPU device is um and
that's that's how we do things across so
this is this is just a little hack when
you have one one GPU so that you do
this um and then we do this XTS gem
which is the same exact thing as we've
been doing before except you have these
things that are on the host and then
they're managed by um this this sjem
function so you don't have to actually
move anything to device you just you
don't even I I don't have a single camm
copy in here
um you just pass in your matrices on the
host and it'll manage all of that memory
back and forth but at some performance
cost so you'll see that in a second when
I compile this um
we don't actually need to link LT but
that's
fine um and so you can see maximum
difference between CPU and GPU results
right um and then if we go to
say and then we just link KU
Bloss we'll give that a second here I
did I did the exact same thing as as our
Koss LT but for XT instead and made very
big matrices so 16 384 you notice the
kuo Run does uh but you know like I like
I think I highlighted this before but 0.
59 seconds or 6 seconds on average and
then the kuas LT is going to be way
longer than that so uh we'll we'll just
give this a second here to finish um but
yeah you you you get my point it takes a
while you don't want to run this maybe
you don't want to run this in
production um so we get the average time
everything matches with in toolerance
and we're good um but yeah that's that's
kublos XT for you um go and delete
these I hope you enjoy that section on
kuas or Cuda basic linear algebra
subprograms uh that was that was quite a
bit hey uh we got a second part on CNN
so when you do when you do um for
example like P install torch like
this uh and you see like uh where is it
kublos qnn right that's this is where
this is where it's kind of coming from
right and you have all the other things
like q fft and C random number
generators and CP solver and CP sparse
and Collective Communications across
multiple nodes profilers Triton which
we'll go into later right I mean this is
this is why I'm covering this stuff so
that you can uh so you can kind of work
with it and you understand how Pi torch
Works under the Hood right that's one of
the main reasons I'm putting this out so
when you go into CNN um there's there's
actually a lot more to unpack here as
compared to kuas but it's not
conceptually hard um some of it is a
little bit intuitive but not really um
so CNN is not entirely for matrix
multiplication it does matrix
multiplication in some operations to
really speed things up uh but it's not a
performance bottleneck you don't
actually explicitly do matrix
multiplication in CNN that's not a thing
that's what kblast handles right um so
in CNN you're going to deal with things
like
convolutions um pooling layers soft Max
um Dropout right batch
normalization uh tensor Transformations
like reshaping and concatenation layer
Norm all this right so all these other
deep learning operations other than
matrix multiplication is what qnn is
going to cover a lot of um a lot of the
a lot of the common most Comm L used
ones um so this is this is kind of why
I'm bringing you to the docs here is
because this there's this is a super
direct interface with everything um so
they actually have their own thing Doc
Nvidia deeplearning CNN and you go there
and it brings you to this page so
there's multiple things here we have
like a getting started or installation
guide which we don't care about and then
the other ones the important ones which
is backend API and developer guide so
we're going to be looking at these two
today and doing some examples of C DNN
operations and comparing them so if we
go to like backend API overview um we
can see it's like
um Cuda so it supports the Cuda streams
that we were talking about before um it
has multiple things that it's kind of
like linked to so there's like I I don't
I wouldn't pay attention to that
entirely but um you have these you have
essentially have these three parts so
you have qnn graph qnn Ops qnn CNN and
adver serial so graph is going to it
it's not uh it's not it doesn't support
like graph operations where you're like
dealing with graphs it's more so how do
you combine operations together in the
form of a graph so when you're doing
like a like a convolution layer and then
you're adding a bias and then you're
doing a Max pool after it like that
that's going to look like a graph right
you're going to have these nodes
essentially where it's like a node is an
operation and an edge is a a tensor
right or a matrix and so it' be like
convolution 2D and then there's going to
be an edge which is the which is the
data flowing from from the output of
here to the input of the next node and
that next node might be like the bias
that it adds right uh and then and then
it's going to flow out of the bias into
uh like a Max pool layer or average pool
layer and then it's going to go from
there and so instead of doing these
separately where you do a separate
function call for uh convolution bias so
you do like a manual bias kernel and
then a manual Max pool kernel you just
fuse these all into one and you keep
track of all of your all of your uh data
in between and it does that for you so q
that that's what the whole qnn graph
thing is um it supports you know both
forward and backward path so when you're
going through calculating the prediction
predictions uh and when you're uh
modifying all the gradients and and back
propagating through it supports both of
those right so it's designed for it's
designed for kind of
uh just putting something in place
instead of having to write like all the
kernels from scratch is just kind of
makes your life easier that way um so
there are multiple things within a CNN
graph so we have these pre-compiled
engines runtime compiled engines um I
have this pulled up on my second monitor
here which I'll probably just bring over
um where did it
go yes so the pre-compiled single
operation engines I'm going to make this
more readable the pre-compiled single
operation engines pre-compiled and
optimized for a single specific
operation like a convolution because
they're pre-compiled they offer very
efficient execution and are inflexible
in terms of operations they can perform
right they're comp compiled down to
machine code they only do one specific
function on something but it goes very
fast because of all the optimizations in
b area that it has right um so like for
example a major multiplication engine
that is pre-compiled and optimized
specifically for that operation right
like similar to convolutions um and then
there's generic runtime Fusion
engines designed to dynamically fuse
mult multiple operations at runtime so
offer more flexibility compared to
pre-compiled because they're generic and
they can adapt right uh these are things
that would that would happen during the
compilation um not might not be as as
high performance optimized but they're
they are generic and they can and they
can they act as like a generic fuser of
operations together so you will get
those performance benefits but they're
not going to be as high so you still get
them but they're not going to be um
they're not going to be as high as
something customly written for that
algorithm then you have a specialized
runtime Fusion engine similar to generic
runtime Fusion engines uh but they're
typically uh specifically optimized for
certain patterns or combinations of
operations right so offering runtime
flexibility and leveraging optimizations
for particular use cases or operation
sequences and then for example an engine
optimized for fusing convolution layers
followed by activation functions in
neural networks like similar how similar
to how I was talking about before you
have like convolution and then a bias
and then uh convolution bias and then a
Max pull layer uh similar similar to
that right um It'll recognize your code
architecture uh and it'll find the fuse
patterns where you would get a speed up
so um it's it's going to just it's going
to be um it's going to be smart right
it's going to try to be smart when it's
when it's compil this down and seeing
where you could actually get a speed up
from
um and then you have the specialized
pre-compiled so pre-compiled for
specific
sequences they offer the same high
performance as pre-compiled single
operations so these ones that were
really fast uh but can handle sequences
of operations rather than just single
ones so these are
actually these are actually amazing if
you are trying to do a lot of layers
like if you have a whole like say a
Transformer Block in a neural network uh
and you want to do that entire attention
block this is an example of what that
would be so you have a lot of different
operations that you're doing in there
but if you just have this wrapper that
says multi-ad attention you call that uh
you get everything you put everything in
that you need and you get everything out
that's useful and then you can continue
on and it's going to be highly optimized
pre-compiled into binary specifically
for that right so this is kind of how
qnn is structured and this is these are
the things you're going to you know want
to pay attention to when you're trying
to optimize when you're looking out for
how you can take advantage of underlying
qnn features
um so uh you know there's an example of
like runtime Fusion right here um and
then if we go back to the graph API if
we go back I know it's bright you'll be
fine um
we pop over to this this graph API I
think that's where it was yeah graph API
with operation Fusion so
um convolution
forward pointwise bias pointwise value
right um that's that's kind of the whole
idea and if you wanted to fuse these
together you would do like uh you'd have
like essentially some organization you
have three tensors that you input um and
and that would be like their variable
names uh and then like these two would
go through here like your um like your X
and then your your W your weight kernel
the convolution filter itself is your W
and that would output something with
this arrow and then this one this bias
would come in um and it would
essentially add to the output of that
convolution and then you would do a
pointwise rue which is it's just
a it literally just goes one by one
through through each element um
and then you get your output so that
that's the whole idea of a graph is like
you have these which is your data flow
the edges is your is your actual data
and where it's flowing to and then the
points the nodes themselves are the
operations so um continuing to go
through this um you know inputs
convolution backward so Alpha Beta Dy uh
W and DX um and then you would end up
getting
um yeah you you you kind of get the
point you put whatever in is required
for an operation and you get whatever
out is is useful right um especially
important you pay attention to that in
the backward pass of things because
there's going to be more data you'll
have to take care of
um but yeah these these kind of work the
same way all around um normalization you
have like your mean Epsilon and variance
um then your
scale continuing to go forward um same
ideas generic runtime Fusion engines you
can kind of just scroll through this and
get the idea about how everything is
architected
um there's there's quite a bit here I
don't expect that you'll read all of
this um
but yeah that's that's pretty much how
the whole uh Fusion engine thing works I
know it's a kind of a a silly term but
it it is you're effectively fusing
operations together and you could say
that acts as like an engine right so if
we go back to this VSS code here that
I've opened the read me file you can
actually find these in here so just you
know a bunch of um bunch of stuff but
like the graph API very important um
Matt Mo um convolution forward backward
backward data
pointwise
um yeah just like pretty much some of
the images copy and pasted and then this
one was this one was actually
support uh that this one is support for
the different Compu capabilities right
so if you have like for example if if I
did um can't remember what it was it was
like device query remember that when we
printed out the computer capability and
mine was 8 uh
8.6 so um I would actually not get the
uh convolution backward filter fusions I
would not get this because it's only
supported on 9.0 and up right so pay
attention to things like that when
you're trying to fuse things together
for like research production purposes
you want to pay attention to what is
supported on your Ware or whatever
Hardware you're working on um so that
you don't like try to do something and
have it not work and waste time so it's
good to just like double check with this
stuff and see this is all in the CNN
docs
but there's still a few more sections we
have to cover so I'm going to dig into
those um we have the Ops API which I'll
dig into next is is very simple um if we
just go
to here go to Ops um essentially you
have these these same opaque stru types
as you did with kuas um except they do
different operations so you can do like
um like you can like create tensors
pooling um filter Dropout loss
activation all of this so the actual
functions here might be hard to read
it's very bright
um but activation backward activation
forward you just have like a massive
list of stuff I'm not going to go
through these one by one um but but you
get the point these are all the
operations that are supported with kunan
to CNN and we're going to test we're
going to test some of them
out so you know you get a bunch of like
uh descriptions about each what if each
of these do so it you know in case
you're wondering about something or
you're not getting an output as you'd
expect um you would generally refer to
these doc so you could whatever type
you're working with or whatever function
you're trying to call like let's say
you're you know working with this or
maybe you're doing let's see maybe
something simple like
uh like U activate backward right so you
have this you copy it f and you you can
find these all across so you have the
qnn activation backward and it has all
the different types in here that you
would use um and then you have the this
one this original one that we
highlighted before so that's how you
navigate these you just search for
whatever is wrong and then kind of just
like look at that and see any of the any
of the notes on it and see if you miss
something um that's that's kind of how
uh you're supposed to approach these um
and then going into uh CNN API so this
is where stuff might get a little bit
interesting um it's not like any graph
Fusion stuff you're doing it's just like
raw algorithms um so you'll have um you
know convolution backward bias like all
just all the different convolution stuff
um there is I mean there there is fused
Ops um so that's where like some of this
would come in but um yeah this is this
is where all the convolution stuff is
going to be for like image processing
and you name it right so we're going to
actually use convolutions in a second
here so I'm going to I'm going to save
this but it's you you approach it the
similar way as you would with with Ops
operations and then you have the uh
adversarial
API which is um same idea but you know
other functions so like you know rnn's
um C uh CTC loss multi-head
attention uh we'll do yeah see
multi-head attention weight so if I go
um multi head attention multi-ad
attention forward awesome how do we use
this right there's there's multi head
attention forward there's 22 of these in
here 21
now so you kind of get the point we can
scroll through
these there's a lot
jeez um so this is how you would do a a
multi-head attention block forward and
the forward pass there's a lot of stuff
in here but that's that that that that's
kind of how this goes right um just the
adversarial like extra the other section
miscellaneous whatever you want to call
it um but now we can actually go into
some of the uh
comparisons to understand uh how to
actually use CNN in a Cuda script now we
can actually go into some of the code
and examples behind CNN and how it works
under the hood well not not how it works
under the hood but how we can use things
like P torch under the hood to make
operations really fast so in this
example um you know we we do the Cuda
runtime and the cnn. H I'm just going to
do the 10 function for example um and in
case you haven't seen the 10 function
yet um
we go to Google
Images uh it literally just looks like
like this 10 H
um or like this maybe this is a better
one it's like between -1 and one it's
just a little activation function that
you do it's like a nice smooth S curve
and uh yeah so that's that's all we're
really doing here we don't actually need
to like do the type in the formula it's
already done for us um I've actually
written out the 10h kernel here and
operation is literally just 10 HF for P
function on device um so very simple um
we we want to have a tensor with the
shape um what's it called n by n by C by
height by width that's the format we
want to use so it's going to be like n
is batch size channels is uh Channel C
is channels height and then width right
so the whole idea of like channels is if
you have uh like like an image for
example like the image you're video
you're watching me on right now this is
going to have three channels it's going
to have RGB right so this is if uh say
you've you've done some convolutions and
now your now your channel Dimension is
very big so instead of three you've got
like 32 elements per pixel that you have
to keep track of and and do operations
on right so we're making a big tensor
here big tensor um if I actually go into
python new 256 we going to go well four
times cuz four is the number of of bytes
it's going to occupy 4 * 256 * 32 * 2 *
224 uh squared we end up getting this
number and if we divide this number by
uh 1 million it's
about 1.6 gabt that's how big this
tensor is and then we're going to do a
10h on
that so Cuda DN is going to handle this
and we're going to compare that to the
naive kernel um
and yeah so just stepping through this
same Cuda Malik initialized data Cuda M
Copy we're going to create some events
that we can Time stuff on the GPU we're
going to do our our warmup and and
Benchmark runs um we're going to do some
warmup runs for the knif kernel
um we're going to do benchmarks for it
we're going to set up qnn and this is
where we're actually going to learn a
little bit um and then like benchmarks
for CNN of course this is where it m
takes place so we have this qnn handle
type we create
that we have this tensor descriptor type
so you actually need to um it's like the
when you did like a matrix a descriptor
or Matrix B descriptor it's the same
idea but we do that for tensors because
it's you know it's more in the Deep
learning context there's more deep
learning operations in Cuda CP DNN since
it's deep neural network C deep neural
net right um so we have create Tor
descriptor which is is going to just
take the memory address of this and
actually create the tensor descriptor
based on the type um we're going to set
the tensor descriptor so it's going to
be um this type which we which we did
already the tensor format the data type
and then each of those uh NCH HW format
right so we do this we do this format
and you can you can look this up and
there's um it's right here tensor format
so we can do NCH HW we can do NW C or n
nhwc um and Etc right so that's we just
we just pick this one and then this data
float we look at this um we can have
like a bunch of different ones fast
float for fp8 um fp8 so we'd have one
sign bit and then five exponent bits and
then two mantisa bits right so it's
eight total right um and then fp8 you
know more more mantisa bits and then
Boolean we have all these different
types but we want the float there's no
like float 32 here we just want a normal
float no no half no bf16 none of that um
just something basic to to to
use and then we create not only the
tensor descriptor because we have the
tensor itself and then we have the
activation descriptor which is about
what the activation is going to do and
we have a custom type for that um and
you can go here and there's there's a
bunch of different um I think
it's I don't know where exactly this is
but I just like to right click on things
to learn
yeah good
luck uh we create the ACT activation
descriptor with its memory address and
here we have the activation descriptor
type as before we have the CNN or uh we
have the activation type uh mode type so
the activation mode uh is going to be
10h and then the uh propagation type is
just Nan um we're we're not we're not
doing that
um and then the coefficient is going to
be uh zero so there's not going to I
don't know what what is KF I don't know
what that is um but anyways this is just
like the template layout we're having
and I don't expect you to like go
through this and understand every single
character that's happening here this is
just kind of a more template example to
show you like how we're comparing these
how we're running and testing and you
can like take these out and put them
into other pieces of code so don't like
feel bad at all if you don't understand
this it is there there is a lot um but
if we go to like this for example we
have like sigmoid R 10 clip R um swish
all this right so we just want the tan H
function um
now we go to activation forward as we
saw just like a a few minutes ago um we
have the scann handle which we defined
before activation descriptor which we
which we just covered the alpha
parameter the tensor descriptor which we
covered uh up here we have this um
we have this void X so that's just
that's just the input a beta term which
we don't need um and then tensor
descriptor type for y so and the output
itself is just a uh it's it's nothing
it's nothing particularly special it's
just a void so we don't need any like
special types for it it's just like a
raw data like array output essentially
um going to be a bunch of floats right
um so that's that's that and it's going
to be on device that's why we have the D
there um
um we're going to synchronize everything
and then do our benchmarks run
benchmarks runs we're going to find the
average time we're going to verify
against the
CPU like a CPU tan for example it's not
not going to take long since it's like a
like a pointwise operation it's just
going to go one by one through it it's
very it's like linear time um so when we
actually uh when we actually compile
this 10 H to DNN see it knows
we run this you're actually going to be
surprised by something so give this a
second to
run my machine might be lagging a little
bit I'm not sure
but we're going to let that run for a
second here our Matrix sizes are are
quite big remember we have these
so um you know tensor size as we wanted
um the naive crud kernel time notice how
this is actually faster than the CNN
activation time um they're both correct
we just compare the results um you know
pointwise and this is faster why that
really made me angry when I when I saw
this I was like what is the point of
having a having a CNN activation like
what is the point of this um and the
point of that is just to give give
yourself things like Alpha and beta
right so when you have Alpha and beta
these are extra numbers that you have
have to consider in the operation and
when it's so simple when it's as simple
as just a like exponentiation or like a
multiplication um and it's it's like a
very simple like for example Ru takes
almost no time to complete 10h is like a
very simple operation just on a single
number um you just output that to the
same index it's very computationally
simple but when you add in little things
like Alpha and beta I suspect these are
what actually cause the performance
difference it might be mostly these or
some cdnn over head I mean again we
don't even know what this what this is
doing under the hood it's a complete
Black Box opaque struct we don't know
what's happening so it's hard to
actually know why this happens um
there's not very many resources on why
custom kernels might be faster than C
andn I haven't really found any of that
so we're just going to hold the
assumption that uh there's this big
opaque struct Black Box thing that we
don't know um and then you also have
just the alpha and beta as well that
you're you're um timesing
and adding things by right so that's
going to add some extra compute compute
overhead but these are not very big
differences at all right so you have
like 8.52 3 and then 8.6 it's like this
is like nothing this won't actually
matter in production it's like if you if
you take the difference um if you see
how much faster um the naive cter
formula is it's like literally 1.3%
faster which you're not ever going to
notice in a real environment like that
it's just unnoticeable
so it doesn't actually matter that much
if you care like totally just like go go
ahead go and R your own kernels but that
that's that's a general idea it doesn't
really matter that much um for for
convolutions it will matter though um
then going down to this I wrote a a p
torch script to just kind of illustrate
things out manually so like how pytorch
handles um how pytorch handles the
custom tan like when you write it from
scratch on your own um versus when you
just use the built-in the torch the
torch. 10 where did it go yes torch. 10
um so just kind of comparing those side
by side and seeing how they perform
um so if we write these out um o it's
taking some time to do this yeah so
custom t h um that's going to take 21
milliseconds remember how CN beforehand
uh was taking about like point I don't
know what it was like
point it was it was a very small number
um the custom like built in 10 is still
very fast um so if we go back and we
just nbcc compile this and then you know
run and let's just like look at which
what the shapes of our numbers are real
quick
um if I do batch size by say or if I do
256 by 32 by 224 by 224
four Rand n and we wrap these in
Brackets
here we can we can check this one real
quick and see how fast this
runs and then we will compare the python
script to that directly without like
deleting the output so we can't see it
um just so we understand like how much
performance could be gained from say
using uh using like a custom written
Cuda kernel or custom written uh CNN
function so if we go python TCH compare
it's going to take a second oh yeah ran
out to memory awesome
so
um Rand yeah no that doesn't work I bump
this down to like 128 it might work
it's not very fast yeah so like Custom
Custom 10 is super slow and then the
built-in one 4.3 let's say 4.4
milliseconds right um and then we go up
and we can see that you know this is
this is actually
um this is about double that right so if
we do 4 point about 4.4 *
2 8.8 right so we go back up and it's
like this is less than that so if we
write a naive kud kernel like this is
just naive if you were to optimize this
and imp Implement something like Loop
unrolling which we'll go into later and
you optimize this even just something as
simple as an activation function you can
get this surprisingly faster than Pi
torch um and just like write everything
manually you can actually get
considerable speed UPS so uh that's just
to provide some context there um but
yeah activation functions don't worry
about do that too much it's not really
going to affect you um and then we go to
like convolutions right this is this is
an example of where we're actually using
convolutions um so you know we we we
have a lot more things to pay attention
to I'm going to dive into this right now
now we can jump into convolutions a
little bit um I've been hacking around
with some of these and uh let's just
going to show you how these how these
work so we're going to start off with a
visualization first I'm going to bring
over a
convolutions visualized just pop over to
here and um this is just what it looks
like so we can like you have these input
sizes kernel size padding dilation and
stride input size is this I can change
the input image the kernel size the
actual weight itself the the weight term
um the padding so how much black pixels
are put around the input the dilation of
it right
um and then stride as well so I can make
it stride by one each time or stride by
[Music]
two um and and that's that's pretty much
just uh that that you can mess around
with that in your own time um but I've
written two scripts
so one for p torch so the P torch and
this one use the exact same values in
the exact same order um the exact same
parameters here they're all the same and
I'm just doing a side by-side comparison
of them so that we can get desired
output so it's
essentially it's essentially like a like
a 4x4 the input is like a 4x4 image so 1
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 and
then the kernel itself is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 n and it's just going
to right it's going to do that and we
put a padding over it uh so that this is
going to end up flooring to one so Cur
size is three and then divide that uh
floor by two so if we go python go three
two we get one
and that's just going to be our padding
and then torch is going to do that with
this functional Library here um and and
we get the output right so this should
be very self-explanatory very easy we're
just reshaping it and then you know
reshaping it here as well um but when we
look at this part this is actually where
the fun kicks in so we do our cian N.H
at the top I've written a naive Cuda
kernel for this for doing 2D
convolutions takes in an input a kernel
the output the width height in channels
out channels kernel size uh and batch
size so uh don't don't worry about how
this works internally just it just let
it be there as some like template code
that's going to do what we want um it's
modular so um and then we have all the
same settings as we do in our py script
at the top here so
um we Define like how big our inputs
outputs and kernel elements are going to
be we print this out um we do our
classic just malic we have our our
values
organized
um more kud M Copy stuff and then we
create the CNN handle so this is all
very similar to uh what we were doing
with CNN and our t t function um we
created we create an input and output
tensor um filter descriptor for the
kernel itself um
convolution descriptor for the
convolution operation we create all of
these we create the convolution
descriptor with that memory address um
we're doing going to use the 4D
descriptor because it's going to be
shaped batch size by Channel by height
by width um and then if we look at these
so we have the we have the tensor
descriptor the format so how which what
it was like the shape of it and then the
data type which is just a float 32 as we
have here um and then we have the N by C
by h by W right so batch size by
channels by height by width and we do
the same thing for all of these um the
output is going to be out channels
because it's not inch it's going to be
how many out channels do we get in the
end um and then the filter descriptor is
going to have a different it's going to
be organized a different way it's going
to be um out channels by in channels by
height by width so out channels in
channels height uh height by width right
for the for the kernel itself for the
convolution filter you I'm going to use
those interchangeably convolution kernel
and convolution filter same thing um and
then the actual descriptor itself um
this is a 2d descriptor so it's going to
be a 2d
convolution um and we just dump all
these in so the padding H padding W um u
and v and dilations we we're just we're
not even using dilations um convolution
mode so it's going to be cross
correlation and the data type is just
float um so I don't expect you to know
what what all like the convolution laws
are and everything we're just comparing
to P torch and making sure that
everything lines up um and then in terms
of the um in terms of the algorithm
itself um we have a little thing that
searches through stuff here uh I might
change this later this doesn't it's not
very beautiful to look at um but what
you what you can do is actually just
like literally this uh where is it this
algo here when you do the when you give
uh when you give CNN like a workspace
size to do the operation in there's this
CNN convolution forward algo type which
is right here um forward algo type and
there's a bunch of them in here so uh by
default what that's supposed to do is
cycle through them and find which one is
the best but I find that it might be a
little bit better to just cycle through
these one one by one on your own so try
out implicit gem Tri out pre-comp gem
triy out gem tried out direct fft fft
tiling WI noat nonfused count right so
try all these out and see how they work
um which I which I have in this uh
comparison script we're going to do
later on but uh yeah don't don't don't
worry too much about those just you can
kind of just run the script as is um but
we're just trying to find the best
convolution algorithm for our problem at
hand right so when you have a a smaller
kernel and a small image a certain like
maybe an implicit gem might be faster
than say an fft tiling uh because of the
overhead right so you have to just
consider things like that your problem
size all that stuff um the workspace
size is just how big how big you
actually um return the minimum size of
the workspace to be pass to the
convolution given an algorithm right so
you're essentially just saying how much
do you get to work with here um and this
is defined by a bunch of things that it
it just it just decides this right so we
give it a bunch of descriptions and it's
going to use that context to decide um
what the workspace size should be um
now now we can do our Benchmark uh
warmup and Benchmark runs so we have
this um you know just skipping Alpha and
beta we have this convolution forward
function which I'll show you in the
Nvidia docs in a second here um this
consists of the handle Alpha tensor
descriptor for the input the input
itself which is just a you just any just
a void pointer right
um and then the the filter descriptor
the kernel uh convolution kernel so a
point again a pointer to to an array uh
the convolution descriptor so actual uh
operation algorithm itself the algorithm
um the workspace which we just find in
workspace size and bytes the workspace
size and bytes um we pass in this we we
do this size T which is like a size type
for like storing large values and we put
this into here and then this value
changes based on these settings right so
when we put this back in here it's going
to decide um when it's actually running
this how much do we need and and what
are the resources requirements it's pred
decided right
um and then we do um we just we just
enter the output description and then
the output uh the output device array
right and then we do the same thing but
with our uh con 2D except there's like
it's less complex to filter through and
then we synchronize all of our threads
and blocks in the GPU with Cuda device
synchronized very simple and we do the
same thing for benchmarks runs except we
just add a time and an event recording
as well right um so fairly simple
Concepts happening here just timing and
benchmarking and mainly just filtering
through what the heck a function takes
in and what are all these types doing
right that's that's really the mess you
have to dig through
um now if we go down um we can actually
we actually print out the CNN output and
the naive kernel output so and then the
flattened one as well so that we can
compare back to Pi torch element by
element um we just destroy all the
context afterwards same thing with the
tan uh same thing with the tan Cuda
script um go and run this so out
01 just like that link
CN we end we run this
um all of these are uh as expected and
so it's it's going to just yeah it's
going to select an algorithm these these
are all messed up I might change these
later but
um we notice that qnn is slower than the
naive kernel and that's because it's
just really small right it's very small
um qn probably has more to organize it's
got these Alpha Beta terms everywhere
it's got to take care of and um yeah
there there might just be some extra
overhead there so it is it is indeed um
you know like three four four times
slower than this just just because it's
smaller and it's not a big problem size
so if we look at the output here we see1
178 217 and then the end is like 274 275
175 now if I go and run um torch
compare it's going to do the exact same
thing notice how we get 111 178 217 and
then 295 1 uh or sorry 274 299 295 175
so go back here 274 295 175 perfect so
everything we can look through these
these all line up 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
11 12 13 14 15 16 elements uh and this
one has you know 16 elements as we print
out um at the bottom here just the
length of
that so I try to be like fa quick with
that it's very you know kind of just a
bunch of boiler plate code that we we
run through um but now uh now that we
know that this works and it's outputting
what we want it to we can actually go
take a look at the comparison script so
the comparison script um actually real
quick before I go to this comparison
script I'm going to bring up the uh the
cian and docs here just to kind of show
you the
uh go to
CNN so we're doing this convolution to
CN convolution forward right so we look
at this um and there's a bunch of things
in it so like this descriptor type
um handle Alpha Beta so it just
describes everything that we need to
know right so if something I said didn't
make sense maybe just like look at here
and it might make better sense to you
that way um but if we want to say look
at something like the forward algo type
we go here click on it and there's a
bunch of there's a bunch of values so
implicit um expresses as a matrix
product without actually explicitly
forming the Matrix that holds the input
tensor in so there's a bunch of
descriptions here about like different
algorithms you can use um and just like
when you might want to use it there's
also other articles on like which ones
are good for different cases um
convolutions are very very well covered
uh in the whole deep learning space so
shouldn't be too hard to navigate but
these are these are going to be your
forward forward pass
algorithms now if we
go back to um we go back to this
comparison script I'm essentially doing
the exact same thing except I set the um
I set the algorithm used to implicit gem
so that's the um that's this one right
here so I just set that manually and uh
yeah that's that's that's pretty much it
um now we we we set this to algo and
then we just plug an algo in there so
that's that's like the main difference
and then the other one is just how we
initialize our data everything else is
the same as this initial like uh just
the the convolution uh compare like
between P torch um so we where is
it yes so we initialize uh on the CPU
with just a bunch of random values um
and then we just do an operation with
those so I make the I make the element a
lot make this whole thing a lot bigger
so it's 224 by 224 by 11 by 32 by
uh 11 11 32 64 it's not it's not times
all of these but the input is going to
be of size width by height uh it's going
to be width by height by by in channels
by batch size so n chw as we did before
it's going to take up a lot of space um
but we're just going to Benchmark this
and see how it
goes so we go and run this get a batch
size of four and we notice CN average
time is 14.8 millisecs and the naive
kernel average time is about 82
milliseconds so if we do that if we do
that division
there we notice that we get a 5.5x speed
up by using 2D andm how awesome is that
right I mean if you optimized this naive
kernel up here and made it like more
specific to your your specific use case
rather than calculating a bunch of stuff
it would be faster um but this is kind
of just like for demonstration purposes
um CNN is still wildly fast and it would
take a while to get something that is
actually um more performant than this um
like significantly more performant it
would take a lot to do that um but
that's that's the idea right uh this is
why you use things like CNN and P torch
is because they're they're just like
super fast they just it just did a
massive convolution operation of like an
image with 32 channels of batch size 4
and a kernel size with like 11 by 11 um
it it's just like insane the amount of
operations it does in such a little
amount of time so that's what we're
working with um that's that's uh that's
that's C and in for
you now when you're working with big
massive data centers and GPU clusters
even if it's your own local rig that's
just on the side and you have 8 409s or
309s connected to it um this part might
come in a little bit of Handy right so
larger rigs or data centers um let me
just change that how that looks um so
you have kublos MP versus nccl versus
Mig uh now these are all different I'm
going to start with Mig because it's the
easiest one to explain essentially think
of it as your like your Amazon your AWS
and you have a you have a giant you know
GPU inside of your inside of your
facility your data center and so
typically with this type of GPU most
people aren't going to uh use the
entirety of it just like a small chunk
they just want the parallel processing
aspect for like some some whatever
signal processing I don't know and so
what you can do is you can actually
split that node um you split that node
into a bunch of a bunch of smaller gpus
it's multi-instance GPU you can have
multiple inst es connected to the same
card and you can split workloads evenly
and securely across those and so that's
what that's what Mig does it's used in
uh data center environments use cases
right um and then you have nccl so nccl
is actually really really important for
um distributed cluster Computing so this
is essentially going
to it's exactly how it sounds right it's
not going to it's not going to do
operations across but it's going to help
manage and communicate uh different
things across a cluster so use for
Distributing information collecting it
acting as a general cluster level
Communicator whereas kublos MP up here
is going to be doing the grunt work of
doing like say giant Matrix
multiplications across like a note of
eight 8
8100s um and then nccl is going to is
going to uh like run this in batches so
remember Collective Communications uh
these the operations within that um and
and there's more resources on this uh
would be like all reduce broadcast
gather scatter across right so not like
there's no like multiply or like fused
operations in here it's it's doing it
across a cluster and communicating uh
communicating data right um so just for
reference in pytorch you would use
distributed data parallel um for this
distributed cluster level Computing so
distributed data parallel data
parallelism at the module level which
can run across multiple machines so
module would be like say a function in P
torch right um which can run across
multiple machines um should spawn
multiple processes and create a single
data distributed parallel instance per
process uh and there's there's a bunch
of more stuff you can read about this
this is used a lot actually in pytorch
it's fairly simple to set up um but this
is this is like kind of all of that
simplified into one usable thing um
now going back um there's I do have more
resources on this too um I'm not going
to cover all of this since I don't
actually have a cluster in my house to
experiment it on uh but there are some
links and resources that you could you
know you could find yourself going down
a rabbit hole with these which is what
might be quite fun um but kuas MP is
actually going to it's literally
designed to do distributed basic dense
linear algebra so if you're doing like a
multi-gpu
um tensor tensor operation um this kualo
MP would handle that so if we go back
here and we go to
kuas uh kuas MP high performance Cuda
library for distributed dens linear
algebra um getting started um for
example like code samples um
right you you have these giant like
grids and stuff that you handle um
how to use
it um yeah maybe like how to use it for
example cap
API um and there's a bunch of
interesting resources on here as to how
you would do things maybe there's like
an
operation I don't know um that's this is
up for you to navigate it's optional you
don't actually have to know kublos MP
because pytorch does a lot of that for
you if you're just working with those
workloads um but if you're going to be
working on like data center
infrastructure this is something you
want to learn like Koss MP and nccl
so um hopefully that helps to provide
some context on uh like larger larger
setups give yourself a pad on the back
if you made it this far this has been a
lot so far and we've covered we've
covered actually an insane amount and
now we're going to cover one of the more
technical parts of the course called uh
matrix multiplication and how we we
optimize it so this is going to be one
of the most technical Parts uh mainly
because we're looking at uh like
lowlevel optimizations how do we
actually speed this up on the hardware
and so it's no longer just like the
general idea of how it works we're
actually using our knowledge and
additional knowledge that I'm going to
share with you on how we can makes uh on
how we can make the fundamental matrix
multiplication or the mat Mill algorithm
uh really really fast so this algorithm
is proprietary in deep learning it is
everywhere uh and so I figured the best
way to teach you how to optimize kernels
would be to use this as an example and
luckily uh we have we have a repo by uh
Simon bohim I think I think that's how
you pronounce it this guy's a this guy's
a performance or Colonel engineer at
anthropic so he probably knows what he's
doing and uh he made this really cool
repo called sjem cuda as well as a blog
post to go along with
so I'm just going to be following this
um and I was kind of lazy and not going
to like write all of this from scratch
on my own so I kind of just went along
with this and I want to explain to you
uh the steps of going through this and
how we actually how we Pro how we
progress through these different steps
getting up to uh pretty close to kublos
Performance and gigaflops uh or perhaps
even surpassing it depending on which
Hardware you have but uh this this is
going to be the goal so you might have
come across this article already uh but
but in case you haven't or in case you
have maybe this was too hard I'm just
going to go over this and uh we're we're
going to we're going to go superow level
things are going to be super clear after
you finish this part um you're going to
understand how to optimize uh Cuda
kernels so let's get started we're not
actually going to occupy the cud course
repo with this I'm going to link it in
the read me file so you can follow along
in case you're just going through the in
case you're going through this this
course repo but I'm actually going to
take some steps back here and I'm going
to clone it into my CA directory here so
I'm just going to delete the old version
um and we're going to get clone the
other repo in so it's just that
literally just uh pop in here copy copy
paste this in um go Ahad and get clone
that uh and then we're going to go ahead
and open this up and open this in vs
code so I'm going to drag that to my
side monitor here going to close
this and open this one up
again now inside of here we're going to
look at the read me first for setup um
so we can see that it uh in in the in
the build instructions we have to do um
we have to
do make directory build um CD into
it
oh uh and then we're going to
cake it's going to take take a second
there and then we go D- build period and
it's going to build everything for us um
now the idea here is to uh build
everything show all the different
benchmarks uh after after we actually uh
go through uh each optimization so we're
going to essentially print out the kuas
performance and then we're going to
print out naive and then we're going to
print out the next optimization and then
we're going to print the next one X One
XX until we get to the end then we're
going to compare all of them and see
which one is the fastest
so we can go ahead and start off with
just going
into just going into here so have a
bunch of different kernels we have naive
we have a global global memory colest so
if we actually go back to the uh blog
post which is what you know I kind of
expect you guys to follow there's not
too much here it's mainly just the code
so if we go back to the blog post um
we're doing we're we're we're
essentially just going in this order and
he does it in this order too so the
night of implantation I mean we've
already done this right um I can
actually go back and if I like make this
full
screen and I go out of this
um and I go into the Cuda course writing
your first kernels and then matm notice
I'm going to copy this for a
second and
then we're just going to paste it uh
inside of here just for
reference so we have these two kernels
and I just want to and I just want to
make sure that we're all like caught up
here the one I taught you before is the
exact same one that we're showing here
so this takes in um a b and C this one
takes an A B and C it it takes an alpha
and a beta as well I mean it's doing
it's doing a different it's slightly
different operation so it's not exactly
matrix multiplication but it's it's
essentially doing this uh this
essentially the the CU loss map that I
showed you before where it does the
alpha term uh like times every single
element in in the in the Matrix that we
calculate in the actual matl output and
then it adds um beta Plus plus a c
Matrix and then assign C to that new one
so it's a slightly different it's a
slightly different operation that we do
but we're mainly going to worry about
the matrix multiplication mechanics that
get get us to this temp variable so when
we look at this we have M K and N so
it's a matrix of shape so a is shape M
so it's like M vertical that's like the
batch size you could say and then it's
like K as like the length number of
columns right and then the B Matrix is
going to be K vertically and N long
right so we we essentially pass it in
the same way and we index them the same
way but in this example in in uh in
Simon's example we just we just pass
these in differently so it's like m and
n as like the edges and then K is the
middle one that we want to pay attention
to so we save that for the third one I
guess maybe that's that's thought the
thought process there but anyways we
have the we have X and Y so row and
column um the Y is the same as the row
here so uh which which y index is it at
because a row like row is vertical it
could be this row this row this it's
like a vertical scale right and then the
x is uh is column so which which column
is it at this is this is
horizontal and so we make sure it's not
out of bounds and then we continue with
what's inside of that little chunk of
memory and and we we proceed right so we
have this accumulator sum uh and then we
have this L term
uh we we could say that's the length and
uh and then we have this K which is
which is the length of a and then the
height of uh the the height of B right
so when you're do producting you're
you're taking the uh the row uh the a
row of a and a column of B so you're
iterating over you're iterating over k
and a and you're iterating over K and in
B right so that that's where that that
comes from that K stuff and so you're
just iterating
uh like in a row you're going through a
like this you're going through each
piece like each number and then in B
you're going through each number
vertically right and then we just plus
plus each time and then this sum output
this accumulator uh is just going to be
essentially the so a it we're looking to
uh multiply the first the first element
here by the first element here and then
and then advance and then advance and
then advance and then Advance right
that's what we're trying to do
you could also think of it as like a a
nice way I like to visualize this is
like a a 2X two tile so you have you
have like a 2X two tile you
have I'm try to visualize this from your
perspective you have like a up here and
then you have B down here and it's like
is that is that correct maybe it's maybe
it's yeah it's a here and then B here
and so when a has like a row that row is
going to like point to uh like the the
uh the y-coordinate in C and B is going
to point to the x coordinate in C so
when they like when they like intersect
it's going to find the the index in C
that you're going to calculate that dot
product result from that's a cool way I
like to visualize it for um but anyways
getting back to the point uh so we have
this row times uh times K so like which
row are we at the length of the row
right or sorry which which row are you
at so which row relative to you know the
the Cuda architecture itself and then K
which is the length of it so you're
going down you're essentially like
wrapping you're striding around and
you're doing this as many times as you
want to as like depending on which row
you're at and then you add the the K
offset to it so you might not be all the
way through the the length of it and so
you stop and that's where that plus
comes
from and then same thing for here we
have this L term which is K so how um
essentially which column are you at
right so here we have rows and then here
we have columns so it's uh L which is
essentially the the length of of that
vertical the length of a column and then
you iterate over uh you iterate Over N
times right so n is the n is the length
there and
so you essentially you essentially
Advance as many times you need to to the
to the I guess you could say to the
right and then you offset at whichever
column index it is so so same idea we're
just we're just advancing uh instead of
instead of going rows we're going
columns right and then we just
essentially assign uh
whichever in C we we index it like we go
uh row time uh time n so it's an it's an
M it's
an it's an M by n so it's going to be
like m is here and N is here so it's
going to go
uh row number times n so it's going to
stride n every time it wraps and then
it's going to do plus the column index
which is that X component right and
that's how you do the naive again just
just to give you a little refresher
there that was a while back we did it um
and then the same idea here so you
have m&n
m&n you have the accumulator we have
this I term that we're iterating through
and we have
K uh and then we go we have this temp
term we go X so X is the same as row so
notice how row is assigned to Y and X is
um well actually got a little bit stuck
there I was looking at the uh the block
and thread uh indexing scheme here and
it was kind of misleading so like notice
here how we have rows and those are by
the the Y index so whichever y position
I it's at that's like the row that it's
going to pluck out or the the column
it's like X so it's going to pluck out a
row or sorry a column in this in this
example we do um like X so that refers
to like right here um is is picking out
like it it kind of makes sense right
like X matches up with X and Y matches
up with Y but when we look in here um
like in comparison to this it's like the
row times the stride of K so we're going
to stride the the K length over and then
then come back to the next one and then
offset with
L in this one we have X which is like a
column Index right so it's like what why
would you do that we want to we want a
row index but this actually works and we
don't have to worry too much because
this is a square Matrix so because these
values are actually the same because uh
the grid and the and the thread index in
both the the X and Y dimensions are equ
we don't actually have to worry about
that so this is something youd want to
pay attention to in rectangular matrices
but we don't have to worry about this
right now so just kind of assume that uh
we can kind of just say that this is uh
like why and treat it that way but I'm
not going to edit this because we might
have to deal with this later on in uh in
future kernels so you kind of get the
idea though this is very similar to what
we were doing before um don't pretty
much just don't worry about the indexing
scheme it's it's going to be fine
um and then we yeah literally the only
change here is that we write out uh
using Alpha Beta and C right so that's
really the only difference there so
let's go ahead and actually run this
now so we pop into uh SJ Cuda and then
we go into
build now we can go uh sjem and then we
go number one so this is the naive
kernel that we run and we can see that
we're going to do a Max size so
Dimensions M = Nal K right so these
are okay I might have lagged there for a
second but yeah I mean as we can see um
Dimensions m equal nals K right so these
are all the same it's just like 128
essentially and then 256 512 1024 all
the way up to
496 and we can actually see the
throughput and G A flops per second so
what this means is how many billion Giga
right Giga is uh * 10 9 so billion and
then flops is floating Point operations
per
second and this is on a given size right
so on size 128 we get on average 46.2
gig uh billion floating Point operations
per second and on 496 we get about 166
billion floating Point operations per
second which sounds like a lot that
sounds like a lot of operations right
166 billion per second wow that that's
really high but the answer is that's
actually not that high it's going to get
a lot higher than this so high actually
that it it's going to seem like this is
minus kill this is going to be seem very
very small and actually slow so notice
how this took um this took uh eight
about is 83 seconds to do 50 runs right
so very um very slow or no per per run
sorry so not for 50 runs but for for
each run that it did which there were 50
of it took about 83 seconds to do that
on 496 with a naive kernel so a few
other points before we actually jump
into this um I want to First Look at the
uh I want to First Look at the blog post
here so when we're calculating the
output in the KN implementation I mean
like even just like looking at this uh
it's like really intuitive uh I I love
this example but
anyways uh when we actually look at the
the simple naive kernel um essentially
we're trying
to
uh we're trying to
find uh a certain part inside
of we are trying to find a certain index
inside of C that is going to be the
output so we're saying we want to do the
fastest possible calculation to get say
this number uh this index calculated in
the C output right in C
uh and so right now the way to do that
is to load in a row and a column and
then just just calculate that that's
that's what we found out naively so far
and it takes very few lines of code to
do that and so we just kind of iterate
through like I was saying before how you
put a on the side here and you let it
you let them sort of act as coordinates
that's that's what I was referring to
there um but anyways uh that's that's
kind of one of the one of the goals we
want to keep in mind is how do we
calculate the output in index it'll help
you it'll help provide some context on
how we actually get there cuz when we
deal with more complex kernels you'll
actually see there's a lot of steps to
actually get to a certain place and so
it helps when you're able to keep in a
consistent uh frame of thought where
it's like okay how are we actually
ending up at this result and then you
can sort of backtrack through and see
what's happening um so instead of just
like going and like reading like a novel
from from the start of the konal to the
end and just seeing like oh I guess like
we we'll see what we stumble into it's
like you actually want to see what
you're trying to calculate in the end
and that helps and and this blog post
refat a lot of context on that so
another little note I wanted to add is
like don't worry about 3D structures too
much so when we have the like the dim 3
type and we have the the YX and Zed uh
Dimensions all populated with numbers
greater than one it's like four 2 and
three it's like don't worry about that
we're not going to be dealing with 3D
stuff it's not going to be that
complicated it's going to be more so
like how do you transform uh
onedimensional and two-dimensional um
um dimensions and index efficiently so
don't worry about 3D stuff we're not
going to do any of that um and then the
actual uh indexing scheme here is giving
us coest memory access so I'll jump into
this in the next current a little bit
more in depth but essentially what's
happening is uh when we when we're doing
this uh like row calculation for example
um what it's like when it goes through
through um each row essentially what's
happening is uh we have this we have
this like X term from here and we put
this x term in all of the like in Cuda
when you have adjacent meaning like in
the X dimension in like in like the
length part horizontal when they are
next to each other you actually get CEST
memory accesses so when you're accessing
um a you actually you can actually uh in
in assembly it's actually going to group
multiple of the together into one so
when you have like a when you have a a
block inside of that you have a a warp
and inside of the warps you have um you
have uh 32 threads per warp right and so
we can like in inside of the actual warp
itself it's going to uh it's going to
call us memory access if possible and
when things are adjacent it actually
makes that possible so that's kind of
why we're seeing the weird indexing
scheme here again doesn't work for
rectangular matrices but in this case
it's kind of a an efficiency Improvement
for for indexing um the a matrix so
before we pop over to the global memory
colas kernel I thought I should probably
highlight something so this is important
to know for all kernels and even the
previous ones too but this is just kind
of like how memory is laid out right so
when we have a 2 X2 Matrix 1 2 34 um in
memory this is going to be laid out as
literally just a vector 1 2 3 4
so when we want to like for example in a
when we want to go to the next
essentially the next row and then do an
offset what we're doing is we're going a
current row times K which is this
Dimension here the the the horizontal
one so we're doing let's just say we
want to get to the number four here
right so if we want to get to number
four it's going to be current row well
the current row is going to be zero and
one right so current is going to be one
and then K is twoo long so it's going to
be uh 1 * 2 which is going to give us
this index so uh like the array at index
two is this so it's like 0 1 and two and
then the offset from that is going to be
the the the column index that's going to
be one so it's going to be uh 2 + 1 and
it's going to give us array at index 3
so that's just kind of what I mean by
strides it's like how how you go and you
like jump across the whole row that's
kind of what I mean there but going into
this uh glob memory Cass kernel scroll
down
and uh and I'm just going to I'm kind of
going to like skip this part and and
just lay it out for you but the whole
idea here and this is the critical
concept so the Matrix memory layout as I
just highlighted it's going to be it's
going to be consecutive memory like this
what going to
be it's going to be laid out like that
um and this is not going to be
consecutive memory right
so when we do do product of this and
this it's going to go to the third uh
third row and this is going to go to the
third column and we get this value right
this is a consecutive this is not in the
naive kernel we jump through these and
we iterate through uh we iterate through
a so we start off this like B column and
then we
go and then we we go to the next
one right we we we index in that fashion
we advance through the arrays in that
fashion and what we end up with in the
output is we get this like we get this
stack of blocks right and this and this
is what it looks like when we write to
the output it's going to be a stack of
blocks because we write um vertically as
as the rows advance in a that's what we
prioritize however if we uh
instead cess the memory
accesses uh we can get we can get these
laid out in this fashion so essentially
what we're doing is we're changing the
indexing scheme here um all of this
essentially Remains the Same except we
change the way that this is indexed and
we ensure that we're using thread idx
right so remember when we did uh when I
I was previously talking about how um
all of the essentially all of the all of
the the X like the thread idxx component
those are grouped together in a warp so
if you have like for example block size
32 um there's going to be 32 threads in
a warp that that's the maximum and so in
a in like blocks if you have this like
this this Square Block it's like 32 by
32 and you get the X Dimension you're
going to get the maximum number of
threads in a single warp if each element
there is dedicated to a different thread
right and so this way you're maximizing
the memory accesses because you can put
all of those together and you can make
that load uh you can make that data
transfer operation much more efficient
when you let an entire warp take care of
it it can do all the values at once or
or or group them together and make them
like way faster as opposed to going
through each individual uh each
individual uh like y component right so
when it goes like thread idx doy it's
actually it's actually not as efficient
right um and so we kind of just Chang
the indexing scheme here with these to
sort of illustrate the previous point I
wrote a little table for uh like what's
in the brackets here so this division of
thread idx and block size then the
modulo of or the modulus of that um so I
just kind of wrote a table here of what
these would actually look like in
practicality so if we just assume block
size is four which mean it's not in this
case but we can just simplify and
understand what's going on that way I
don't have to write out like a bunch of
numbers uh we assume block size is four
and so because block the because block
size that the size of an individual
block is four that means the thread idx
is going to have four indices uh in it
so it's going to be thread idx Z and
then one two and three it's going to
have four inside of it right so when we
divide we're going to floor the
operation uh that that's just what's
going to happen naturally is this is
going to get floored it's going to it's
going to truncate the end of it because
we're doing integer
Division and we're going to get 0 0 0 0
right 3 / 4 is 75 it's going to trunk it
75 and you're still going to have zero
um and then we jump up to when like this
advances then it's going to be uh well
the block size is four and when the idx
jumps to one then it's going to it's
going to be 1 Time 4 is four and then
plus Z and it wrap it kind of just like
resets right except it's plus one so we
have that going on then we have the
modulus as well so modulus is uh you
divide so 0 divided by four
um like integer and then what's the
remainder of that so if we do 1 / 4 um
that doesn't actually equal a whole
number so you end up with a remainder of
one and then you do that for the rest of
them so like 3id 4 is or three mod mod
four is three and then four mod four
since it just equals one there's no
remainder left so which just is zero
right and you get this thing where it's
like 0 0 uh 0 0000 0 1111 one and then
here it's like 0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 right so
when we actually look at um this example
here inside of
the where is it no not this one inside
of the Coles kernel um notice how in I'm
going to show you a second in our code
how this row does not actually change
and what we're doing is we're just
indexing very carefully these values so
when we're when we have different
threads that are like because each
thread is going to calculate its own uh
dot product right um like this thread
and this thread adjacent to each other
in the same warp they're going to access
um adjacent values so when they're
accessing adjacent values in the same
warp you can actually group all these
together whereas instead if you just uh
did this one if you did this thread and
then this thread and then this thread
that means that the first index of all
those uh all those threads um you you
you cannot actually you cannot actually
col that because you have to do like a
stride and they're not they're not
adjacent right so that's essentially
what we're doing here um and then we end
up with this like instead of a stacking
like blocks we end up with this with
this horizontal layout um so when we go
here we can see that c row so this is
only actually going to change every
every um every time we advance right so
this is going to stay at zero which
means that c row that's going to stay at
zero and then the plus I part that's
going to advance with with the dot
product itself um and then here I is
automatically going to advance so that
means it's going to uh it's it's going
to advance a column each time while the
row is going to stay at the same place
because c row is staying at zero right
and so you can kind of see how this
works out we have we have C column or or
or current column and this is actually
going to change over the threads so it's
going to go zero it's going to go 0 1 2
3 4 and then it's going to jump to the
next block block idea right and so what
you end up with is literally what I just
demonstrated um you end up by
essentially each each thread within that
warp is is accessing an adjacent value
and so you can group those and and cess
or combine the memory aises together and
we get more performance efficiency with
this so that's kind of like what this
article that this section talked about
um and if
we if we bump back bump back to here and
actually run this so kernel number
two we can see um we're actually getting
a lot higher Giga flops on this
one uh and then we can see that we get
about 1183 gig of flops here so that's
actually a pretty big increase of
performance I think previously it was in
the it was about 10 and uh what was it
like 180 or something or
like 160 I can't remember but it was
very low so this is actually like
significantly it's like 10 almost 10x
higher this is like maybe 5 8 10x higher
than what we had before on the 496
Square Matrix right so that's actually a
crazy performance Improvement we were
previously at like 83 seconds uh per uh
per
um per run and now this is at point
point about2 so if you if you actually
do the math there um 83 over uh 12
that's about a 7x increase in
performance in throughput so uh that's
that's pretty good um now we can uh now
we can move on to Shared memory cache
blocking which introduces a different
concept still uses what we've currently
done but introduces a whole another
Paradigm that's going to uh really help
accelerate and speed things up so next
we jump into something called shared
memory or SRAM and this is abs abolutely
critical to take care of when we're
optimizing algorithms for performance so
let me just kind of explain what the
deals with this so right now we're using
uh Global memory right uh the the host
is just our little Ram slots uh going to
the CPU and that's like really slow
that's about 5 gigabytes per second
still fast but very slow compared to um
this 200 GB per second that we get with
our vram this is what we're using now or
you can get even faster and use shared
memory which is around 1.5 tab per
second of memory bandwidth or registers
which is about 8 terabytes per second of
memory bandwidth we're just going to
focus on registers right now or or sorry
shared memory right
now um now in this blog post he had uh
about 700 gigabyt of glove memory band
which is really fast compared to this
and then about uh
12 terabytes of or 12.1 terabytes of
shared memory bandwidth
so uh or sorry not 12 terabytes 1 Point
1 Point 1.2 terabytes memory bandwidth
um terabytes per
second
now how do we capitalize on that how do
we actually use shared memory well it's
actually easy
um you use this little keyword called uh
it's not here but
I have it it's called Uh shared so
shared memory is literally just how you
use the that Shar that little L1 cache
so when we look up at the actual
architecture of this um I could open
image and new tab so you have your
Global memory so like the the big chunk
of memory that you have that's about two
200 gigas 200 gigb a second then the L2
cache for like a transfer medium and
then each little SM or streaming
multiprocessor um these have their own
little L1 cache or the shared memory and
this is very small compared to these two
right um but they are extremely fast and
they connect directly with registers and
the and the cores on your
GPU so when we can utilize these there's
actually far less travel distance you
have to go so instead of like every time
you need to access a float you go all
the way through um like s m or shared
and then to L2 and then to Global you
literally just just uh store a bunch of
them temporarily in s and in shared
memory have all of the threads use them
for like like essentially do a ton of
work with the memory that it has and
then once you're finished with that you
can replace it uh you can you can write
new values from Global so instead of uh
writing from Global every time you need
to access something you instead load a
you preemptively load a bunch into
shared memory and then you use them for
a bunch of work and then you then you
replace them with a new one once you
advance
right and sort of the goal here is just
making sure that we do this properly so
if I just go out
again shared memory is located on chip
much lower latency higher higher memory
bandwidth um heed this on a voltage GPU
so to go over how exactly we'll be using
shared memory it's actually a bit of a
different philosophy now I'm not not
going to like do like write this out and
everything because it can get like quite
uh it can get quite intensive when we
write stuff out
but this is essentially what we're doing
we're doing a little thing called tiling
which I demonstrated earlier where you
have uh little tiles that you do Matrix
multiplies for in a in a bigger Matrix
multiply
so instead of doing instead of doing
rows and columns we actually go and do
something a bit different and instead
what that is is is say we have this this
Chunk in C here and and so what you
would do is you would essentially like
if you have
um say
a let me try to use the current vs code
thing as an example so we have this uh
we have a we have a a c right now going
back
to going back to this one I'm going to
try to exp this is this have to explain
so bear with me um we're essentially
going to load in tiles and we have this
little C like the coordinates here and
all we're going to do is we're just
going to multiply multiply these two um
together and then multiply these two
together and multiply these two together
and then like we just essentially
multiply every Matrix um and then that
that that like coordinates up to uh this
this final thing here so we go we go
like through this way way and we sort of
we start at the very like the the very
top of B and the Very left of of a and
we multiply those together and then we
add it to the next ones we go in and in
and in and in and in until we like maybe
Cross or something and then that like
intersection Point
um that intersection point right here
that's where C is right and so when when
you have a bunch of these smaller um
less intensive map moles that can be
actually done on blocks
uh on on thread blocks then it actually
makes the job a lot easier because what
you can do is you can be smart about it
and actually store these blocks in
shared memory right uh if you're doing
individual rows or columns I mean sure
you could do that but it actually allows
us to uh distribute some of the work
more when we're when we're using blocks
when we're using literal tiles of the
Matrix right uh so let's go ahead and
dig into how this actually works under
the hood you're going to understand ort
of how tiling Works more once I explain
it and how I explain how everything
advances as as we dig more into detail
but uh this this is the idea here we
just we tile and we we we store these
blocks temporarily in shared memory and
do as much work with them as possible
okay so this is the code for a shared uh
a shared memory cach or or tiled mapal
you could say and uh pretty much a lot
of it uh well not a lot of it but the
start is pretty close to or actually the
exact same as as the last C we wrote so
we have this uh c row maps to block idx
dox c row maps to block idx dox and C
column isy C column isy now we have this
thread column uh
is uh maps to the mod operator and then
row maps to division operator right so
row maps to division and column maps to
uh mod right so these are these are
the the we essentially use the the same
idea as before and then we add this
additional piece in which is going to
allocate uh some some space in the
shared memory which is going to be of
size uh block size by block size right
so it's just giant thing you could say
that like each of these little rows just
like wraps around and you have this like
super long thing laid out in memory but
we're going to treat it as an actual
block like a square um and so why we use
block size by block size is because um
if we just say I mean we're going to
lower we're going to lower what what we
interpret block size to be in in the
examples just for intuition purposes but
in practicality this would be 32 right
block size will be 32 you have 32
threads that fit in the warp and maximum
1,24 threads per block so if you
actually
divide um if you divide
1,24 by 32 you get 32 so what we end up
doing is we have a warp a warp takes
care of these warp takes care of these
warp takes care of these and we have
like we're literally taking up the
maximum amount everywhere uh just by
using block size uh or a shared a shared
allocation of block size by by block
size right that that's the idea there um
and so we go down and I'm just going to
pull this up on the side here just for
reference um
so in
a what we do is we say uh we're going to
advance the pointers to the starting
positions right
so essentially we're going to
multiply uh c row we're going to do c
the the the current row times uh times
oh can zoom out the current row times K
right so K is going to be this Dimension
here this this this long one the the
sort the horizontal one and so if we
multiply the current row by K let's just
say we have like a current row
of uh if we have a current row of if we
want to do current row of one right so
we want to do current row time K which
is this length so it's going to jump
down to this one and then we want to do
times block size which in this case
since we split it into a bunch of tiles
is going to be two right it's going to
be 2 by two
uh and so we end up jumping two instead
of that so we go um the current row is
going to be one so we're going to do
this this one here so it's going to jump
uh the length of
that times the number we want to do
which is essentially one so we don't
jump down one and then that doubles
because we have block size equal to two
right so it's going downum two rows and
then we end up exactly where we want we
want to start at the first number um on
the first on the first uh like
essentially tile of this row
right uh and then B we we advance that
pointer to uh the current column times
block size so in this case b let's say
we want B to be uh like two right so the
current column is uh is is 2 so we do 2
* 2 which is four so we go 0 1 2 3 4 and
we end up there right so very intuitive
uh and then we have C which essentially
combines the to so uh in this case we
want to do c so it's going to it's going
to be um like it's going to be this row
and this column here so we're going to
end up it's going to be um the the first
row and then and then this column so
it's going to be this tile uh that we
want to take care of so it's going to
jump it's going to jump over to uh this
one from
the uh from the uh what's it called from
from the a matrix we're going to jump
all the way to or what was it no no no
in B we're going to jump all the way
here and then in a uh we're we're
essentially just going to add the we're
going to add the offset right so we want
to we want to jump down to because this
is the end Dimension so instead of
multiplying by K we would do
uh we would do uh we would do times n so
it ends up being like essentially this
we essentially this plus this right
except instead of uh instead of using K
we use n because that's that's the
length of C right so that that's the
idea there um and then we end up at uh I
believe it was this this totle 24 25 34
35 um so we continue to go down and this
is where we Define our accumulator right
so the temporary accumulator we have uh
and then stuff really gets interesting
once we once we get inside of this for
Loop this is where the magic happens um
so we have this term uh block idx and
we're going to iterate over K right so K
is that K is that uh the row the the
sorry the column The Columns number of
columns in a and the number of rows in B
right so we're going to advance block
size each time uh or sorry going to
advance advance block idx by block size
each time um and so inside of here
initially we want to store uh the stuff
in SRAM right or or shared memory so we
want to store it in here and literally
all we do is we look at uh the index
inside of here so thread row which row
is it times the block size so block size
is going to be that stride or that
wrapper and then plus the thread column
so which offset do we want to be at
right it's going to pick out a certain
spot in there um and luckily enough uh I
picked a block size of two so it's going
to be 2 by two and that actually makes
our job a lot more simpler to understand
I mean you can abstract it up to like
four or 8 or even 32 but we're going to
stick with block size of two for now and
this means we're just going to have um
we're just going to have two a thread
thread index thread
idxx of zero and one right so very very
basic threads to work with here and so
we're essentially just going to load uh
into this this shared memory which we
defined up here uh and we're just going
to essentially that that little spot
inside of it we're going to we're going
to pick that out from A and B so in a
it's going to be the thread row times K
so K is going to be that that that
length right
uh and then it's going to be
uh plus the plus the thread column
offset right so just that that ex
essentially the the same idea as what
we're doing here um
and then we're going to have the uh same
idea for B which is going to be n so n
is that again n is
the n is the top one here um and then K
is the top one here so K corresponds to
A and N corresponds to B right um I hope
that kind of makes sense and then
afterwards we just sync up everything so
this part's a little weird because we're
doing like sync threads but this kernel
itself like everything in here up till
now is like a thread so what this means
is that in the entire Block it's going
to make sure that all the threads catch
up to this point it's going to make sure
that every it's going to put a barrier
and makes all make sure all the threads
have like put what they needed to in
memory or else if we start doing other
things then you might have like a zero
value there where there's like there's
nothing that exists at that place in
memory and you're using that to do
operations which is then going to make
your answer wrong so you want to make
sure that all of the threads within the
block are actually caught up to here so
like these are on the level of threads
but we're essentially telling Cuda that
we want all of the different threads
that are doing all these parallel
operations to catch up within the for
Loop that's what we're
doing
um then we uh Advance a uh then we
advance a by block size so this is just
like advancing it preemptively we
already have all of this stuff St uh
stored in shared memory so we can
actually just Advance a we can ADV we
can advance the a point because remember
a is a pointer right um we can only
actually use like the index to get the
values but a itself is a pointer so we
advance that in memory we advance that
in the memory space by block size so a
is uh so a is like this this side one
that's like going to point inwards to c
and then B is going to point downwards
so uh a is going to advance a single
block so if a is like here for example
um a is going to advance block side so
two it's going to jump to here right um
and then
B uh B is going to B is going to do the
same but it's going to jump so it's
going to
go it it's just going to it's going to
Jump N right so it's n is like this
length it's going to do block size times
n it's going to jump it's going to jump
down two right and it's it's going to do
exactly what we want so it's going to
advance the tiles in the directions that
we expect Ed them to you might have had
some confusion about how we're just
using like the thread columns and just a
reminder uh these this a term is already
advanced to the correct position right
so once we're Advanced to like this this
Tile For example then we can just then
we can pretty much just use threads we
can use the the the thread indexing
scheme and that'll give us exactly what
we
want so now notice inside of this for
Loop we have the same indexing scheme as
we did in the global memory colest uh
kernel so when we uh when when we're
just efficient about going through the
columns and having the C as like a as
like a horizontal layout instead of like
a vertical stack of blocks that we're
just doing the exact same thing here
right um and so you might be wondering
about this temp variable um so this temp
this temporary is just is just going to
start off as nothing
and all we're doing is each thread
essentially each thread has its own temp
variable right that's going to be stored
uh in the register each thre has its own
temp variable and it's going to
accumulate this temp variable for uh
it's going to accumulate a DOT product
so what this is going to
do is it's not actually going to
multiply matrices together instead what
it's going to do is it's going to just
accumulate as it goes through tiles
right so as it goes through it's going
to like accumulate each value in the
output of C as it as it goes along right
so based on the thread it's going to say
say one is going to do like the row of
this one and then the column of this one
right and so when they when they
interact together or when they when they
interact they're going to end up at like
this top left part maybe and the thread
holds the temporary value for that
specific part um and what it's going to
do as like as it goes down through the
tiles it's going to accumulate this dot
product right so you get the first you
get the first dot product and then you
add it to the next one from the next
tile right because you're you're
essentially just doing the normal naive
matrix multiplication but you're just
accumulating through the
tiles and so in the end uh you end up
with just this this accumulated temp
however this is only for a single dot
product operation this is only for one
tile and the reason why we have this for
Loop inside of this one we're being very
clever about this is so that we can
actually do this accumulation through
the tiles right so that way we can kind
of be we could just be clever about how
we uh go about doing that uh and then
after we're finished we can just go
ahead and uh you know sync up all the
threads make sure that they're all
caught up and before we actually write
this out to C so I guess just going a
little like iterating over this again
the thread row so that's like which
which row within the tile we want times
the block size so that's going to be our
wrapper and then the the idx is going to
be how we're iterating through it so a
is row so we're going to that's the idx
we're going to go through this way
that's going to be the the offset on the
horizontal part and then B is going to
be uh idx times block size uh and then
plus that offset as we were doing uh
before right so we're maintaining that
Global memory access uh the that access
pattern that we had before um and we're
and we're just simply writing out that
temporary variable as it accumulates
through the tiles right so that that's
the idea here is we're accumulating
through the tiles so now we can uh
hopefully that makes sense feel free to
rewatch some parts of that feel free to
plug it into something like chat GPT or
CLA son it or something like that and
try to try to visualize what's happening
I have I have a separate uh additional
like diagram here just of like what this
looks like laid out uh I decid to add
this to the to the the course assets
folder inside of the faster Mill section
so if you want to check this out I might
add other ones to it but uh this is yeah
this this is the uh shared memory
blocking uh cud
kernel so now we can actually go in and
uh and profile this thing so I up into
here and just go sjem number
three we run this for a second it's
going to be really fast and so if we
actually compare this give it a second
it's doing the the last one there so if
I actually compare this to number
two which wasn't
uh give it a
second yeah so our number two with just
the Cass memory access was achieving
about you know 1,200 and this one is
achieving about 1,600 so we have a
decent improvement from that right um
but I probably should have done this
earlier but just to like spoil just to
spoil the surprise kublos is actually a
lot fast we run the 0 kublos is uh about
11,400 gig flops or 11.5 Tera flops
which is really fast especially compared
to our previous uh our our previous
naive kernel right this is extremely
fast now just to iterate before we move
on uh this this uh shared memory kernel
this is not implementing like the full
version of tiling this is just
implementing like a partial dot product
version of tiling known as blocking so
when we when we accumulate like dot
products that's not actually like the
full like the what you would Inuit it as
tiling right tiling as I described
before is when you like take the
matrices you multiply them and then you
you advance and then you multiply again
and you like add them every time they
multiply uh element wise and this is not
what we did here what we did was a
partial dot product so keep that in mind
the next one is going to be a little bit
different though
so 1D uh 1D block tiling is a bit more
advanced um but we'll get through it so
just to help get tiling crystal clear in
your head I'm going to use two matrices
as an example just to show how this
intuition works and I've actually
written out I did a little I was testing
a little bit and I I did the math Wrong
by hand so we're just going to use use
the computer for that um but I wrote out
a matrix a here so 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
11 12 13 14 15 16 and then this one B it
counts by twos but it goes backwards so
2 4 6 8 10 12 14 16 and then and then
continuous up to 32 so I've written
these out here in the terminal um and if
we just do
a multiply
B we notice that we get this output
result and these are pretty I mean these
are pretty easy numbers to work with
right so what I want to do is work
specifically with this upper right tile
the 200 180 456 404 that's exactly what
I want to work with so how we're going
to do this is we're going to use the
we're going to use an idea from
here
um to get this top right piece we
essentially want to uh cross inward
right so we're going to start off with
multiply a this this a portion with uh
with this B portion we're going to
multiply those together a * not B * a a
* B and then we're going to add that
with the product the the matrix model
product of this piece and this piece
right so if we start out first by doing
1 two 5 six and
go say um
a uh temp
torch.
tensor and then inside of here we're
going to have a smaller ones so it's
first going to be uh 1
1256 uh and then we multiply that with
torch.
tensor tor. tenser 4 to 1210
right and if we print out a temp we get
this
result now we do uh B
temp tch. tensor and I'm just going to
print the uh actually I'll just I'll
just print the layout here we'll do a
we'll do the same idea for a temp but
I'm just going to remove these values
and we'll place this
with uh with B temp so this is going to
be uh
3478 multiply that with uh 2018 28
26 20 18 28 26 all right okay awesome
now we print out B
temp
oh and then we do a temp plus b
temp and we get the result that we were
expecting 200 180 456
404 um 2 180 45644 and that's a TOD M
that that's really all there is to it it
just helps when you're able to draw this
out by hand and understand what the
purpose is when we like advance for
example when we advance pointers by like
a a greater offset than like one or two
or three or four it's like when you're
skipping entire rows and you're going to
like a c when we when we when we do that
stuff this will help you understand why
we're doing it
um but uh yeah we can go ahead and begin
awesome so now let's go ahead and look
at the uh boiler plate code for this as
well as the runner script uh for this so
in the runner script we'll actually pop
down and you can see each uh each little
like function and how we call everything
in here so like the kuas function for
example there's like different ones for
like fp32 brain float 16 tensor float 32
right uh and then we have like the naive
the colest the shared me caching which
we just recently did and then we have
the 1D block tiling right so notice how
in the shared memory block we just have
32s everywhere we have 32 32 32 32 and
32 right everything's 32 because
everything is a square but in this one
we we actually mix it up a little bit so
we we have these essentially this this
block uh so M it's going to be this this
block on uh on a so it's going to
because it's specific to uh A and C
because when we do our our uh like our
matrix multiplication shapes we're going
to cancel out the inner ones uh K and
then you're going to be left with um
we're going to be left with M and N
right so
just pay attention to these shapes here
uh we also have the eights down below so
uh just just like be aware of this we
use we use different uh shapes here to
help speed up operations because we
introduce A New Concept um and that
concept is 1D block tiling for
calculating multiple results per thread
so if we actually go back into uh the
shared me uh blocking uh when we write
the output we have the specific spe ific
index per thread that we write out it's
just one we write out one output of that
block or or sorry of that tile and
that's it uh we just leave it at that
there's no iterations we're not we're
not wunning multiple per thread just one
now if we go to here we notice that
we're actually writing multiple so we go
over this res or this result idx um
that's essentially goes uh it iterates
through uh
TM which is this term that we found in
in here which is uh essentially threads
per M Dimension you could think of it
that way so in short we're going to be
writing out multiple results per thread
and that's going to speed up um
everything a lot so like imagine if you
had to do uh you had to issue a new
thread every time you're going to write
an output of this entire Matrix so if
you have a
496 uh by
496 that's going to be about 16
different threads that are writing out
right that that is a lot of threads you
have
to there's a lot going on there so uh
when
we um when when we use when we iterate
over we can get one thread calculating
uh multiple and make things more
efficient it does it does make the
indexing more complex and this is
probably one of the most intuitively
difficult kernels to understand but once
we get there uh it should be a breeze so
going up for our boiler play code we
have this c r is block ID x.y so we're
going to use blocks uh each individual
uh block of threads is going to
calculate uh a specific tile on the
output right so we have this block
essentially the current the current row
and the the current column so current
row is like it's like a like vertical
which row are we selecting and that's y
right so that's vertical and then the
column like we doing before it's you
know horizontal Dimension um now we go
to here which is essentially the the
thread uh the the lower level thread
column within that so we have this we
have this BN term that's used and this
BN term we remember back to here was 64
right so let me pop back to
this this BN term we see it in both the
B Matrix and and the C Matrix right this
is BN right it's that length right there
so when we actually
um when we do mod BN what that's going
to do is it's like if if BN is 64 it's
going to be like um thread idx like zero
divide by that it's just going to be
zero right and then it's going to go 1 2
3 4 5 because we just have this
remainder that's like not 64 right so
once we pass 64 then it then it's going
to Loop so it's going to it's going to
iterate through all the columns and it's
going to go up 0 to 63 and then once we
actually hit 64 it's going to um it's
going to it's going to divide right so
it's going to floor up it's going to
floor to zero for each of these indices
leading up to 64 and then once we
actually hit it it's going to divide and
it's it's going to go to one right
because it's going to floor down to one
and we're going to be it's going to be
like a bunch of zeros and then a one
right and we use this to pick out our
rows so the columns it's like 0 1 2 3 4
5 all the way up up to 64 and then the
rows it's like every time we stride this
many it's going to it's going to bump up
one so the division is going to go up to
like one and then two and then three
every time we stride that 64 length and
then it's going to increase the row
index so it's going to it's essentially
going to be like like I said a row index
it's going to move us downward right in
C uh and this is this this is kind of
why we we have this here so moving
further down we have the a shared and
the B shared so just the the normal
shared memory that we allocate um so
this going to be M by K and then K by n
right that's that's the space we're
storing and then uh in this specific uh
in this specific
thread we advance the we we advance the
block tile to the beginning of A's row
and B's column right so we did the same
thing in our past one where we had
Advanced everything uh forward right so
this is
literally uh this is literally the same
idea right so we're we're doing the
exact same thing there we're just using
a little bit different terms because
it's now rectangular tiles um these
assertions here are pretty much in place
to say uh we don't want to go out of the
block dimx range right it's just like a
essentially like a you could think of it
as a boundary Checker so when we're when
we iterate through BM or BK we don't
want to go out of range we want to make
sure that these kind of add up we want
to make sure that um when we have this
like 2D structure that when we flatten
it out it stretches the length of block
dim dox and that that's pretty much
what's happening there um we we assert
both of these so uh essentially when we
go back it's like um you know n and K
are the same and then M and K are also
the same so that kind of lines up there
and then same and then for these ones
the same IDE as what we were doing here
so the thread column so we do this thisx
divided by the uh the X Dimension there
which is BN that's the that's that's the
trailing dimension in C it's going to be
M by n and so in here we just do thread
idx divided or for the for the column
index of a the inner column index of k
or a sorry uh we're going to do thread
idx mod BK so BK is that that horizontal
dimension in a right cuz it's M by
K and
then the inner row in
a is going to be just the the division
of that so whenever we stride the length
of K it's going to notch up one and it's
going to tell us which row index we're
at right that's that's kind of how we
that's how we use the threads to decide
which index we're at and then same idea
for uh same idea for B here except we
use the trailing dimension in B which is
n uh instead of K in the a matrix right
and and then in in
uh we essentially here we we allocate
memory this is going to be very
important for when we write things out
later on so notice how we iterate over
this term TM we're going to make thread
results like a like an actual uh thread
local cache that has the size TM TM is
very small right so in here TM is TM is
actually eight so that can that can
easily fit in registers um and then we
just initialize this with a number just
say zero and then we're going to
populate that later on right so we just
initialize this beforehand and then
we're going to change it later um now we
actually jump into a little bit more
advanced stuff so this entire sorry this
entire Loop here is where a lot of the
magic actually happens so when we're
when we're in a single uh when we're in
a single um when we're in one when we're
in one of these
iterations we are trying to calculate
the uh compl complete tile for uh an
output in uh C right within a block
that's what we're trying to do a a block
a block in like a certain block idx
within the grid is going to calculate uh
an output tile in C that's the goal here
so we outer we we Loop over these block
tiles by iterating over K right K is
that um K is the uh horizontal dimension
in a and the vertical dimension in B
right so we we iterate over those and we
advance by this much each time we're not
actually going to use uh we're not
actually going to use block idx like as
you can see we only actually have it in
this one line here it doesn't show up
anywhere else so this is just for making
sure uh that we don't if we just like
iterate by one each time then it's going
to go out of range and we're going to do
this Loop way more than we need to so we
just want to do it for as many blocks or
for as many blocks uh as we need
right we then populate the uh shared
memory caches so this is within uh this
is within a single uh tile right so
notice how we use the inner row a times
K right so it's the that's the that's
the which row are we at inside of it um
and this is these are like um these are
like very small ranges of indices right
and that's going to in a it's going to
loop around K and then that EXT column
index is going to tell us which position
we're at right relative to uh the thread
of course so we can like parallelize the
ACT actual loading
part and then we do the same thing for B
all right so we have this they have this
row um and we're we're we have we have
like which row are we at and then uh we
want to essentially stride that number
based on n and then end up with that
offset column index um so that's what
this is Here We sync everything up so
this is again at the at the Block Level
so it so a kernel normally runs at the
level of threads but because we're doing
sync threads it's going to apply to all
of them so all of the threads uh within
this within this block are actually
going to line up they're all going we're
going to put a barrier and they're all
going to meet up and they're going to
synchronize at the same same spot right
um and then we just Advance the block
Tile For The Next Step so when we uh
when we need to do this load again this
is already ready and we don't want to we
don't want to like worry about this
anymore right
okay so remember A and B are just
pointers right when we scroll up we see
A and B are Pointers to uh float arrays
right so when these are laid out in
memory uh they're they're not like it's
not like an array of arrays um or like
an an array of pointers where each
pointer inside that array is a new array
like we did in the in the C and C++
review chapter it's not like that it's
it's literally just a it's literally
just a pointer and it's the pointer is
at the start of that thing that's start
of the array that's laid out in memory
so it's not the actual value it's just
the memory address so if we take that
memory address and we we plus one it'll
go to the next index next one next one
next one right um that's what we're
doing here so we already did this in the
last we already did this here um where
we or is it this part we just we just
Advance further um so a advances um
essentially plus an an entire block size
so we advance the we we just Advance
Plus uh whatever this value is to a so
it's going
to it's just going to increase that much
whatever we set that to and then this is
going to increase but it's going to have
that n stride right so the the trailing
dimension in B is n so it's like K byn
and so it's going to it's going to wrap
right it's going to wrap and it's just
going to find the sort of the the next
the next one in uh in in B right and
that's that that's really all we're
doing there
so then we go to this next part uh this
is where actually a lot of magic happens
and I'll do my best to explain this but
this part's like kind of intuitively
hard so we have multiple Forbes in here
we have this idx that we iterate over BK
with uh we have this float we have this
this specific float um this this this
sorry this this temp temporary variable
and then we have an inner loop here so
I'll try to explain this as best as
possible um
we jump back to here we notice how uh
like initially we have these two
matrices that we're trying to multiply
together so this is uh this is a and
this is B right and we have this this
tile intersection as we did on the
Whiteboard there um and so the really
the the magic happens is is like in
these Loops right we've already taken um
in this outer one we've already actually
taken the block tiles we already have
these in shared memory and now we have
to do fast operations with them so we go
down to here where we actually have
these in shared memory right this is a
tall and and not very wide this is uh
wide and a little bit tall right so it's
it kind of matches
up and then inside of here what we do is
we notice how we do we iterate over idx
and then in here we iterate uh through
through this this this TM right so we
have this idx and then res idx uh over
TM so if we actually pop back to here um
essentially what's happening is this at
the lowest level in the innermost Loop
res idx is going through uh like we we
have this jump here which I'll explain
that indexing in a second like how we
actually arve there but res idx is going
through these it's advancing uh
vertically downward and it's multiplying
with whatever value this is so that
little top left corner in B that top
left corner value in B is going to stay
the same and res idx is just going to
multiply with that value it's going to
go and it's going to compute a partial
dotproduct along this
column right now now when we do uh when
we iterate over uh idx what's going to
happen is uh idx is going to it's going
to go forward this way and it's going to
go down this way right so notice how
these these arrows are are colored very
similarly they're they're actually the
same color so that means we're GNA
idx is going to evolve downwards in B
and idx is going to evolve uh to the
right in a so whenever we evolve like
one it's going to like essentially res
idx is going to take this value it's
going to go and then we're going to uh
evolve one forward and then where IX is
going to reset and then it's going to do
a DOT a partial dot product for the next
column right it's going to do a partial
dot product uh for the next column and
it's going to do this all the way until
it is finished inside of inside of uh
this this entire section and then when
these evolve uh inwards right so when
this is when this is going forwards um
and like just not even considering res
idx just like think about like sure
these ones are all filled in this one
too but when this goes forward when this
goes forward and multiplies with this
and they are both inching in one at a
time as dot this is what's happening as
idx is is moving up um these are
actually acting as little um like
essentially little tiles right and so
you end up Computing this specific uh
you end up Computing the full dot
product of this so when when this one
moves like here it's like 1/4 of it is
done right 1/4 of it is done and then it
moves up half is done half is done 75 75
and then it's fully done once that
evolves all four steps this entire Index
right here is computed and so we notice
that when we do res idx and we go
through all of these we end up
completing the entire row so when we go
through this way and these this this
goes forward we complete one column at a
time right one column at a time is uh
completed per thread and so when we um
when we have other threads acting like
thread column and the thread row which
is acting as these little blocks that
are shiting downwards instead of like
little individual 1D columns um you
actually end up Computing the entire
thing so thread column is laid out this
way through like it's like essentially
all the column indices in in the B
tile and then you have the thread rows
which are here and so this is going to
compute all of the all of the columns in
C it's going to it's going to cover all
of them in the tiling aspect and then
this is also going to cover all of them
so what you actually end up with is you
can complete the entire tile by giving a
thread more operations to do so when we
actually jump into this
um we can see so first of all we have
this temp B right so this is coming from
the B shared memory this is so we just
say
idxx is zero this is the first iteration
it hasn't or the zero with iteration it
hasn't changed yet so this is zero and
it's going
to it's going to evolve you know across
BN zero number of times right so 0 *
that is z and then plus the thread
column if that is also if that is also
zero then it's just going to be here
right it's literally just going to be
there um and when idx moves up then it's
going to
um like this isn't it's going it's not
going to move this way that the this
offset here is from the thread itself
the thread index itself but we're
actually going to Traverse downward
right that's that's the do idx as I was
explaining before and then uh you have
the uh this res idx the result idx and
this goes through TM right so this is
this little block that we have here
um
and when we actually look at how this is
accumulating remember this is the size
of um this is the size of TM we're going
to iterate through TM with this red idx
or res idx that's going to be the the
POS the the amount through TM which
we've iterated through we're setting
that index to uh a place in shared
memory and this exact place is going to
be so the thread row times uh TM plus
res idx right so thread Row in this
case thread Row in this case is
whichever one of these it falls at right
so that that's a specific row that it
falls at considering that we evolve uh
like in TM blocks right that's that's
the that's the amount that we evolve we
we progress each time and then this res
idx part um res idx is how much are we
vertically offset so we we advance like
four or like eight or four or eight
downwards and then we have this
additional offset res idx um but we have
to make sure that we actually arrive at
that specific piece cuz it's it's going
to be laid out in memory like this right
so we have to make sure that we evolve
straight downwards and that we get to
that certain res ID ex
position now we multiply this by the k
which makes this a lot easier for us
right that's that essentially solves
that problem so however many we want to
go down this this thread whichever
thread row we're talking about times TM
which is you know that that block
space um plus res idx which is that
offset and then times that all of that
times BK right this this K Dimension
here and that's just going to times it's
going to
go right where we need to be
then we just add the idx offset which as
I highlighted
before is literally just going to
progress that way so it's going to
iterate all the way to the starting
position uh and then idx is going to
tell us how much has it gone to the
right uh and so you have this do
idx here that traverses downwards and
here it traverses to the
right now if we go back we're
multiplying this um by this one we're
multiplying it by uh the the temporary B
value keep in mind this is the only
thing controlling this is the idx which
we already highlighted this is going to
make it go downwards and then the thread
column so thread column as I mentioned
before again we're kind of just going
like starting with the visual example
and then going into the code and then
connecting that to our visual example so
thread column is that that horizontal
offset and that that like each thread is
just going to get a different horizontal
offset right so it depends on which
thread we're at um
and then we go back to here um and we
have this this thread row right so
that's just going to depend on which
block we're at so in this case we're not
at block uh we're not at sorry we're not
at thread row zero we're at thread Row
one so it's going to Traverse TM uh
layers down which in this case is like
maybe four or eight or whatever whatever
number we pick right um and then it's
going to end up there and then the rest
of the math is going to ensure that we
get to the correct position with respect
to resid and
idx some other things you want to pay
attention to here are how these actually
uh are coest in memory right so in
memory um keep in mind when we're
loading these columns in when we're when
we're loading these little column bits
in in uh in
memory we're loading them as if they're
like adjacent next to each other right
so this like thread zero is going to be
adjacent to to thread thread column one
thread column Z is adjacent to thread
column one they're next next to each
other thread column two three four five
right so when we actually load this on
the level of threads that memory access
is going to be CEST it's going to be
combined we're not going to have to you
know consider this stride and then like
oh we need to get two memory accesses to
get both of these it's like no you can
actually fit um like a bunch like
however many as you need into one right
so technically what you're going to have
here is you're going to have um
since BN is
64 BN is 64 so this this whole length
here it's going to have two warps so
it's going to literally going to be uh
like two memory accesses that we need to
do because um that like an entire warp
that can actually make memory accesses
really efficient when we have two that's
that's effectively just two memory
accesses uh that we have to worry about
so it's really awesome that we have
these that we have these colest right I
mean this itself this other one isn't
going to be coess but that's fine um
because we you know we're we're still
using shared memory what we do care
about though is that these are colest
right the column accesses are colest and
that's going to make things really
really fast so to iterate um we we
essentially iterate over and we complete
we let the threads complete uh The
Columns uh like partially and they they
Advance over and the and the dot
products are going or the the dot ID EXs
are going to evolve and they're they're
going to close inwards and then they're
going to complete that slowly right and
these these individual threads are going
to complete the columns right so they're
going to they're going to move through
the res idx and then the do ID XS are
going to evolve this way so you end up
just completing a whole column because
these line up and this one lines up and
so you get you get a bunch of
these and then one of these
right so then we sync up the threads we
make sure that they're all caught up so
that we can actually write out the
results safely right this is for a
specific block tile so when we have like
a bunch of them in the entire thing we
have a bunch of block tiles we're
worrying about um we want to make sure
that we've synced them up for this
current block tile just for safety
purposes right we don't want to mess
anything up so we're just going we're
going to be safe there and then when we
actually write out the results it's
going to be very similar to what we
actually did um up here right so we
iterate through this TM term again um
and we're going to have thread row time
DM plus red res idx and then times n
right so n is in the bigger picture of
that whole that whole C Matrix um and
then plus the actual uh thread column
itself which is going to be that offset
uh and that that's the actual uh index
that we write out and we're going to
iterate over TM or eight indices every
single thread so each thread is going to
write out eight elements right instead
of just one writing out eight
elements um and then we're we're just
going to keep in mind this you know this
this thread result results we're just
essentially each time we write out it's
just going to populate that index so
it's like a very easy way of just
keeping track of uh of like which ones
we write out at the lowest level of
Hardware like SM and registers so it's
just going to make our jobs easier on
that level so we could literally just
store them one by one it's like eight an
array of eight elements and then we
write out that array of eight elements
we don't have to worry about strides or
any of that stuff right um we multiply
Alpha by that um for each for each one
right for each index and then we do the
same with beta so beta is another term
and we have C which uh I mean c is just
we're essentially just element or we are
we are pointwise multiplying beta so
it's like whatever beta is maybe like
0.5 or three or whatever it is we're
just multiplying each each one uh and so
we consider the the strides and the
offset as as well for
that okay awesome so now we can actually
generate or we can actually see how this
performs uh so remember how bad our
initial kernel was I'm going to go ahead
and run SJ 00 just to show kuas um it's
going to iterate up and we're going to
get about 11.4 11.5 Tera flops of
performance and then if we go ahead and
run the block to one so kernel number
four go ahead and run
this we're going to get like actually
quite a bit faster than the previous
which was
03 and this one
uh give it a
second this one gave us about 1 1600 uh
1600 gig flops this one is about a 3X
speed up of what we previously had which
is really good so that pretty much just
shows uh that the memory access patterns
we use so that that coling of of memory
access was really really useful and even
more useful was using a single thread to
do multiple computations to compute
eight elements instead of just one right
so that really really SP up our
throughput and performance there so now
if
um I actually wrote a like off camera I
wrote a separate uh I wrote a separate
function here or not function file main.
cuu inside of the Kel's folder so so we
could easily like compile it um what I
pretty much did is I just uh imported
this so the the for essentially the
block tiling kernel the the header for
that right here uh I included the macro
which we had in the previous file I
initialized the majores so 1024 1024
1024 um and then our previous like 64 64
8 and 8 and then I just populated these
um could amalik manage just use like
this this unified memory which is like
going to just reduce a bunch of
boilerplate and make things uh a little
bit sped up for us but you're you're
going to see the the main thing that
we're looking for in a second um I
initialize everything properly and then
I call this kernel uh and we're just
trying to see like what is the actual
code look like under the hood here so if
uh if I go up to this command that I ran
recently nvcc D PTX that means parallel
thread execution parallel thread
execution is what Cuda compiles down to
it's the Assembly Language for parallel
processors uh and then you have just the
file that we're compiling and then we
output kernel. PTX
right or I have to get out of this um
and then go into
SRC kernels uh and then go and run that
this is going to give us this kernel.
PTX file which I'll just open here we
bring this
up we go into uh kernel.
PTX we notice uh there are a lot of
lines in this there are 308
lines
and it doesn't tell us anything super
specific specific right like we can see
um like for example like an ad an ad
operation or uh like a fuse multiply ad
with a with a floating Point 32 number
um it's like I think output and then
like multiply these and then add this
one I can't remember the exact order but
like fuse multiply add right you can
find all these instructions in here
[Music]
um multiply right um
yeah we have the the load instruction so
LD so it's going to load uh a floating
Point number into uh
shared into the into the
SRAM and then we leave this if I can
exit Vim uh I have a separate one that I
also outputed this is the Shader
assembly so initially nvcc is going to
compile everything down to PTX and then
PTX is going to further compile to
Shader assembly which is then actually
run on the GPU Shader assembly is what
it executes so if we compile uh you know
Cuda binary right this actual the actual
binary that we run and then we and then
we uh compose this back up into the
Shader Assembly Language that uh is
actually executing and then we output
that in the Cu uh the Cuda binary
format we
can uh
Oh wrong one let me let me check real
quick we go yes so we've compiled it
into this and now we we uh we look at it
again through the special command so
Cuda object dump uh dump Shader assembly
and then just open essentially open that
and it's going to give us the exact uh
assembly code or what we just what we
just uh compiled right that entire
script
so if we look look very carefully for
like load instructions right so if we
look for LD
um which I know is from the it's from
here so PTX compiled to Shader assembly
the S shared memory loads from from B
shared are vectorized right B shared was
the one where we had uh these individual
uh columns right so when that was in
shared memory the smm loads from shared
are vectorized remember when we had the
threads that were adjacent to each other
those are what we're looking for so if
we look for
LDS so we have
LDS um U 128 right LDS u32 right we have
all these ldss here um and this is when
they're not coest so this this LDS when
we have the 32 that means it's it's it's
not uh it's not cess together right
these these um when it's when it's not
accessing like four in a row so if you
do a a 32-bit floating Point number 32
bits * 4 is 128 so when we're accessing
four in a row it's going to be 128bit
load in uh Shader assembly so this is
what it actually looks like when we get
those cols memory accesses going and
this is what it looks like when we're
not right so we end up having to uh you
know maybe load more so we have like two
loads here uh but anyways that this this
is the entire Point here just to show
you what the actual loads look like in
binary format that this this is what
they look like uh and we're going to
further optimize uh these kernels to
perform better right fe uh I think this
is f ffma is like fuse multiply ad
floating Point fuse multiply ad I can't
remember we can actually search that up
uh to uh F FMA in uh Shader assembly
so yeah fused fused multiply ad there's
probably a manual somewhere which I'm
not going to look through right now you
can do that but uh these are the Shader
assembly instructions that we're working
with
um Now we move on to 2D block tiling
which Builds on what we've already done
but makes it even more efficient and
makes it even more
performant okay absolutely give yourself
pat on the back if you made it this far
this been quite challenging so uh you
know feel free to take take a coffee
break or whatever um get some
tea I have some tea with me right here
so you know it's it it is a grind um but
if we step back to just this blog post
here we go to Kernel number five so
increasing arithmetic intensity with 2D
block tiling before we were just
calculating columns right we were just
calculating columns and now this one is
going to calculate entire blocks it's
going to calculate like a mini block
inside of the big block tile right
that's the idea so before we just had
this idx in the in the in the the B tile
this was going to go downwards and we
just had a single thing that was
iterating down and calculating you know
a column so you have this you would just
kind of intersect and you get this
column filled
out but now we have this res idx uh n
component right so that's just that's
just going to go and make this
essentially cover um like like a square
or like a row and a column right so they
intersect and it's going to fill up like
a square area um so we have this we have
this term which we're going to iterate
over and then we have this new TN term
so TM is literally just this component
and then TM is this component underneath
right um so now like stepping into
this this is kind of just what it looks
like under the hood when we sort of
visualize how this is how this is being
calculated so we look at our um
we look at our our a tile and we look at
our B tile and it's literally just we're
storing a column um in reg M so that's
like an actual register memory in this
kernel we're actually using register
memory so we're we're occupying it a
little bit more we're uh as you can see
we literally populate it so reg m is
going to be of that size and then T reg
n is TN size right um and the total
results is going to be the surface area
of that total area there
um and we just we essentially just store
a column and a row and those will those
will dot product through this entire
thing and they will intersect and you'll
get this little square right here um and
you can we can see how that evolves at
each step
right so now there's my marker let's
actually step into this
kernel so we go back to here and we see
um you know run sjem 2D block tiling
right so we have this we we have a we
have this same BK term right so BK is
just going to be eight in this case um
and we have TM which is also the same
and we have this new TN term right so
we're essentially just going to
calculate um like this area that we fill
out is going to contain 64 elements it's
going to be 8 by 8 that's going to fill
that entire thing up and we're going to
have 64 in
there now we have this little hacky
situation for handling like the very
very low like the smaller matrices that
are going to be tested when we do a
Benchmark so this is why we have this
little out statement here
um so in case we you know decide to use
um in case we decide to use like a very
small Matrix this is able to deal with
that effectively but normally we're just
going to we're just going to pay
attention to this first if statement for
now um so if these are bigger than
bigger than or equal 128
right
um yeah so in
here pay attention to this we have a
grid dim which is going to have um an X
component right and then a a y component
right so that that's going to that's
going to stay the same and then this
block Dimension the the number of
threads within a block right it's the
that like the block itself the dimension
of that the X component there's just
going to be one value here and that's
going to be um essentially the the total
number of elements in the output tile so
you know we have this B and this BN and
then they then they they you sort of
just get this this filled out area of C
the C tile that is going to be of this
of this size right and then we divide
that by the total surface area covered
by um by just what a thread calculate so
a thread is going to go through those 64
elements it's going to be 8 by8 it's
going to go through those and they're
going to calculate a small little mini
grid for us um like per thread right um
and so if we we divide the total number
of output result results by the uh by
the space covered by a thread we
actually get the number of threads right
because each little piece here is a
thread and so if we divide this by this
we actually get the total number of
threads within that entire SE tile um so
if we do this math
here we're going to get so
times8 and then divide this by
by8 and this simplifies to well 128 is 2
to 7 right because remember like if you
if you know like int 8 Precision it's
it's like it's like an image essentially
like number of number of like uh RGB
values in a single U like in a single
Pixel so you have like RGB and each of
those is like Zer to 255 so that that's
like how you can go down to what like uh
128 is 2 to the 7 cuz it's like in 7
instead 8 that's how I made that
Association but we have this 2
7/ 2 3 * 2 3 and what you end up
with is 2
/ 2 6 and we do our exponent laws and we
get eight right so 14 - 6 is 8 so two
the8 that means we have
256 my marker works
properly 256 threads
right 256 threads my writing is messy
ignore that um awesome so we know the
number of threads that we're calculating
now this is going to help us when we
actually jump into this kernel here so
you know we have our our BM or BN BK TM
and TM again
right there's a lot happening here let's
break this down so to start we have our
our row which is going to be the the
typical y component we've already went
over this the total results in a block
tile are as we already said in the in
the runner file uh this is just
essentially the the the whole the whole
seed Matrix so you have the M Dimension
then you have the N Dimension you
multiply those and you get total area
right that's the number of results we're
going to get calculate and then we get
the number of threads per that entire
thing so how many individual squares are
there that a thread is occupying right
and so that the square surface area is
this which we already calculated and so
this number of threads per block tile
should equal 256 right and then we just
assert that down here so we want to make
sure that 256 value is equal to what we
just calculated which is going to hold
true of course and then it won't it'll
actually continue with executing right
um let go down a little bit further
um don't worry about these right now
we're going to get into those in a
second so we do the the classical just
allocate shared memory we advance the
block tiles based on um you know where
they're supposed to be at in
the uh in in the in the current block
right or or I guess in in in the current
thread this is where a lot of the magic
happens right here so this this part is
crucial pay attention to let's first go
over the easy stuff so thread results is
just like how big is that that little
square that thread is going to calculate
that's just going to be um this is going
to be 8 by 8
right we have this reg M term which we
saw in the blog post so reg m is this
and reg n is
that TM and TN right that's just going
to be the the little the I guess the the
iterations of the dot product so each
dot at each iteration of the of idx it's
going to store those in registers and
it's going to calculate them really
really fast right it's going to be like
it's going to be like eight it's going
to be like 8 by one and then a 1 by 8
and it's just going to evolve that
way now we look up at
these
so in a row a so we just essentially
have the thread index and we divide that
by BK
right in a row same idea but we use the
mod oper
then we have this new term called a
stride right and now we're actually
going to do the math we're going to do
the math for a stride
here so so stride
a stride a is going to be number of
threads per block tile which is 256
divid by BK which in this case
is8 so here if you divide this out you
end up getting
32 so our stride a is going to be 32
right my marker is a little weird let's
pay attention to that term
um and then we have this other stride
down here stride B is the same thing but
instead of dividing by BK we divide by
BN so BN is actually
128 so if we divide 256
right
128 the answer is
two now these are going to be important
these are going to be very important as
we sort of Step through this so let's
jump down to this actual uh loop here
now so inside of a shared look at how we
Index this start starts here and ends
there we have this first thing in the
brackets which is uh inner row a so it's
going to be a certain row that we're
looking at plus a load offset right so
the load offset is going to iterate up
to BM which in this case is
128 so you can think of it as us having
this
um this is the a
tile
right and so this is going to
be this going to be
BM and that's going to be BK right so
inside of here we're going to iterate up
to BM in strides of stride a now stride
a is size 32 right stri a is 32 so if we
actually look at how many times it's
going to stride through this until it
reaches the end it's going to start at
zero and then it's going to go down to
32 I can
and then it's going to go down to
64 and then it's going to go down to uh
I believe
96 and then it's going to stop right
it's going to it's it's not going to
actually hit this it's going to stop
there so we're going to have this this
initial offet of zero and then it's
going to bump up to 32 in the next
iteration and it's going to jump to 64
and then 96 so notice the actual area
that we have to fill in here right
notice the actual area we have to fill
in so this
area
is
32 and then this BK we already know is
eight
right and it's going to be the same for
this and same for that and same for
that so this is actually where where
some really cool stuff comes in now this
this inner row a here this inner row a
is calculated as the thread idx divided
BK
right so this value if we do the math
here idx is say Max is out at
256 my marker I need to get
a 256 ID BK which is a right
now this number is going to max out at
32 and that's going to be our row right
so remember this if it's
32 this number this this inner row which
is based off of the thread itself is
going to max out at 32 now this inner
column on the other hand is going to do
mod BK right so when we do this it's
essentially going to it's going to go
like 0 1 2 3 all the way up to eight and
then once it hits eight again it's it's
going to jump rack zero and it's going
to reset so it's going to be like 0
through 8 and then reset 0 through 8 and
reset right and then we're going to have
these these rows uh the row index that
goes from 0 to 32 right so every time we
hit the next eight it's going to it's
going to bump up one
right and so this actually makes a lot
of sense so inside of here we have this
load offset which is going to be strided
by this much this 32 here and then we
add whatever this row offset is so we
have the row offset plus whatever that
number is we can effectively populate
this entire area here so it's like the
zero or the or say it's like I don't
know 64 and then plus whichever row it's
at from the thread index itself which we
which we calculate up here
um it's going to be that times the K
Dimension so it's that's why it's going
to stride over as many rows as it needs
to and it's going to end up at some
certain index and then once we multiply
that we know where it's at vertically
and then we simply add the inner column
index to that so the inner column index
like I said before is going to cap out
at 8 right so it's going to cap out at 8
and it's going to land somewhere here so
by doing this we only actually iterate
over this four times and each thread
spanning you know 32 * 8 CU if you
actually do 32 * 8 that's
like 2 5
2 5 is 32 and then uh two uh 2 the 3 is
8 so 5 + 3 with our exponent laws that's
2 to the 8 which is int 8 maps to 256
right so that that's how I kind of make
those associations you don't have to
follow along but 8 * 32 is
256 look how awesome that is each thread
is going to occupy an individual spot in
here so we're going to load this Chunk
in each thread is going to take a little
spot in there 32 * 8 and then we load in
the next one each thread takes its own
spot so it's like one operation for
every single iteration right so we don't
have to go sequentially through it each
thread is just boom done it's one
instruction same for this same for this
same for
this and then we just index accordingly
we just kind of adjust it so instead of
BK being the being the stride over you
know we do we times K so it's able to
stride over the entire thing when we're
actually loading from the GPU vram um
because it's it's actually bigger right
so the these matrices are much bigger
when we're when they aren't um tiles yet
so we have to stride like the whole K
distance instead of just the the the the
tile K
distance and then same idea applies to
um BS right the the the not BS
bshar
not not that
if I get up for a
second and look at what BS looks like
it's literally
this let me actually get a different
marker
terrible it's going to be like this go
down this way right that's what that's
what BS is going to look like now if we
look at if we look at these values
inside we have this load offset which is
going to iterate up to um up to up to BK
right and
BK is
this remember it's not it's not this
part anymore it's it's the side and then
this part is BN right because it's K byn
as the B Matrix
so when we when we iterate in these
strides it's actually going to end up
being um well BN in this case is 128 so
it's going to be this uh this stride
value is going to be um or stride B
sorry is going to be 256 / 128 which is
two right as we calculated um down
here so it's actually going to stride um
it's actually going to
stride it's going to stride two right
and two times the length of this is
actually a quarter right so if you have
eight values you have eight different
eight different rows you split it
once now you're in half and there's four
rows here and four rows there now if you
split it in half
again then you have two and two and two
and two all that that up adds up to
eight so when we actually stride we're
just going a quarter of the way down
same thing in here we go a quarter of
the way quarter quarter right same idea
applies here so whatever this stride
value is it's going to start at zero and
it's going to go up to six because it's
going to it's going to cap out at
um it's going to cap up at B whatever BK
was in this case is eight and it's just
going to stop so it's going to go 0 0 2
4 6 and it's going to stop right then we
have this inner row b which is from here
and this is just the same idea so inside
of this we have the thread idx um in
this case it it's just going to max out
at
256 and we divide that
number we divide that number by BN which
in this case is
128 and the column is the same idea it's
going to go zero all the way up to 128
and then it's going to reset right so
it's not just going to iterate every
time we stri 128 it's going to to uh
it's going to go up it's going to
essentially one mod 128 is one 127 28 is
127 right so that's that's literally all
it's going to do here
um in case you haven't noticed already
this is the same idea as here except
we're just dealing with kind of like a a
more like very stretched out thing
instead of instead of like these nice to
look at I candy looking blocks right so
the idea here is is that we just go
however much we need to in here CU this
this total thing is like 128 and 128
that totals up to 256 so it's
essentially each thread gets its own
little space in there one thread two
thread three thread four
thread right they all get their own
little piece in there and they're able
to load in quarters downwards right that
that's that's essentially how we're
loading into Shar memory so just given
this new context we're just loading um
you know we're just being clever about
how we load
things so given that we understand how
it's everything is loaded into share
memory we can go and jump into the next
part here and this part is like where
things get a little it's a little funny
it's not actually as as intuitive and
bad as this part um but it is still a
little bit weird with the indexing part
so if we jump into this it's we iterate
over this idx right and this idx going
back to this is literally just it's it's
going to evolve right so idx index0 1 2
and three right they're going they're
going inwards like this
uh one thread is in charge of this
little block at the center um and the
threat the each thread is is responsible
for uh loading in a column and a row
right one thread takes care of that
um now if we look inside of here we load
into the registers right so the
registers are the extremely fast pieces
of storage that are literally right next
to the core in in the in the GPU and so
we have this reg M right which is going
to load that column in so how do we load
this we have to look at this thread row
right and to understand everything else
let's go look at thread row here so
where is this thread row so it's the
thread ID x.x so this could be a maximum
of you know
256 and then we divide that by BN / TN
right so BN is 128 and TN is 8 so you
divide 128 by 8 and that's 16 so we have
256 divided or 0 to 255 and then
whichever one of those it is divide that
by 16 right so inside of this we end up
having 16 different numbers that could
we could be through right so if we look
at this original atile Here There are 16
different
um There are 16 different rows we could
be right and these are just offsets keep
in mind we're loading in columns that
are eight elements long so we have like
16 16 16 all the way down uh we have
this eight
times um
and each of these or no sorry 16 times
um each each each little column here
this little like colored in area you
could say that is going to be eight long
right so we essentially are loading in
like we go eight that's like that's like
a single um that is a single column and
then whichever one comes next it's like
this is another eight and we go all the
way down 16 times and that multiplies up
to the total length of M which is 128 so
the math is mathing um the same thing
applies to thread column right I mean
these are these are square matrices so
it's not actually too bad to deal with
this um so same idea here um and we end
up with some range between 0 and 50
right so if we go back
down thread row time TM so TM is
uh TM is which uh like TM is essentially
eight right so it's going to be
whichever thread row we're at so which
whichever one of these out of um out of
out of 16 are we
at and then times um times
TM plus I and I is going to be that
little iterator here that goes up to TM
right TM is like that the length of that
column or the like yeah you could say
the height or the the length of that
column it's going to iterate up to I and
it's going to put that into the register
M right we multiply this whole thing by
BK so that we get this offset going
because we have to go through this k
thing and reset every single time we
want to get a new column you can't just
go directly down you have to stride one
entire length over to get to the next
one and then we add idx to this so This
actually becomes very intuitive when we
look at it from a glance so hopefully
this is sort of hopefully this is sort
of making sense in your head um but this
idx is just going to evolve us it's
going to be that that horizontal offset
and then this is the vertical offset
right this whole portion here that's the
vertical offset
um and then we apply the same concept to
loading into register n right so let
register n isn't as bad um because we're
actually loading uh we're actually
loading horizontally so it's going to be
the idx which by the way idx is going
downwards now so idx times BN BN is the
length of it right so you're going to go
down um whichever idx you're at
um you're going to go down that many
layers and then you're going to do uh
whichever whichever thread column you're
at so each thread is going to have its
own uh it's going to have its own little
section of that right it's going to have
it own job cuz the thread is like
loading a specific a specific Square in
that tile so thread here thread here
thread here thread here it's like
yeah each thread has its own thing so
we're just worrying about a single
thread
um thread thread is like you know thread
one is like here and then thread 255 is
or thread zero is here and then thread
255 is here because it goes to like the
very edge and then the very edge and
then they intersect at 256 right that
that's how that's how I'm sort of
visualizing this now we have this extra
I term which is literally just the
horizontal offset so when you when
you've like looped around how many
whatever amount of do ID EXs you need
then you have that additional I which is
going to be the offset so you're going
to load in the first first element in
the row then the second then the third
then the fourth and then the same
applies for this column up here which we
already did it's just going to do 1 2 3
4 all the way down to eight right and
it's going to store this out in like a
register memory like a line and this
allows us to easily do product that
right so when we drop down to here um
this is the entire Loop yellow to Yellow
um we start off with the the M component
right so thread m is this part and then
thread n is this part so this this n
component is actually inside of it now
the thread result is calculated as res
idx M so whichever however much it is
through uh TM right that times TN which
is the which is the horizontal stride
that you need to do to get to the next
the next um the next row
right and then you have this TN as well
so TN is how how far along you are so
it's or sorry res idx is how far along
you are uh so this is going to be your
your vertical stride and then this is
going to be the horizontal offset right
so that's how that's we mean we're
storing it in linear memory but this is
this is how we're going to index into it
right and then we do whatever that is um
and this keep in mind this is an
individual um this an individual grid
right say you're you're looking at a
point within that grid you're doing um
essentially a DOT product across those
so you have to iterate through you know
eight and then eight again so it's 64
iterations you have to go through
filling up that entire tile um and then
you just use you know as you would
expect that that value whatever it is so
you're just essentially just crossing
them you're finding where they intersect
and then you're setting whatever this is
in that so it end is just becoming this
entire uh Matrix light out it's like
instead of being uh loaded like this you
just take this row and you attach it to
the end and then this attach it to there
and then this one it's even further
right that's all we're doing there so
it's like literally as you would imagine
in your head this is how it's working um
it's just it's just important to
actually highlight like what the
indexing is actually doing instead of
just trusting that it works it's really
important to actually dig deep into what
this is doing under the hood so I
encourage you if this doesn't entirely
make sense it's very intuitive I
encourage you to test it with your own
examples so even just like get a piece
of paper write down on a whiteboard
whatever you need to do um and just and
just sort of write this out and try to
visualize it through each step right so
you can even set for example TM to and
TN to four right you can make it much
easier on yourself you don't have to go
to the full extent that we're using with
you know our parameters like eight and
two 128 here you don't have to even go
that far you can be very simple about
how you exercise that
um but yeah so this is actually how we
calculate the the individual thread tile
so the This Thread tile this little 2D
thing inside of the bigger block tile
and we calculate one of those per thread
right so 256 threads are laid out um so
it's it's like 0 to 16 0 to I think
240 and then over here it's 256 that
that it might be like shifted based on
how you're seeing that the picture in my
hand waving but that's the idea is you
go from from0
to 256 right let me just make sure
everything is uh synced up you know we
make sure that all these are done um you
know as we're iterating through all
these all of these block tiles right we
have to go like on the on the bigger
matrices A and B we actually have to
take these tiles and we have to uh move
them closer together right so this is
what this whole Loop is doing we want to
make sure everything is synced up both
after the uh shared memory um population
so after we we we populate those we want
to sync everything and then once we've
written once we've written all the
results here we also want to sync
everything up make sure all the threads
are caught up before we you know evolve
to the next one and mess with stuff um
so then we have this write out um and
this isn't actually too bad this part's
pretty good so inside of here we iterate
over the same things that we did here
when we were actually calculating uh
when we were we were multiplying those
those thread rows and columns those
little thread
tiles and if we just step through this
this is actually going to seem a little
bit weird at first but if we scroll up
remember that we advance everything to
the starting position given this thread
right or given this block rather so we
have these initial terms which are the
blocks these are which tiles we which
tile we actually care about within C
and this is already stored here so we
already know which tile we actually want
to worry about and the the memory
address has gone through it's skipped a
bunch of
spaces through just like integer
operations it's been multiplied and
added up to the point where it's where
we want it and then we just do
everything from there so we can if we
stride like an entire length K it'll go
here and then the remainder of it and
it'll end up back to where it is but
just like one one element lower right so
that that's really all we're working
with here now if we scroll back down
it's literally just like this end term
that's that's like the end term um that
that's the that's the horizontal part
right so that's the part that we're
actually striding over so if we have um
we're looking at the C
Matrix we have thread row times thread M
right or or TM which is
8 plus the res index remember we it's
the same same idea as as uh as what we
did up
there and so
when we are
um it's essentially the same as this
except we're doing I instead so you know
I is you could think of i as like up to
um you know TM it's like the same idea
we're just iterating through that that's
going to be the um offset inside of that
tile right so like relative to
um relative to the actual SE tow that
we're working on this is going to be
like the relative off set right um so
that's going to be
downwards time n right so that's going
to give us our our downwards um our
downwards movement and then to progress
sideways we have the red column time TN
right so an individual thread um
individual thread
times times that uh that TN length of
eight right so essentially we're going
to have a bunch of uh a bunch of threads
occupying like a square and those
threads are going
to um or no not not the threads
occupying a square but they're going to
occupy the whole thing and then threads
are each thread is going to iterate
through that TM and TN right and so we
have this this vertical offset we have
the horizontal offset and then plus that
additional little kick to the right
we're going to iter this is how much we
need to actually like stride over like
how big steps we we take um and then the
initial just like inside of that inside
of like one of these steps it's like how
much do you actually go forward right
how much do you do you add to
it and then we just use what we've
already computed so thread results um
same indexing scheme here this should be
fairly intuitive um we just multiply
this element wise know for each
iteration in the loop and then we have
our beta times you know element wise
this which is literally the same same
indexing scheme that we use here so
hopefully the the block tent kernel
sense now we're going to jump into well
actually before we actually jump into
the uh vectorized kernel I want to run
this so if we go sjem we go sjem 04
right this is this is block ping
normal this is regular 1D block tiling
right then if we step this up to number
five look at this 4800 gig flops on 496
right that's decent but if we step it up
to five
we double
it so if we do uh python we go at
9162 /
4873 got about 1.9x speed up right which
is really good now we compare to the
results
here
um so about about this time 1.9 roughly
is it's pretty close to 70 right so I
mean we're we're essentially getting the
same results here uh so everything is
working out we just doubled the speed by
using 2D block tiling instead of 1D and
now we're already about 2/3 of the way
to kuo Performance we're actually really
really high up there so now let's go
ahead and continue with vectorized
memory access which is going to give us
an additional little performance boost
okay awesome so now we have this new
colel to worry about
number six on vectorizing the shared
memory loads so if we look inside of
here essentially we do this we
everything in here Remains the
Same except we have this new float 4
type right so notice how we have this
this float 4 I'm going to just highlight
that and see where it shows up so it
shows up here when we're loading
into uh when we are loading into shared
memory right so a shared and B shared
right this is where it comes up as well
as when we're writing out the results so
when we're going in from Global vram
into shared memory we use float for
loads and then when we're writing out
from registers we load uh we load with
float FL as well right this is what's
happening here now before diving in
right into this I want to go over and
review just like what the heck this
float board does there's a lot of terms
like reinterpret cast and all this all
this weird symbols and stuff so let's
just like go and clarify what this all
means I wrote a separate file here
called float for. cuu you can write the
same thing but I'm just going to go over
this kind of Step by Step so we have an
array length n right 1 3 4 all
floats we have a host input host output
we initialize device input and output we
K like those with n * size of float we
kud M Copy that from host to
device host to
device we we you launch this with a
uh with a grid size of one there's a
single block and within that block
there's a single thread so it's just one
thread that's actually being used here
now we run this and then we copy back
and then we display these based on their
indices right so 0 1 2 3 then 0 1 2 3
the inputs and the outputs and now what
actually happens inside of here is what
we want to pay attention to so we pass
this this device input and the device
output in right these are Pointers two
arrays um output as well now we have idx
which thread index in this case is going
to be zero right it goes from like zero
up to whatever the length is minus one
and so this is just going to be zero so
when we actually look at this this idx
pay attention don't don't worry about
this yet this idx is going to be Time 4
so 0 * 4 0 * 4 0 * 4 0 * 4 it's just
going to be 0 1 2 and three
right these are going to be our x y z
and W components now let's actually look
at what's happening here so this new
float 4 type it's part of the it's part
of the Cuda runtime it's part of the
well it's not part of the Cuda runtime
if we actually look at this it's part of
um x86 right Vector types we have this
float 4 we have a bunch of different
other Vector types that are device
built-ins so we can't actually um we
cannot actually uh see what these are
under the hood they just kind of work
for us U if I try to click on these
right it's just like that's really all
it is
so there's Parts in here a lot of this
is built in handled by the compiler Etc
and so when we break down what's
happening here um we notice that we have
a few parts we have this reinterpret
cast and Lally all this means is that
we're going to reinterpret as this uh in
in the actual instructions right so this
isn't going to manipulate memory or do
any data Transformations it's literally
just going to uh
reinterpret as a float 4 that's that's
what the it's going to tell the compiler
what to do right and this is going to be
a pointer to float 4 right so we're
we're transforming uh this essentially
so this is a memory address this ENT is
a memory address to whichever index
we're looking at so in this
case it's going to be you know idx * 4
in this case this is just going to be um
this is just going to be like idx is z
so it's going to be 0 uh 0 * 4 that's
just the beginning element right that's
literally all all this is is just um
we're we're doing input at index zero
and then we're uh we're getting the
memory address for that so it's the
memory address so the first element in
that entire array and then there's the
following memory addresses for for the
extra ones and then we uh we we we we
reinterpret this as a float for pointer
so we got the pointer the the memory
address here and we're reinterpreting
this as a float 4 pointer so we're just
going from pointer as a float to pointer
as a float 4 and the float 4 uh is just
going to contain essentially the
starting index plus an additional uh
three afterwards
right um and then we just have this
stored as as uh index zero uh for this
specific data type we don't want to be
you know redundant and take up extra
space so we're just going to index zero
and then the compiler is going to know
what to do with that later on um it's
just literally just going to be thex
component is going to be index0 Y is
going to be index one Z is two and then
W is three right so that's that's
literally how we have it laid out how we
have this thing laid out here and that's
literally all the all the float 4 data
type is so hope that that kind of makes
sense to you um you know when you read
complex uh when you read kind of like
complicated expressions like this it's
good to just break it down step by step
right so you have this like you have
this thing with its open and and it's
closed and then you have this thing with
it's open and it's closed then this
thing with it's open and it's closed you
just kind of see like you do like your
order of operations or simplified
however you want but yeah hopefully that
makes sense and if we can uh I'm
actually going
to
uh oh sjm CD into Source kernels and
then if we go and compile that into
float 4 we notice that we get everything
as expected right so 1 2 3 4 that is the
poost input so that's how we initialized
it here um and then the host output
which is um exactly how we want
everything to be stored um that is all
checking
out now this next kernel is really fun
uh it it plays around with some things
that are usually played around with and
toyed around with when you write really
really uh performance optimal crud
kernels right so the idea here is like
remember how when I showed you before
those uh we go back to here and uh I'm
going to step
out and go to SRC kernels and then we
did the we did this one and we saw
um we go up we saw the these um like
this load this this load instruction the
load. E and then there was like some
load uh 128 so like load 32s and then
load 128s right so that that's like the
whole that's the whole deal here is
we're going to try to make more of these
load
128s a single floating Point number is
32 bits and so if we um if we if we make
this like a vector type meaning
you know we just put multiple numbers
with each other in the same type then we
can have more and we can load more
things
so let's go ahead and actually jump back
to uh this part here and let's explain
like what the heck we're
doing
so in this one we are
essentially uh we're essentially taking
the a tile so it's like normally
vertical so it would be like tilted
downwards like the bottom would go here
and then this part would go right there
we're just transposing it
right and this transposing is going to
let us cheat a little bit um we still
get the same amount of memory in that
shared block except we index it
differently and this will allow us to
coass memory accesses right so normally
we would um if we go back up we would be
taking these and we would be advancing
to the right here but notice how
um for example like when we're actually
loading this in uh our threads are going
to be loading in um from like top to
bottom right so we're going to have like
a like threads essentially organized in
in different pieces and we're going to
be iterating downwards to populate this
right if you remember how we populated
it before um these axises were not CEST
but uh the B the B tile the B shared
tile um was CEST because our our threads
were uh loading horizontally so when our
threads we need like thread one thread 2
thread three thread four those are all
next to each other so Cuda is going to
go ahead and load those in um as a like
if you have four of them adjacent to
each other it's going to load all those
in as a single load operation instead of
four separate ones so that's what we're
aiming for here and the idea here is
instead of advancing instead of having
this vertical tile and then taking this
and advancing to the and like having idx
to the right it's going to be flipped
and we're going to iterate downward so
our threads are going to be paired like
this next to each other and it's going
to iterate downward right that's the
whole idea there um but what's even more
important isn't even how uh they iterate
downward that's just what the graphic
looks like what it's more so about is
how we actually um are able to load from
Global into shared right so how do we
take the a how do we take the a tile
just on its own and then load that into
shared and then populate it like this
right so we pop back to here we notice a
few things so first of all this is the
same this is the same this is the same
but these and these are different right
so if we pop down here just pay
attention to the inner rows and columns
for now so notice here how that this
this is actually very familiar but
notice how we don't actually have that
Loop so if we go back to uh block tiling
for example this two block tiling we
were loading uh in four Loops so we had
um BM was 128 long and then this load
offset would increase an increments of
32 and it would do four different
iterations of the four Loops totaling
totaling eight different iterations per
thread so each thread was doing eight
different instructions or I guess at the
high level eight different instructions
for uh for moving data
around and that's like kind of a
bottleneck a little bit so we can
actually speed that up and notice here
we don't actually have any Loops it's
literally just we store this temp
variable um this is doing this is done
once per thread by the way so this is
like once per thread um but we
essentially we go into we go into a we
get this inner row and we essentially
just we essentially just find um where
exactly uh where exactly this is at and
we're going to load this into shared
memory as if it's transposed right
so for
example I have this thing written on the
board here this is the a tile and I drew
a little section at the bottom with 1 2
3 and four these are four different
values that we're going to count as a
float four all right so when we actually
transpose this when we do a tile then
say t you might not be able to see all
those just don't worry about it um we
transposes and essentially we're like
flipping
over over this this dotted line here so
these are going to flip over they're
going to go from this
to this right those are going to flip
across that
line and they're going to end up like
that what you're going to have
is you're going to have when these when
these flip over they're going to be
ordered one two
I'm sorry bottom bottom I one two three
four
now don't worry too much about how these
are in uh how these are in like a column
format what we do care about is just
that we're loading these in a coest
manner right so notice how I've kind of
Taken like half of this tile here and
I've actually done this for a reason so
if we if we go ahead and look back at
what these inner rows and all this stuff
is saying it's essentially the same as
what we had um over over here in 2D
block tiling except instead of just BN
or BK it's that and then divide by four
right so I mean it's it's four for a
reason it's literally because we're just
we're just um we're using the float 4
type so if we're going to do uh thread
idx which in this case is going to max
out at
20 it's going to max out at um say
255 and then BK is 8 so it's going to be
8 / 4 which is 255 / 2 which gives us
the indices 0 to
127 now this one on the other hand
is going to be um same idea except we're
doing the mod right so 255 mod 2 that
means every two times it's going to
reset at zero again so we're just going
to have the two numbers zero and
one essentially this indexing allows us
to treat this as a group of four so when
we divide that means it's shrinking to a
fourth of its length and then when we go
down here and multiply by four again
which you'll kind of see the intuition
for in a second and when we multiply by
four again it's just going to stretch
that back out to what it normally used
to be so this is just considering uh
this little Flo float for indexing
scheme we have now if we pop down to
this here uh we can see that this I'm
actually purposely making this um match
our a tile here so notice how we have
this inner row a right and inner row a
is between 0 and 127 so the row for this
tile is between zero let me put this
here for now
Z and 127 right so you might not be able
to see that but 0 127 this is very long
this is like the longer side um and then
we have 0 to one so two values for the
for the column right column A so 0 to
one or or one rather and all this allows
us to do is just sort things more easily
so notice how we have like uh we have
this thing that's normally of size
128 by
8 and 128 by 8 if we actually do the
multiplication for that
um that's 1,24
right so
1,24 and and then reduce this number we
divide this one by four
right that actually reduces the whole
thing from 1024 to
256 guess how many threads we have 256
it works out perfectly so each thread is
essentially taking its own little one of
these right so this is going this is
spanning down 127 0 to 127 and this is
going 01 and which just like split in
half right so you have you have like 1 2
3 4 5 6 7 right eight and we're just
like splitting this in half and then
it's it's spanning the length uh
spanning spanning the height downwards
right and all we have to do is just
store this as a float so this is what we
do here we we literally uh take the
inner row we do that times case we need
to you know stride around and and get
back to the same to the same uh to the
same column again and then we do plus
the inner column A offset this is all in
context of like this a tile being
Advanced where it needs to be so we're
literally just adding K considering that
we're in this bigger Matrix right that's
all we need k for everything else is it
it just works because we're in the we're
just dealing relative to this specific
tile as a part of the whole bigger
Matrix now inner column we're actually
going to stretch this out back to four
again because uh because we previously
shrunk it right so we just need to
expand that back
again and this is just going to index um
in the old fashion style right where we
where we find the the vertical offset
meaning uh meaning here and then we add
that so vertical offset and then we plus
to the so we like we find which row we
want we multiply by the by the K term
and then we get where we want to get and
then we Plus for the horizontal offset
right and we ex we have to multiply by
four to like to actually uh span that
entire length right so if you wanted to
go to the very end of The Matrix um if
you want to go to the very end of The
Matrix here you'd actually have to take
this two term or whatever that is times
four and it would it would get you all
the way to the end right that's that's
the whole idea there um but if we go
into this look at the way we store these
right this isn't actually too bad so in
a shared we have these four different
they have these four different stor
which is each four different component
of the float 4 variable so we have this
x y z and W term this is the first one
index zero and then index one index 2
Etc right so all we're doing there is
we're looking at the inner column
whichever column that is keep in mind we
have this new tile of this shape we're
doing it relative to this because this
is how we've this is how we're storing
everything so we're going to go um the
inner
column whichever that is so in this case
the the column we have to keep in
context how we stored column for this
one the column in this case is which one
of these but since we
um since we transposed it we have to
consider the column in the context of
here right so it's actually a little bit
different so instead of having row as
this it's actually column because we
interpreted column from this originally
that that's kind of what's going on
there hopefully that's hopefully that's
easy to understand
um and then we have this times 4 which
is obviously we're going to stretch it
out as we need it to and then whichever
index we need to plus right we're
storing this as like a as like these
these vertical values right so instead
of horizontally laying them out we're
storing them vertically and this is why
you have this extra index here this one
this is going to be like the the the
column Offset you could say
um like which which sorry which yeah
like which row are you at rather and
then the the BM term that is just this
and then we move it over here so it's
going to stride across as many times as
it needs to and then we can add the just
inner row uh a part right so so the row
originally came from this part and now
we're just flipping it over to this side
so we get the actual offset there and
that's literally that's literally how we
store it it's like literally that easy
um
so then we go further and we look at b b
shouldn't actually be too hard I'm not
even going to explain this it's
literally like be we're just explicitly
adding memory cols uh memory coling here
like if I go back to this um what's it
called shouldn't the compiler just be
able to colest the second version and
generate the 128bit loads um the and
then the reason is that the compiler has
no way to verify that the float B
pointer is pass to the kernel um as as
128 bit aligned right which would be a
requirement for this so essentially
we're just saying like like in the in
the previous example where I showed all
the Shader assembly there might have
been some instances where it did not
actually know that it's okay to store as
a 128 bit right is it like a float Fort
like an implicitly 128bit align type um
but in this case we're explicitly
passing reinterpret uh cast and we're
we're explicitly setting it to to float
for or
128bit and that's promising the compiler
that this is aligned right this is
telling the compiler you can you can do
it what you need to with this we've set
this up properly work your
magic and we're just helping out the
compiler that way so that that's what's
happening here same like it's literally
this this identical indexing scheme um
not really much to to talk about here
but uh after this is all done keep in
mind this is done once per thread right
so we do we store and then we write
right right right
and it's just super fast right so don't
don't worry about the uh don't worry
about how we're writing this we don't
actually have to make the rights coess
so then the rights don't have to be um
you know adjacent like this they can be
uh separated like by
rows uh and then as long as the reads
are coess that's fine so the reads
coming from here and then we're just
we're just flipping it over and it's
Landing there which is
perfect and then we move on to actually
calculating the results of that little
of that little thread block the the
essentially the thread mini tile within
the bigger one and we iterate through
with normal. idx right s similar scheme
to what we had before except the
indexing scheme is a little bit
different um we remember how we we have
b as like this this rectangle where it's
like this is short and this is this is
long right a is the same way now now
that we've transposed it a is also like
this so instead of a being uh like this
it's now flipped over like this right
and so all we have to do is just change
up how we index it and that'll work so
I'm not even going to go over b b is
like very obvious understand but uh
going over a right how do we iterate
through this so idx right when we look
at this we go um so whichever whichever
index we're at we'll just disregard that
for now um we'll just say that's zero
maybe um and then this since this is
multiplying by zero that's going to
simplify to zero so it's going to
be uh zero plus and then we'll say uh
maybe
the whichever thread row it's at um
whichever thread row it's at is going
it's going to multiply by TM which is
eight so it's going to stride however
much it needs to right um
and then we simply add I to that right
so thread row instead of being here
thread row is actually here because it
was previously right you can see how
that translation works this was thread
row this was long this is thread row now
now this is long right so it's it's the
same idea it's we're just we're just
making the naming a little bit confusing
there that that's really all it is we're
just stay consistent with whatever this
term means because we have to transpose
it right um and then we just iterate
through through um through I as we need
to right
so this should be intuitive I don't
really think I need to explain that too
much it's just like mainly paying
attention to the uh the naming
convention so thread Row versus thread
column like why are those different um
that's because you you're uh
transposing and then you do the typical
write out um so if we go back to this uh
up this is all it's doing right right so
revolving idx
downward all of these all of these
threads are sort of next to each other
in memory that's why we're striding um
TM right TM is that
um this is TM so whichever thread row we
are at um we're going to stride TM
because each thread is going to take
care of multiple of those values
um and yeah we end up uh we end up just
just sort of looking this a bit
differently uh and
then yeah just just some more visual
examples instead of having it as like
here and then these these like inch
these like uh inch forward
it's right but this is actually switched
over so it's just kind of the
transposing spatial reasoning you have
to have to get through and then this all
like is pretty straightforward um but
yeah now we can actually pop over to the
the write out section awesome so we're
actually almost done we just have to
write out the results now and we have to
make sure that these our these are also
uh in this Flo float for types so also
uh colest into uh the the uh global view
Ram right so we have the the normal um
iterate over TM and iterate over TN
except we change the iterators a bit
differently so in TM the rows we're
iterating over we're we're doing we're
iterating up one each time so it's going
to go one one one one one right and then
for TN we're going plus 4 each time so
we have eight values here and we have um
we have two values here right so when
you have this total 8 by8 thing you
would normally have to do 64 values but
because we're doing float 4 We're
storing four of those times 16 total
right so you can kind of do the math
it's like four values time 16 different
uh rights um so it's going to do four
values each right for 16 of them and
we're going to pop full that full 64
thing across the TM and and TN tile
right um so we we set this temporary
variable as the current uh C the C the
current C value right so this whatever
uh whatever the the the current C is
that we care about relative to how we've
indexed through these right and this is
all keeping in mind to where we are
actually at in the entire in the entire
C Matrix the entire C Matrix right so
the the thread row offset times this
plus the res idx um M offset and then
all of that times n which is the stride
of that and then plus our our columns
time TN and then our res idx n this
should all make sense this indexing
should be like pretty much Crystal Clear
um we've we've done very similar to this
already
um and a lot of the syntax is also
similar to this float 4 we did here so
if something doesn't make sense just
look back at this and break things down
again that's the easiest way to do it um
but in here we have this we have this
temp type right and now temp keep in
mind this is what C originally was so we
can actually store uh things from the
existing uh TMP or the temp variable
inside of it against we can actually do
more to and then right back inside of it
cuz we don't care about the old C result
we just want to calculate the new one
right so we have this thisx part which
is the index zero so we're not going to
add anything and then index one and then
two and then three these are all x y z w
respectively uh so we have this Alpha
term the thread results which is with
with respect to the thread results uh
variable in the register so it's going
to be the res index M so which which row
are you at right and then the um and
then TN which is which is how that spans
so you're going to stride over and get
to whichever row you want then you're
going to offsite offset by this and then
based on which Val which index you're at
within the float 4 array within that
specific the the float 4 window right
you're going to add uh these to the
actual uh memory addresses or the or the
index themselves right store it as like
kind of a vector type so uh this way we
can actually get the the value that we
want and then we simply just add that to
the beta scaler and then multiply that
by the existing C value as we got from
up here right so that should be very
straightforward um luckily this is only
in register so the indexing isn't too
complicated uh and then we simply just
write back right so using the same idea
that we did back here the same indexing
scheme uh and we simply uh write write
out c um on the level of threads that's
Factor memory
coing okay awesome so now uh we can
actually just print out how well these
do right so we just finished up the
vector the V col colest memory access uh
with vectorization kernel let's go ahead
and print that out how well does that do
so the last one was uh 2D block tiling
kernel number five we go and print this
out and we get a peak of about um 9,000
so about about 9100 gig flops and this
one
about 10,800 gigaflops which is quite a
big increase from before so that's about
what
roughly uh
1,600 more Giga flops than before which
is pretty solid right it's like a 15% 16
whatever perc increase in performance um
so now let's actually go ahead and print
like some more right uh I know the the
autot tuning one was good so we go print
this one did about 11,000 so relative to
this one it did you know moderately
better and then we can print out the
last one which was kublos so kublos was
supposed to be the fastest we can
actually see that this
11,496 is very close to the autotuned
kernel right so if we actually look back
to what we previously did which was
number six we are very close to coup
loss so 10,000 we'll just do 10,800
divided by
um 10,800 ID 11 uh
11,496 so we get about
94% uh kuo performance just using the uh
vectorized uh uh like the float 4
loading right so that's ridiculously
good and we can still optimize further
with these ones right so consider that
if we were to optimize these further and
maybe use um some additional tricks that
you'd find in like research papers like
this could actually get really really
fast right
so that's uh it's pretty cool that we
can do that just on our own hardware and
we can actually see it from start to
finish and understand it intuitively um
the reason I'm not going to go over
anymore is because it's just more and
more complexity to dig through as you go
through each one um and I want to save
some time for the last final project in
the course which we're going to do
shortly um but yeah I'm not going to
cover all of these I just kind of cover
the main ones so uh cols memory access
from from Global just like a bump up
from naive and then uh all the different
tiling variants and then how we can how
we can vectorize memory access
right so given that um let's actually go
ahead and print out the uh the assembly
instructions for this specific kernel so
if I pop out of here and go into Source
SL kernels do
nvcc PTX and then we
go number
six out and we can just go
Um number six.
PTX okay so instead of that uh I just
remember that we had this main file here
which we can reference so if I just go
ahead and save this if I like take the
the title of
this and I replace
I repl that in
here uh and then we go ahead and compile
we're going to get our actual uh PTX
instructions here
so uh it seems like we got some errors
which is because if I actually go in
here we have to copy this copy it
back oh we're getting
vim and
and so pretty much what happened there
was I had it imported properly but we
just weren't including the TN at the end
here so I just added that um and now it
now it's successfully uh compiled so we
get kernel. PTX we open this um and we
can go ahead and see um let's see if we
can find any the 128's aren't in here so
I actually have to go in and uh and
change this to Shader assembly we can go
ahead and do um
n BCC Das will do Arch is
SM oh Arch equals sore
86 and then we'll do Q
binary um main
dosc um and then out and we'll do it
main
main. Cuda binary and then we'll go
ahead and C object object dump
and we'll do main dot key binary just
like that we go ahead and move this
up and we can see that um if we look for
the specific ldg doe instruction ldg
do
128 128
1288 128
128 and so on and so forth so how cool
is that we can actually verify that all
of these
um may we can find like a 32 in here
somewhere oh that's just going to be in
uh that's a
register that's a register as well
that's a
register so we actually do not have any
32-bit loads any 32-bit transfers at all
everything is perfect
um everything is
great how
wonderful so now uh now that that kind
of makes sense that we are able to
literally see what the uh instructions
are looking like when we provide optim
optimizations um you know we can we can
actually we actually feel a lot more
confident in our ability it's not just
like me telling you that this works and
trusting it it's like you can actually
see it this is what is being uh this is
what's being run on the gpus controllers
the little microcontrollers inside that
issue the instructions
right and so if we pop back to here um
there's one little thing I wanted to
cover it's an extra optimization which
is using tensor cores so we go to
programming tensor cores um you
literally just search it's on the Nvidia
blog programming tensor cores in Cuda 9
so Cuda 9 um I mean we already actually
have I go here Nvidia SMI we're on Cuda
12.5 so that's fine we don't have to
worry about incompatibility issues um
but
essentially this gives the whole
instruction sets on how to use tensor
cores right so
um ca9 provides these new features these
tensor cores will essentially like for
example on the on the Volta architecture
you can you can do this where it's like
you multiply these two fp16 matrices and
then you add another one right the the
fuse multiply and add operation we saw
previously um except on the level of 4x4
tensors and these are supported in the
in the CU loss Library um so two tensor
two Cuda libraries that use tensor cores
are kublos and CNN right the ones we
ones we covered earlier kublos use
tensor course to speed up gem Matrix
multiply uh operations and CNN uses it
to speed up convolutions and rnns so
that's cool but what if we want to write
our own what if we want to write our own
code that isn't dependent on CU loss
right because CU loss we could just call
like a separate function but it might
not be as slow or we can't like fuse the
actual tensor core instructions with a
specific kernel that we want to do like
for example um flash attention right if
we wanted to write that kublos might not
let us do that because it's sort of
independent we can't include those calls
inside of kernels um so if we wanted to
actually look at how to use that um
where did it
go scroll down a little bit tensor
course and
CNN and then um programmatic access to
tensor cores and that's where ca 9.0
comes in so we're good um essentially
there's this new thing called a um the
complete namespace is NV and then in C++
it's like the the W the W
MMA um
this means warp Matrix multiply
accumulate which I'm not going to go
over like exactly what that means nor do
I entirely know what's happening under
the hood there but um that's that is the
tensor core uh operations that we can
call right so there's a bunch of
examples here I'm not going to go over
this part but uh this is just kind of
like a nice little um you know dock for
understanding how the heck to use tensor
core operations and you might you might
might even want to implement those
inside of the block tiling kernel right
so the ones that we just wrote you might
want to say take like a single thread
and have like a thread or a piece of it
and try to like block these actual
tensor core operations right and make
these really really fast so that way
it's not just so that way it's not
iterating through eight and then
iterating through eight more and having
64 total operations to do but rather
just having one right so these are
literally going to be organized in a 3D
structure inside of the tensor cores on
the the GPU um and it's it's literally
just like a a 3D thing or a 2d thing
depending on how big Dimensions you're
using um because you can do like batch
by uh Time by Channel if you're using
Transformers or you can do
um yeah just there there is there is a
lot going on in the hardware but you can
actually you can capitalize on those so
anyways I'm not going to ramble on this
is this is tensor cores uh you have
permission have fun with this um I
encourage you to do so I might add some
more to this course later on in the
GitHub repo that'll you know sort of
talk more about tensor course but this
is
it okay so we can finally take a
breather now matrix multiplication is
pretty much finished um there's there's
a little bit more that we'll do later on
but for now you can consider matrix
multiplication finished for the next
section or two um now we go into Triton
which essentially takes the previous uh
takes the previous chapter and says
let's abstract that and make it easier
to use um so so taking uh you know
matrix multiplication or like tiled
optimizations where you're tiling things
into blocks and then you know
multiplying them together more
efficiently we can actually take that
and do it in Python with much simpler
syntax so this is Triton
um Triton is a bit different than Cuda
all right so before I actually go into
the the whole design here and what
Triton is about I want you to pay
attention to something so if I go pip
install
torch you'll see that we get all of
these all these all this Nvidia stuff
which we've seen before and then we get
this Triton Triton 3.0 right and Triton
is used by pie torch under the hood or
accelerating and making things faster
with python syntax right Tron is also
fast just like Cuda and so there there
are some differences between them which
I thought I should highlight um so if we
pop over to the uh pop over to the
Triton website search up Triton doc or
Trident website or whatever uh this will
come up they also have a GitHub as well
so the GitHub has you know a lot of uh
you know useful stuff um yeah just
playing around with it so setting up
configuring tridon doing custom things
uh but you can just PP install tridon
like that and it'll work the same way um
but if you do look at at the Triton
website you'll see a bunch of sections
so like how do you install it um
tutorials on how to use Triton so
there's like a bunch here which I don't
necessarily cover in this course but you
can you can go over more of these uh if
you want to um and then there's the
important ones that we care about so
Triton um what are like the Triton docs
there's like jit autotune heris all that
um just going
through going through
functions um and then we get into Triton
language which is the most important
part of all um we have a bunch of
different operations here with tridon
and I'll go into the whole design of
Tron in a second here but this it just
like makes it really easy to see that
all of the operations are right here so
um like the programming model uh
operations to know creation Ops um so if
you have like a if you have an X tensor
and you want to make a y but you don't
want to populate it with anything or you
just want to make it zeros you can say
zeros like right as a creation um shape
manipulation linear algebra so dot
product
um pointer Ops uh memory pointer Ops
bunch of things math there's a lot of
math Ops reduction Ops so like maximum
or you have an array and you're trying
to find the maximum of it and you reduce
it to just returning a single
value uh scan and swort operations
atomics like we went on previously
random number generation and Etc right
there's there's a lot here even even uh
debugging and printing too so try and
this is this is where all of the
operations are that you're going to find
um which makes this really easy to go
through um but if we go through uh where
is it introduction yes so the whole idea
here and if I go to uh Triton
paper yes this one so I'll look at this
in a second here but this is essentially
what Triton was inspired by is this this
paper here for tille neural net
computations like we went on in the
previous chapter right um and and this
this is the whole idea here is you have
scalar Pro Cuda has a scalar program and
block threads versus Trent which has a
block program and scal threads it's like
okay what does this mean this is super
weird um there's a lot of like geometry
happening here so like how do we
actually break this down
um
now to clarify the reason why Cuda is a
scale scalar program with block threads
is because you write a kernel to operate
at the level of threads or scalers in
this case so that's why it's a scaler
program each individual kernel runs on a
thread um but you need to be aware you
need to be implicitly aware that those
kernels also operate on the level of
groups too so when you have uh like for
example shared memory like that's
something you need to worry about right
um Cuda
has Cuda has blocked threads so scalar
program it's like the actual kernel that
you write and then block threads with
the idea of when you actually write the
the kernel itself which runs on a thread
it has to be aware of of all the other
threads too that that's kind of what I'm
getting out there and then Triton is
abstracted up to thread blocks so
um this this essentially means compiler
takes care of all these thread level
operations uh for us so when you write
something in Triton instead of having it
run on each individual thread and have
them communicate and be aware of that
it's going to write on the level of
blocks and all of those like thread
level instructions and optimizations are
going to be handled by the compiler for
you so you don't have to actually worry
about those um
and then when we talk about um when we
talk
about when we talk about scalar threads
it means you don't have to be uh as
worried about them talking inter uh like
interconnected with each other you don't
have to be aware because Cuda actually
handles that part so since you're
writing on the level of blocks you don't
actually have to worry about interthread
Communications you just have to worry
about what exactly the block is doing um
write the oper out clearly for that and
then TR will actually handle that under
the hood so you saw how um there's
there's very little operations in the
tron do language section this is because
the compiler is able to handle a lot of
the additional operations that that
allow for for performance increases
right um so so that's that's the whole
idea behind um that's the whole idea
behind Triton and that whole uh blocked
versus scalar uh blocked versus blocked
and scalar thread
philosophy
so why can't we just skip Cuda and go
straight to Triton why can't we do this
well Tron is an abstraction on top of
Cuda so you have lower level stuff that
offers optimizations and that you can be
explicit about to the Nvidia compiler
the
nbcc um and Triton takes advantage of
those and bumps it up a few layers uh to
something that you can sort of
understand easily and and write less
boiler plate code for so we still need
to understand how Cuda Works to ensure
that we're applying the right
optimizations you can't naively write
Triton code without knowing uh what's
going on on a low level it just helps
helps you prevent boiler plate
um you also may want to optimize your
own kernels in Cuda right so going back
to what I said before you kind of need
to know the low LEL operations uh in
order to make sure that everything is
working as intended right um and if you
want to build on top of Tri or build
things like it or abstract above Cuda
which is shr you you need to learn Cuda
you need to understand what is Cuda
doing so that you can build on top of it
so you can Leverage What it contains
already right
um and so if we go to the Triton paper
here Intermediate Language and compiler
for tile neuronet
computations that this is It's
essentially just
um
it it does everything that kublos and
and CNN does but does it um roughly as
fast and without a ton of boiler plate
so that that's like the whole idea is
you have these tiled computations that
you have to do in kublos and cdnn and it
takes care of those so I'm not going to
go through this um this is like this is
a separate course going through all of
Triton but we're we're going to go over
like how how do the basics work right so
that you understand um how Triton can be
applied um and maybe it'll give you some
ideas as to what to do later on okay so
now we actually go into an example of a
vector Edition kernel in Trine all right
so I'm going to try to break this down
as kind of as as efficiently as possible
uh this stuff isn't too hard it's
supposed to be kind of a break from
doing uh things like matrix
multiplication so uh you you'll you'll
probably find this you'll probably find
this is a end up end up being you'll
probably find this ends up being a
breeze uh so we start off you know we
import torch so Triton is very closely
linked with torch uh so we we end up
using that to to handle some other stuff
like initialize arrays and matrices and
stuff we import Triton the Triton
language and then shorthand version of
that and then we go down further um we
initialize uh a seed so that the results
are reproducible when we when you
randomly initialize stuff um to ensure
that you know we don't get errors or
whatever it's a good practice and then
we have a size of 2 to the 25 so if we
go into here we go
uh this is 33 million elements long
right so if we go
this 33.5 million elements
long um and then we just initialize our
X and Y the two two that we're going to
add on device that are randomly randomly
initialized uh and then we just have
some benchmarking stuff down here don't
worry about this this is just for
testing and and seeing how perform which
we which we'll see in a second here um
but going up when we're actually adding
them together this is when you when you
do um when you're actually adding them
you're going to add X and Y which are
tensors and then you're going to return
a tensor right so it's just X Plus y
return output that's it very simple um
this is essentially uh an easier way of
doing Cuda Malik so instead of Cuda
Malik and C or or CA c c C++ you're
going to go tor. empty like so it's
going to have the same shape as X but
it's going to be populated with zeros uh
we do an assert so we make sure all of
our all of our tensors are on the
device we set num elements to literally
just num elements of the output so how
many what is like the length of this
array um and then we have this weird uh
configuration of uh of like how we how
we actually launch a kernel and how we
Define like the the dim three and and
the grid size and all that stuff um so
we have a Lambda function here don't
worry about this too much by the way
this this you care about performance not
not like understanding how the syntax
Works under the hood um but this is a
just a Lambda function and inside of
here all like all you have to worry
about is that we're doing a ceiling
division of n elements so let's say n
elements is like24 you have an array
1024 elements and you want to add them
together in blocks and your block size
is 256 so what you would do is you would
par that 1024 over four different blocks
of size 256 right but if you have say
1,25 elements then you want to make sure
that you give it an extra block so that
it doesn't miss that element right or
else you're not going to get the right
answer so you have to actually do a
ceiling div um so that it rounds up to
five blocks instead of just rounding
back down to four because then you'll
end up missing that extra one right uh
so that's all we're doing here um and
then just to launch the kernel you I
know it's you do like this this this uh
this function and then you index with
this grid term and then you pass in your
variables after it's like hm that's
weird um but don't don't don't worry
about this too much so we just pass in
the grid as like that uh those like
those like alligator symbols um that's
that's all this is that's your kernel
launch configuration and then you have
the actual parameters themselves so
instead of going
we just
go we just do that very so it's it's
like a syntactical thing
right
um anyways that's that that that
shouldn't be too much of a question I'm
I'm not going over this because we care
about performance as opposed to like
what the heck what the heck all these
what the heck the syntax is um but yeah
so so going up to the actual mechanics
of a kernel inen and comparing that sort
of side by side with with Cuda um we
have we have
X we have we have to actually I forgot
to say we add this Tron jet decorator at
the top to say that we want it to we
want it to be jet compiled by tridon
just like be aware of that CU if you
don't add this you're going to get
errors um but for all the different
variables you know you have your X and Y
your output your Nom elements and then
the block size um which you you know
pass into here XY output output elements
and elements block
size now we have these as pointers
because in memory it's going to be it's
going to be laid out as the the first
element in that array is going to or
essentially this this pointer is going
to be the first element in that array so
you want to start from the you want to
base it off of the start of that entire
tensor or array and you want to continue
from there right so that's how Triton is
going to interpret that uh and then you
do the same for uh y output pointer um
and then we just continue on
so so jumping down a little bit we see
uh p and so P essentially says which
which block are we add in the grid right
um now we have to be careful about this
so a a good way to think about which
block we are in the grid is to actually
go down to here and see how does this
apply right so when we're actually in
this array um let's say block size is 64
and we have 256 elements in this array
um you don't want to just say zero or
one or two cuz those are going to be
individual elements right when we're
looking at the actual data cuz remember
this is how we're actually indexing data
we want to make sure that uh we're
keeping this block length in mind CU
block size is Big right so we're going
to advance
um block size times the number of blocks
and then the offsets are actually what's
important so it's like whatever that
number is and then we're going to
arrange an additional thing of 02 block
size so for like say 64 to 128 you're
going to start start the block start is
going to be 64 and then we're going to
arrange a bunch of different uh indices
between 64 uh which essentially just
going to be an array of 64 up to one up
to 128 right and uh that's going to
that's how we're going to index our data
so we do Triton language. a range zero
to block size and that's what that is
and then we just add whatever block
start is to that so hopefully that kind
of like makes sense in your head now
jumping back to P here you might want to
pay attention attention to this term so
in here we have axis and Builder don't
worry about this just worry about axis
so axis is like uh block idx dox right
um block block like X is the same as
axis zero a uh block idx Y is the same
as axis one and Z is equal to three
right so we have to keep this in mind
when we're writing more like you know 2D
you know 3D spatial uh kernels then we
have to keep in mind this access term so
luckily right now this is very simple
but this is something we're going to
want to keep in mind if if would you end
up writing uh this is something you want
to keep in mind if you end up writing uh
more you know 2D 3D stuff um now going
down a little bit um we have this mask
term so mask equals
offsets mask equals whatever the Boolean
uh I guess the the the Boolean output of
whatever uh of if offsets is less than
num elements so what this essentially
does is we have these offsets which are
the indices in the actual arrays itself
so the input and the output Point input
sorry the X and Y pointers whichever
indices we're at in those we want to
make sure that those do not surpass uh
we don't we want to make sure those
don't do not equal to or uh pass num
elements right it's going to be zero up
to num elements minus one so we want to
make sure that we mask everything off
that is num elements or past that point
right and that's what this is so mask is
just going to be essentially an array
it's going to do uh like it's
essentially going to uh say you know we
have all these offsets we have this
giant like array in memory and we're
going to see um if like we have a you
know 64 65 67 122 whatever we want to
make sure that those numbers are less
than a numb elements right um so we want
to essentially just making sure that
we're not accessing something that's
outside of uh our data structure in
memory we have this whole Space we want
to keep it masked to this one section
right that's what this does and so we
get a new array which is mask and that's
just a bunch of essentially just a bunch
of ones and zeros um and this this
behaves the same way that this if
statement does inside of an addition
Vector Edition kernel in Cuda right same
idea um now going down further um we
actually load these efficiently into a
shared memory so don't
um don't worry about how it actually how
Triton handles data how how it you know
transfers data that's a that's an
optimization that's taken care of for
you so just assume that these are going
to load in um like starting from the
like the beginning of X up to
um up to the end so it's going to
essentially just each each point each
point in memory it's going to each each
data point in memory it's going to load
those in and it's going to do a mask and
it's going to say do we want to actually
compute these values or not that's what
this is doing so whichever point it
starts at all the way up to all the
different offsets so it's like this
point and then it's copied and then all
the different offsets um and then you
have a mask applied to those as well to
say which ones do we want want to
compute so if these ones are like extra
just like compute this section um that
that's what that's what this uh load is
going to do and it's going to
efficiently load this into um shared
memory so the the the fast memory on the
GPU the one on the actual uh streaming
multiprocessor that that's what that's
what this is taking care of for you and
then we do the exact same thing for y
now try and Implement um these blockwise
operations very efficiently so you don't
actually need to do any advanced stuff
you literally just um have these loaded
onto SRAM and it'll do a uh element wise
addition so it'll it'll go through each
one and just add together and notice how
this is blue instead of red that means
like it's taking care of by uh Tron for
us so um that's that's literally how you
compute the output um and then we just
store this back again with another um
you know with another with another data
transfer operation
find and so that's just going to be the
same idea as here so uh the starting
place in memory plus you know the offset
of all the offset indices for for that
block
um the output itself so we're going to
just store the output
um and then have this mask as we did
here and that's how a tri kernel works
so hopefully this makes sense feel free
to rewatch some parts if they didn't
entirely you know click in your head uh
but now we're actually going to jump
into the uh softmax Trident function
okay so now we jump into softmax and
instead of just jumping right into code
I'm going to do a manual like hand
example with this
um
so let
me delete that real quick um essentially
what we're doing here I have a C file
we're just doing this in C to understand
what it's doing intuitively um we have
an array of floats 1 to three so it it
literally just looks like this um
x x is that and so we're going to
calculate the soft Max of
X
um so how this typically goes is if we
search this up on uh on
Google soft Max activation function it
looks like this right so you have this
exponentiate this input so you have an
input Vector um and this this this
symbol is a softmax function and you go
over each one uh and then you
essentially see how much each
exponentiated value contributes to the
total uh the total sum of all the
exponential all the exponentiated values
right so if we do if we open here uh if
I just open I
python if we import math and go say we
go math.exp of
1.0 we're going to get 2.71 because
that's what e is right it's going to be
e to the 1 um so our first
value is going to be
uh
2.71 and then the second
one is going to be two so 7 say
7.39 and then the third one number uh
three is going to be 20.1
roughly now we sum these Al together
so it's trying to autocomplete for me
2.71 +
7.39 + 20.1 0 and we get
30.2 right now in order to get the
actual softmax output we see how much
each of these each of these
exponentiated values contributes to the
exponentiated sum of all of them um well
not exponentiated sum but when you
exponentiate all of them you take the
sum of those which is 32.2 or 30.2 and
then you you see how much each
contributes so
2.71 / 30.2 so that about 9% roughly so
we're going to go um
0.09
um and then we go
7.39 is
0.24 and then the last one's going to be
67 if we go and do it
uh if you round up it's 67 so you have
that right and then if we add these all
these numbers together 0.0 09 + 0.24 +
0.67 you get 1.0 right and these are all
rounded of course um but but but the
point here is this is the softmax notice
how we had this this initial
distribution here and then we went to a
new one which kind of just made
everything add up to one and uh gave it
a bit of gave it a bit of extra weight
to the three right so notice how like a
like three is three times that
1.0 um the
6.67 is way more than 3 times uh 0.09 so
you kind of have that extra waiting for
the bigger values right and that's what
the softmax does um so it's going to
like essentially find like the biggest
number and and um put a lot of weight on
it or highlight it the
most um but there is a flaw with this
approach and I'm going to explain this
right now so essentially the flaw here
is if you have say um if you have
X as say
1,000
zero
and
uh negative 1,000 right so some of these
the sum of these is zero right you have
you have a problem with that and and
that essentially means this is is going
to um this is going to contribute a big
chunk of this or at least it's supposed
to It's supposed to contribute all of it
um but it's not going to because you
cannot contribute like it just doesn't
make sense how can you contribute like
what what percentage does a th
contribute to zero it's like Infinity
right so if you end up doing softmax on
this um like even if you try to math.
exp of 1,000 you're going to get math
out of overflow error math range error
because it's just too big of a number
right
so what you can actually do is you can
subtract by the max of of all of these
right so we can see
um what is the maximum uh what is the
maximum number here so the biggest one
is a th and so what we can do is we can
subtract each number by that value so we
go we can say x we'll just say like X2
equals
um
0 and then 0 - 1,000
is th000 and then 1,00 minus th000 is
2,000 right and so if we go
um we go math.exp of
zero notice we get one
math. exp of 1000 is going to give us
well pretty close to zero it's not quite
going to be zero but it's going to be
very very it's going to be a very small
number right and then of course the same
thing with 2,000 is just going to be the
same right it's going to be very small
and so you notice how if we if we
originally just if we just did this one
normally using these big numbers would
have actually given us errors so we can
subtract by the max we can we can um
you know pointwise subtract by the max
number and then we get something that
makes more sense so you know zero
contributes to all of it because that's
what the that's what the the sum
is and so this is how we actually follow
through in the softmax function in C so
we have three separate for Loops here
the first one finds the max value in the
array so we just set the initial max
value to be the first number and then we
iterate through this uh starting at the
next number we don't want to start at
the first we don't want to start at the
first one we started the one after it
cuz we already we already know what this
one is um and we essentially just
compare if if the new one is bigger than
the max we set the max to that one um
and we end up with this this Max term
which you know same as we did up here
and then we have this we have the
accumulation sum so we iterate through
the length of the array and we do that
index minus the maximum and then we we
add that total to the sum right we we
add whatever this was to the sum so that
we can you know accumulate all of it and
then we just write out
um we just write out the same value we
we essentially just take the input and
then replace it one by one uh and we set
it to uh whatever that exponentiated
value is uh
minus uh or sorry not minus but we we
have that exponen exponentiated value we
divide that by the sum uh very simple I
probably could have explained that in in
a bit shorter time but I just want you
to like gain the int intuition for that
you've probably already written the soft
Max and Pi torch and nump I get that uh
but just to kind of provide that review
as to how it works under the hood and
this uh you know numerical stability
add-on we have um so
now I have an example in uh Cuda as well
so I'm not going to go over this um but
the idea here is uh in Cuda mean yes you
could just you could do
um you could go over you know the length
of one single array but in deep learning
you're not actually trying to do that
you're typically going to have a batch
size and this batch size is going to
have like a bunch of these it's going to
be a batch of arrays that you're going
to softmax right and you're going to do
the softmax on them rowwise you're going
to do here here here uh right instead of
just like to each element so it's going
to go through the rows and this is where
we can actually get a speed up from Cuda
because we can give each each of the
threads we know we have batch size many
threads and we give each of them uh we
give each of them a softmax job right so
we see in
here
how we see in here how we actually give
one to each um we we we give each we
give each thread a separate softmax drop
that's going to go it's going to span
1,24 iterations or goes up to the length
of n right as we can see in these so
like theoretically it's going to take 3
n iteration because has to go three
different for Loops um that's that's
kind of how that works there so we want
to we want to pay attention to batch
sizes right um but there's there's an
example in in Cuda here which you can
look over on your own and and get an in
intuition for the batch St Max but it's
very similar to the one we didn't
see now we jump into the one in Triton
okay so now we actually go into the uh
softmax Trion kernel itself uh a little
bit more advanced in Vector Edition but
we're going to go through step by step
so we obviously import at the top I'm
going to go sort of from the bottom here
explain what's happening and then what
we're going as we're calculating the the
output um so we set our manual seed we
make a random uh normally
uh normally distributed random tensor of
floats um so mean zero and variance one
so it's a normal distribution and all of
the uh essentially the shape is is batch
size by um by n so B by n batch size is
256 n is 1,24 elements long we're just
going to softmax um those 1024 element
rows uh and we're going to do this on
Cuda now we're going to calculate and
make sure that torch and TR now put the
same thing so typically you would do
torch. softmax or or f. soft Max or
whatever and then you would go um Dem
equals 1 right and then we want to do
that same thing for Trident and then
make sure that um you know the max value
isn't too ridiculous we're going to
print that out then we're going to make
sure that this is this is all close with
torch all close right um so we do the
Triton Triton softmax we go
here and in here we have uh rows and
columns so when we print out um I'm just
going to print out uh input shape so we
go here
input shape is as we want right
um output we're just going to do a malic
essentially right there and then uh
instead of doing some weird like meta
parameter uh like doing like the whole
like Lambda function calculating we're
just going to do Tron and then next
power of two so what this says is it
Returns the smallest Power of Two
greater than or equal to n so similar to
what we were doing before but just a
little simpler um and then we're going
to we're going to set block size equal
to the minimum of 1024 and this right um
so you can kind of see how we you can
kind of see why we why we would do that
now we set our grid to n rows because in
our grid we want a block for each row
right when we're processing in parallel
we want we we can't uh we can't split a
single row amongst multiple um or at
least naively we can't split it across
multiple threads so we' want to do it uh
for each block so each different um each
different row would get its own block
essentially and that's how we launch the
grid here um and then you could assume
that you know why we have this um why we
have this trailing is just that the the
trailing Dimensions you can just assume
are one right and so that's how like Pi
torch shap shapes work if you do like
batch comma it'll be like B by one and
so it'll just be like a column Vector
sort of you you could think of it that
way uh and then the softmax kernel we do
this we call this the same way as we did
Vector ad except we add two more things
in so we add in this x. stride this this
is just an input parameter to what
what's going to be upstairs here so we
got x. stride which is the essentially
the The Stride of of the row so we when
we um when we go across it's like it's
stacked in memory it's like Row one row
two Row three row four right um but the
stride is like how far do you have to go
to wrap around to a new one so when we
say we want to go to row four um you
actually have to go okay well what is
the what is the strride right how long
do you have to go across to get to the
next one it's like essentially the
length um and that's you know we we we
we could say n columns but we're just
going to use the um you know objective
attribute x. stride
um passing and columns and then block
size right so we go up and we see that
we get the uh where did it
go output X stride stride and columns
and then block size uh output
input stride stride and columns block
size now we do the same we we we do the
same like pram ID and and the the start
pointers the same way
um we calculate this normally so which
block are we at right and then we have
to advance a number of indices forward
in memory so it's like we we essentially
we take the initial uh input pointer so
where does it start at where does where
does a starting place in memory and then
uh we add that
to we we we take that and then we plus
uh row idx so which row is it times the
length of the row right so then we can
get which row where is the starting row
within that batch right so which row do
we want to go to and then this whole
thing is actually in the bigger picture
which is the whole memory right that's
that's what we're doing there and then
same idea for the output uh start
pointer so we're essentially just
finding the place in memory where we
start based on based on these three um
and then we load in so uh you know we do
the typical load so uh pointer and then
we want to uh load in all of the indices
so similar to how we were doing it
before and then our mask is uh we're
just going to make sure that this is
smaller than n columns um right making
sure that we don't go out of bounds and
then this this important term other is
is a bit critical as
well so
this other term means that if you have
um for
example if you have 1,000 elements in a
row and the block size is24 so it's
going to be a bit longer um then that
means you're going to process some
additional elements it's going to think
that there's 24 extra ones at the end so
what you can do I mean this is not this
is not going to happen in our case
because we've very objective about how
we Define things but in some cases this
will be important to pay attention to
where um you actually want to explicitly
set the edge so that it doesn't mess up
everything else right if that was like
one for example then in our whole
softmax calculation that would
contribute to it quite significantly
because it's you know it's it's not just
like massive sparse integers it's like a
it's like decimal places that are around
zero right um so it's important to do
this when when we exponentiate when you
do
um if we go into uh python here
import uh import math we go Um can just
say
x xal negative float and then
INF
right and then we go um math.exp
X we notice that we get zero right where
we we did math. exp of one we would get
we would get this number so we just want
to make sure that that is not
contributing anything at all that that's
all we're doing there
um so all the other additional values if
they happen we don't want those to
contribute at all just kind of a safety
thing it's good to look out for this um
and then we just do the the the normal s
softmax calculation which is actually
only takes four lines um so we calculate
the max across across you know that row
and then we get the numerator which is
remember we we subtract the Max from
that uh we exponentiate this so we
exponentiate whatever that whatever that
result
is and then we get the denominator which
is a sum
across each individual each individual
one so there there's going to be some
sum number and then we're going to do
essentially this array it's going to be
an array of elements and we're going to
divide this by a scalar value so it's
going to just like take this and it's
going to divide divide divide divide
divide right and it's and that's how we
get our softmax output and then we'll
see that we store this
um similar to how we actually loaded
things in in initially so instead of the
row starting pointer it's the out row
starting pointer same idea um we want to
store a value which is the softmax
output which is what we calculated here
so that's the actual value uh inside of
it um and then our mask is same as as we
did up here so we we want to make sure
that we're not uh doing reads and wrs
out of bounds right and that's that's
pretty much the entire softx calculation
in Triton so you know I encourage you to
uh you know play around with this you
can do you can actually do
um you can actually
go uh t. device print and then we can go
um like P and then just put like row idx
or we could
do row idx like this
and we can actually print that
out so you know maximum difference
between TR TR pytorch and Tron results
is is very small results are close is
true um and then we can see each each
individual one of these so like P ID is
you know 255 this is in the X Dimension
right so if you had like a you had like
a
um this is Axis so we do axis Z same
thing we access of one then you know
this would be on this on this spot
instead of instead of X
right so yeah we we print out whatever
that value is and we get uh we we can
print stuff out in the terminal if I do
like normal just like
save now it might be a good idea to
actually dig into pytorch or not even
dig into it but rather understand how
you can add on top of it make things a
little bit faster uh for your own custom
use cases and whatnot so we just
finished off the Trident chapter uh I
hope you enjoyed that but now we're
going to go a little bit more into
Python and more on the torch side so
I've written a few files here I have
some descriptions about what's going on
uh what's going on with all these like
different types and names and stuff in
uh in the readme as well as some
intuitive examples of what we're going
to be looking at
I wrote a setup script for just
compiling a separate Pythor extension uh
a separate function that we're going to
use to do a polinomial it's very simple
operation um and then uh a Cuda script
that is going to uh compile and bind
into pytorch so that we can actually use
it um in Python and then the python
script itself which we Benchmark against
uh naive pytorch so just all we're
really doing here is x^2 + x + 1 that's
all we're doing so going here we have
this include and this is giving us
errors but don't worry about this uh
when we set up it's going to actually uh
it's going to handle this properly so we
don't actually need um a dedicated
include file or or any arguments for
this we don't need to specify where the
extension. H file is um but going into
the actual kernel itself um so just like
top to bottom we have this new thing
called a template I didn't go over this
yet but uh well I I did I I guess I did
in the uh in the manal section but uh
template
is it essentially if we go down it'll
help if if we kind of go down and and
look at where this supplies um so when
we call this kernel we do this and then
we provide our arguments right we have
the kernel configuration here and then
we have this this this is where the
template comes in so we specify this
scaler t type and that essentially means
um we're just going to make sure
that this uh the
X the y or the the input the output uh
are of this type and so this type is
essentially going to be handled by P
torch and instead of specifying like a
float or or a double or like I don't
know some other some other like maybe
quantize like fp16 type um it's going to
handle that for us and it's going to
just automatically recognize which one
it is and it's going to compile that
down and deal with it appropriately so
this is something built into py torch
and it's custom type that we have uh so
this is kind of just like the default to
use here um easiest and then we have
this restrict so restrict in short
essentially means we're not going to be
overlapping memory uh we're not going to
be overlapping memory accesses so we
have uh we have X here we have an output
here all we're doing is we're doing an
operation on this thing and then we're
storing that in here um we're not we're
not mixing things over we're not doing
two things on like the same location and
then having some output that's stored
we're not doing anything messy like that
so we can just say restrict and that'll
allow the compiler to aggressively
optimize U essentially what the binary
code code is um and so in here we we
simply just do a uh we do this over the
X Dimension the typical Kuda kernel
indexing um and then we do you know the
square the plus and then the plus one so
uh that's the I mean the the kernel is
surprisingly simple there's just some
new colors and new keywords to pay
attention uh to pay attention for but uh
then we scroll down a bit and then we
got some C++ syntax going on what the
heck does this do well we have this Auto
which essentially figures out like which
which type to this to so it's going to
recognize that this is going to be some
torch type and it's going to
automatically select that and this is
just torch. empty like so it's going to
have the same shape as X the input um
which is a torch tensor type so Auto is
going to recognize it's going
essentially going to uh it's going to
it's going to do this we'll just leave
it as Auto for now because it looks
nicer um and then we have our threads
which the typical 10,24 threads per
block as per the maximum and then we
have our you know numb elements plus
threads minus one divided by number of
threads so this is the typical we
already went over this this should be
very trivial stuff
um and then we have um essentially just
some some extra stuff about
uh how the kernel is going to be called
so which which what things are we
feeding into it um we return an output
based on that um and then down here we
just have our are python bindings so uh
don't worry about this too much just
kind of trust the process um I can kind
of read off of like what I was able to
uh find about this exactly
so um Pi bind 11 module
this this is a macro that defines the
entry point for the python module um
torch extension
name uh is it's a macro defined by
pytorch that expands to the name of the
extension so usually defined from the
setup.py file over
here then we have an m and an
m.de so that adds a new function to the
module so the first argument polinomial
activation uh is the name of the
function in Python so that's the
function we end up calling be P
polinomial activation open close
parentheses um
the polinomial activation Cuda pointer
uh or it is it is a pointer to the C++
function to be called and then the last
argument is a dock string for the
function so this it's just like a a
simple doc string it's not like entirely
required but we we put it there
anyways
so anyways this is the this is the full
Cuda script this is essentially as
simple as it gets you can't really do
anything more simple than this uh so
this is kind of like a template you can
work off of and then in here we uh we
import our compiled polinomial Cuda
function which we'll compile in a second
here we have a class so we use torch
autograd and by default when we when we
when we do an autograd when we do an
autograd function we have to include a
forward and backward method um these are
both going to be static so we just add
this decorator that says this is
compiled elsewhere um
and then forward we're going to do um
just this polinomial Activation so comes
from the bin error that we compiled and
then uh polinomial activation of X right
as we said before and then backward uh
backward we just don't support it yet so
we could just say not not implemented
error backward pass not implemented um
and then in here where we actually do
our n and do module the py should be
familiar to of course this this should
look this should be super easy to
understand um from a from a separate
standpoint um but we just do the init we
do the forward in here we we say you
know implementation is going to be the P
we just set it to a string P Tor so it's
kind of easy to read um and then if the
implementation is p torch we do this raw
and if it's not then we do this uh if if
it's Cuda then we do this this other one
which we specified up here so it's going
to do this
um and it's going to apply that to X and
then else we just we just say oh if you
did like uh if you like missed the T it'
be like oh you Pi orch is not
implemented right unknown
implementation and then so we go down
and let's just go to the main function
first then to the Benchmark so in here
random
seed normally distributed random tensor
on
device implementation on pytorch
implementation on Cuda we move these to
the device so to Cuda this is just like
essentially uh saying that this function
is going to be executed on that you
should have probably seen this before
it's not too bad um and then we do um we
can actually just print out uh whatever
that input
was um and then here we do um like here
we we essentially just Benchmark so we
go um the actual activation function
itself the input we're doing it on
um and then just a string that we're
going to print in the uh in the name
here so here we just set a time we go
for a number of
runs uh and then we we we Cuda
synchronize so we ensure everything is
all caught up and then we end the time
and then we essentially return the name
so whatever whichever these it
was um the the Delta time so like the
essentially the not the Delta time but
the difference um and then we divide
that by the number of runs because we're
doing an average times a th so that we
can get it in milliseconds format um and
that just that just kind of works as we
expected to now to actually compile this
um we go to uh we go to the read me and
literally all you have to do is just
python uh setup.py
install give that a second it's going to
use ninja to build
um so we'll we'll give that a moment um
but this is going to create see a build
a build build folder in here
and we'll print out um forward and
backward in a second we're going we're
going to print both of these
so okay awesome it just it just wrote
that out so now we can go ahead and
python polinomial
activation and it'll it'll do these this
Cuda activation. forward of x uh and
then it'll print whatever that output
was and so we get like a tensor and it
it actually formats this properly which
you're like oh my gosh we just we wrote
this in in in Cuda and c and now it
prints so nicely like this yeah that's
what pytorch does for you um and then we
see that the pytorch built-in gets about
10.47 milliseconds over uh over a th000
runs on average and then the Cuda
extension gets about
0.0 243
milliseconds so if we actually compare
these so if I go
um this divided by uh this we will see
the speed up that we get from kud so we
get about a
431x speed up which is pretty good if
you ask me especially on bigger tensors
right this would be awesome uh so so
that's that and if we actually do a DOT
backward here you'll see that it's both
you know it changed to White so that
that's a good good sign that it doesn't
work and if we actually run this it'll
say uh has no attribute backward right
um so essentially raise the attribute
error um doesn't work and then we
default back to
forward and it'll pop back to this to
this nn. module uh awesome okay so
that's uh that's pytorch extensions for
you you can feel free to add whatever
you want to this um so you know if you
have your own custom like research that
you want to add and make it super easy
for others and and yourself and your
organization to use uh totally feel free
to go down this route copy this copy
this template code do whatever you want
with it um this is just the easy the
easiest example I found um to both you
know write and explain so uh yeah that's
that uh that is pretty much the
first the first uh I don't even know I'm
not going to unify a percent but that
was the majority of the course now we
actually have a final project to go into
so this final project is super exciting
and it's going to help you understand uh
neural networks from scratch how to
optimize them for performance um as well
as like data loaders we're going to add
a bunch of things a bunch of
optimizations into making a real world
training run
work I am so so excited for this part in
this last section of the course we're
going to be doing the final project this
final project is awesome we're going to
do an mnist MLP training run from
scratch it's going to go in the
following order we're going to start in
Python pytorch super easy right then
we're going to go to numpy make it a
little harder but understand what's
going on under the hood and then we're
going to go take our numpy code and Port
that over to C right it's going to run
on CPU it's going to be super easy to
read and comprehend and understand right
then we're going to push that over to
Cuda and then we're going to rank it
fast in Cuda awesome so navigate over to
this folder we're going to do a
different one so it's not going to be uh
SL Cuda course it's going to be slash
mnus Cuda is like a just a separate
thing to help organize things better
maybe you want to show this to a friend
or whatever or or present as someone and
this way you can kind of just have
things separated out and neatly
organized right so you can consider this
as like kind of a separate part we're
just kind of building on what we did
previously uh so if we copy this we're
going to go ahead and actually clone
this into uh a new directory and I'll
kind of walk you through how things are
going to go so I'll go ahead and full
screen this
up sure already saved now I'm going to
CD into that going to go uh UV VNV just
like that I'm going to activate this I
just create like a python virtual
environment that's all I really did
there uh and then we're going to go pip
uh UV pip install d r
requirements and it's going to go ahead
and install everything that we need um
okay sweet now we're going to pop into
the uh we're actually just going to open
this up in vs code go ahead and do that
um now if we pop into the uh let me full
screen this perfect okay so if we go
into this python folder just to like
help you navigate the structure of this
so we're we're going to what we're going
to do is we're going to progress up from
uh python so we're going to go through
pytorch uh as seen in
here uh so that pretty much just like an
entire P torch training run for a
multi-layer
perceptron uh and then a little Jupiter
notebook that's like the same as that uh
but just in a notebook format instead
and then we have a numpy script so just
uh going through and writing everything
from scratch and numpy
um this may not look the same by the
time you're watching this but it'll be
very similar and very easy to understand
um at least for the python stuff so I
mean you you've probably already written
some pytorch already or at least you
understand like the basic you know nn.
linear layer right you probably
understand that already so all we're
actually doing in this one and this is
what I'm going to demo initially is
we're just uh we're literally just
training an mnist MLP from scratch using
basic Pi torch so I import everything
initially so like time nump torch right
uh the data loader and the torch vision
for the data set itself which is mest um
we specify hybrid parameters here so um
you know learning rate uh batch size
number of epoch I think there's like an
extra one here I don't know why that's
there um you know train size for like
number of elements in the train set and
then we're going to go and adjust this
data directory
uh just print this out
actually take
that inject it into
here and we'll go slash SL python all
right
now uh sure SL data why
not now this is going to make sure that
we're using tf32 so that's going to use
tensor cores and make things really fast
um this is going to initialize the data
set properly with like you know mean and
standard deviation um this is just kind
of the best the best practice for mnus
so a lot of this here I'm kind of just
following uh some boiler plate uh code
template examples that kind of thing uh
and now we go down further and
it's you know we initialize our data
sets we initialize our loaders we load
in all of the data uh and we have this
exist on the CPU so notice how we're not
doing um device equals Cuda or do Cuda
yet we're not doing that this is this
just exists on CPU right uh system Ram
so we load all of our train get in
right Lo of our test data in we we're
just printing some stuff at each step
here it per Epoch so per epoch we're
going to do train size which is 10,000
divided by batch size which in this case
is four so it's going to be about 2,500
iterations per Epoch and we're going to
do uh three different epochs so
7,500 uh steps
total now we go down further and we have
the actual architecture for this itself
right um so we take in we take in an X
which is our which is our input we
reshape this to batch size by 784
um we do our first layer second layer
third right so it's just like mat one
activation m 2 and this is organized as
such um in features hidden features
hidden hidden features and then the
output Dimension or num
class uh we have our in feature set to
784 so uh this way it's going to be like
a like a batch size by um batch size is
the X and then weight is going to be 784
by 256 right so that's what that's
that's the shape of this it's going to
multiply by this linear layer and then
we have the rally which is going to take
that and it's going to do the Rue
activation on it you can search that up
if you don't know what that is already
it's very very basic to understand um
it's literally just a
graph and in. linear same idea we're
going to take that previous um batch
size by hidden features we're going to
multiply that by a hidden featur
feachers by num classes and we're going
to end up with B by num classes right or
B by output Dimension whatever you want
to say right and that's the idea is we
just want to keep forward and back
propagating through that and making the
network smarter we're going to go Ahad
and transfer the model to
Cuda we're going to we can do we can do
torw compile for a faster version but
we're not going to do that just because
it like takes a little bit of extra time
to do that um we're going to use cross
entropy lws for this for the entire
project here cross entropy loss is is
critical to uh understand
um I'm going to go over some of this as
well like don't worry if this doesn't
make sense yet we're going to like
literally write this in C so don't worry
if this doesn't entirely make sense I'm
just kind of giving you the rundown as
to like what everything is based off of
we're going to use stochastic gradient
descent so that's just your literally
your Optimizer so it's going to just
nudge the uh you know when you calculate
like a gradient or the S so the error
for a given weight uh it's going to just
literally do learning rate times that
and then subtract that result from the
from the actual weight
itself so uh stochastic rate in a sense
sounds comple uh complicated but it's
not it it's not that bad uh and then we
just have our training Loop here um and
I'll I'll I'll go through sort of more
intimately what this means in the in the
numpy script in a second here here but
all that matters is that we kind of
understand uh this boiler plate this is
designed to be like quite minimalistic
um just kind of match what we're doing
everywhere else and uh yeah I'm not
going to highlight this too much but
we'll go ahead and run this uh just just
for just for fun you know CD into there
we'll do python forch reference and
literally what this is going to do it's
just going to install our nness data so
notice how we got it in the python data
directory
um awesome so now it's initializing
everything it's loading all the data um
so we can see this this is learning over
three Epoch total of 25 200 each and we
end up with an average batch accuracy of
90% which is really good so when it's
classifying those digits it's getting
about n out of 10 of those guesses
correct which is really good uh and we
can see that by the loss here right the
loss is if I move this up the loss we
start from you know loading everything
in start from a loss of about 2.38 which
if we pop into um if we pop into Chrome
here go to go to wol from alpha just to
like provide a reference
um
exp of -2. was it
2.38 that's about 0.92 if it's like if
we round down and say -2.3 it's about uh
0.1 which if you convert that to a
percentage is about 10% accuracy which
is exactly what we want they their
images arranged or or the labels are
between zero and N9 so zero like
literally there's 10 values there so
there should be at initialization a 10%
chance of getting one correct because
it's randomly initialized right right um
and so that's exactly what we want
everything is initialized properly there
um now before I actually go into uh the
numpy implementation like numpy is like
taking P torch and seeing like what the
heck that's doing under the hood um just
like kind of a from scratch approach I
would recommend that you pause the video
right now and watch um Andre carpo's
micro guide video so he made this micro
guide video about two years ago it's
done really really well and it literally
just explains the concept of back
propagation on the level of scalar
values so in this one we're using the uh
we're using back propagation on the
level of tensors but understanding this
uh is crucial for moving up the tensors
so after after you're done this and it's
like still a little bit confusing about
how we're going to bring this up to like
bigger matrices I would recommend that
you uh also take a peek at my back
propagation video this is just on on my
YouTube channel here Elliot codes um
about right now 5.7 th000 subscribers
you should be able to find me um and I
just kind of made like a funny title um
because back propagation is annoying to
understand sometimes and so I I did a I
tried to do my best job to break down uh
what the heck that means on the on the
level of tensors on the Whiteboard um
this does have this does have uh 1440p
quality so you can actually you can you
can see stuff um but yeah and then there
there's just like a ton of like content
that you can watch right I don't
encourage you to just like consume all
the content out there but these are the
three that I thought were the easiest uh
to like build an intuition on what back
propagation is um we're going to be
going over back propagation as well um
but this
is uh this is like where you want to
start from if this is like a completely
foreign concept to you um so Entre aroy
does really good I I go above Andre arpo
um lecture and go up to tensors and then
three blue and brown which you you've
probably heard of
already uh does does a a quick little
lecture on uh on back propagation
intuitively so let's go Ahad and jump
into
numpy okay awesome so now uh let's go
Ahad and take a look at what exactly
this diagram is supposed to be um I
could I could walk through and sort of
just like explain what's going down uh
like what essentially what is happening
step by step in here but first I want to
make this obvious how our neuronet
architecture is structured and how the
neurons actually work right what is a
neuron that type of thing
um so I drew this little diagram to help
us understand what's happening and I'm
going to lay this out here so we
essentially take an image this is the uh
hand handwritten digit it's 28 by 28 and
we're going to have this in a batch
right so it's going to be 28 by 28 and
then depth be our batch batch size you
could say um just a bunch of panes
essentially layered on top of each other
we flatten these so 28 * 28 that's going
to is going to have this this whole
image and we're going to take a row and
we're just going to add it to the end
until it stretches out to the full
length it's going to be 28 of these rows
that are added to the edge right and
then we we plug this into the first
weight so X1 * W1 that's going to be b b
by 784 so B by 784 and then times 7 84
by
256 so a column uh the the the the size
of a column in the weight Matrix is 784
and then the length of a row in X is
also the 784 so it's going to layer on
top of those
right um and we're going to end up with
P by 256 then we go to the next one and
we get this we essentially just feed
this through the Rue so it's going to
just it's going to do the the rally
function on each value pretty simple
then we do X2 * W2 and that's going to
do B by 256 which was output from The
Rue it's going to Matrix multiply that
with 256 by 10 10 is our output size
right so we have this B by headden size
which is 256 that's each uh that's each
neuron output that's that's uh that's
essentially how many um neurons we have
is 256 in our in our in our hidden layer
there and then we just have to ensure
that broadcasting is done correctly so
uh I mean you could always you could pop
over to like pytorch uh
broadcasting broadcast
rules broadcasting semantics here so
this is pretty much just how you're
allowed to like multiply things and and
do operations with tensors when they're
certain sizes right so um you know if
you haven't gone through this already
it's it probably is a good idea um it's
not too hard to learn pytor handles this
stuff pretty well so it's just a little
short short read to do just kind of
understand like what's happening there
but um essentially you just want to make
sure those inner values are the same and
then the outer ones are going to be your
output shape right so we have this B
this B by 256 and then the the 256 here
is going to just it's going to do
product it's going to take each column
and do product there and you're going to
end up with a total of uh 10 values for
each batch element right and this is
essentially uh this this this 10 here is
a distribution of probabilities so prob
probability distribution in batches and
in in a batch um and those are going to
be our predictions the probability of
which digit it is so if the screen says
like a zero
um then what's going to happen after our
network is really smart is the if we go
to say any batch element so any any
essentially row and we go to the first
the zero with index in that um that's
most likely going to be the highest
number in the entire distribution right
that's kind of what's going there um and
then we just do the a loss function on
this called cross entropy loss which
I'll explain in a second CR cross
entropy loss isn't too bad um it's
different than MSE loss but it's better
for batches and kind of what we're doing
here um
so we get our loss which initially is
going to be around
2.3 um based on the wol from alpha based
on the W wol from alpha calculation you
can do right where you go exp uh like
exponentiate negative uh Negative X so
um exponentiate negative 2.3 you get
about 0.1 for that um which is 10%
accuracy and then you do the derivative
of the loss which is just going to
essentially element wise subtract the
softmax probabilities by the true one
hot probabilities and I'll explain those
as well what one hot means and then we
just back propagate right so this is
kind of the forward pass here where we
go um matl one
activation m 2 calculate the loss and
then we backwards this way um so we do
derivative derivative of the loss and
then we do our chain roll back
propagation so we calculate dw2 and
that's just going to be uh keep in mind
the gradient of the weight is supposed
to match the shape of the weight itself
so notice how W2 here was 26 256 by 10
here we do 256x B matal that with B by
10 and so we end up with the Dimensions
256x 10 and that matches up um then we
do dx2 which is needed for you know
continually back prop back propagating
through the Rue out layer um and so here
it's literally just taking the dx2 and
then uh doing an element wise
multiplication with the with the
derivative of the r function of X so
whatever the whatever the um the input
was into
that and then we end up with the same
shape that we got here we simply plug
this we plug this Rue out into both of
these we don't actually need to do it
for dx1 but it's just kind of here just
in case in case you have like a deeper
Network and you want to modify things um
but
dw1 it's going to be so x x1. t right so
we're transposing X1 X1 is over here so
just flipping those flipping those
Dimensions instead of being B by 784
it's now going to be um 784 by B so you
have each column is an image right
instead of each row being an image
um we we we map that with B by 256 which
was the Rue output so that's like the
the last output uh gradient um and then
we get our our our weight value right
so uh and then from here we pretty much
just uh modify the the weights value we
get the same shape there so that kind of
checks out
and then dx1 I mean we don't actually
need dx1 here but I include it uh just
in case um kind of the point there is uh
you know dx1 relies on uh on
W1
so uh we we we don't actually need to
like update anything for this it's just
if there was like a a dw0 if there was
like a layer before that um cuz notice
how uh sorry notice how this Ru layer
relies on this right so if you had like
a like if we had a Ru um if we had a ra
layer like before this if we had a rail
layer somewhere in here then you would
actually need to like dx0 for example
and dw0 you would actually need to uh
use this but since we're not we can kind
of just understand that it's something
you would have if it was a deeper
network but you don't actually need it
to make the network improve in
performance right it's just like an
extra calculation that's redundant so
you you can just kind of exclude it
unless you want to modify it um but I'm
not going to ramble on about that for
too long let's actually get to what the
heck these neurons are doing all
right so I got this little like editor
open here it's like my first time using
it but essentially what's what's H how a
neuron works is we're going to just like
zoom in how a neuron works is we're
going to take a bunch of X values all
right so
X1 X2
X3 and uh these are going to go see
these are going
forward uh into a neuron
right what's going to happen here is
these are going to go um maybe I should
draw these a little
better so this is our neuron here we're
just going to put a plus there and
you'll understand why in a second this
neuron is g to have a bunch of different
weights okay this neuron is g to have
this neuron is gonna have one one weight
for each of these X values so w
W1
W2 and W3 and all this is going to do is
just going to do product these so it's
going to go
W1
X1 plus
W2 uh
X2 plus W
3 X3 and that's going to give
us output right
so this this times this this times this
and this times this right that's a
single neuron and what we're going to
end up with is uh when we sum these
together we're going to end up with a
single value end up with a single value
one
Val one value
here now when we jump up to a bunch of
neurons so if we had say um like
X
X1
X2 and we have say 1 two three
neurons this one is going to have each
of these are going to have two neurons
right so this going to have um one
two one
2 and one two this looks very familiar
to something you've seen before which is
the MLP that I previously showed you
right there the images youve probably
seen like you know clickbait thumbnails
with these before and this is exactly
what it is right so you're going to have
uh two weights in here two weights in
here and two weights in
here and so it's going to do prodct with
each of these you're going to have G to
have this which is going to be
um you know like a
W1
X1 plus a
W2
X2 and then the same for these as well
right it's going to do all of these and
you're going to end up with three total
values so you're going to end up with
one two three values in the
output now
if we actually go to linear algebra and
try to understand this concept things
are going to actually make a lot more
sense okay so we go to linear algebra
say we have um something of size one
by uh
say 784 all
right and then we matal this with
something of size
784 by 256 okay ignore my handwriting
it's terrible um but this is this is
going to be each x value
right
X1 and
then X um
784 and we're going to have 256 neurons
okay so this is number one and this is
uh 256 okay
now all we're going to do is literally
take the at this is going to be like
essentially a it's going to have this is
the number of uh rows it has right this
is the this is the height of the Matrix
so it's going to essentially just look
like a vector it's going to be it's
going to be this and it's just going to
be a
line and this one is going to be quite
tall so it's actually going to look like
this it's going to be
784 by 256 like that now
this this column right
here is going to be a single neuron
right this is going to be
um say
one
neuron this is going to be a set of
Weights that's going to map it's each
each of those weight values is going to
multiply with a single x value right so
W1 is going to multiply with this one um
W2 is going to multiply with X2 down
here and then all the way down to
whatever n is or or sorry down to down
to the down to 784 which is the length
of it or or the the length of the column
I guess you the height of the column
whatever you want to interpret that as
um and this a is a single neuron right
as long as that's clear we're good now
we have a bunch of these neurons as a
matter of fact we have
256 different
neurons
right I don't know how to write with my
hand yet I'm still getting used to
it but we have 256 different neurons
right and they're each dot producting
with the input
itself and we end up with a final output
so notice these you know cancel out and
we end up with
1 by 256 so for one example we're going
to get 256 neuron outputs now if you
envision this as
say um batch by 2 784 so instead of one
image flattened it's a bunch of
flattened images right each flatten
image is a
row then essentially all you end up with
is this B just replaces the one so you
you you get rid of
that and you end up with this B here and
this is just uh a batch of neuron
outputs right so it's like think it's
like imagine thinking about this entire
this architecture here where you have
each x value plugging into like a
different neuron just imagine this but
you but you like layer them on top of
each other so you have like you have
like say you have this like as it's as
it's looking at you at the screen and
then you you plop it down like this then
you put another one on top batch element
one batch element two batch element
three batch element four and each of
these is going to give you something so
this all these outputs is going to give
you like say uh this is going to give
you
[Music]
um what's it called 256 different
outputs and you're going to have these
in a batch batch size right so there 256
outputs are all layered out here and
then each one stacked on top is just
another set of 256 right that's how I
like sort of like to to reason through
this in my head you might want to reason
through it differently but I find that
to be a pretty cool trick to
understanding how these are
working now there's another
term that I did sort of leave out and
this is the bias right so the
bias each one of these each little one
of these neurons is going to have its
own bias right
so you know
X X1 X
xn uh and now each of these little
neurons is going to have its own bias so
we're going to do you know a do product
operation as we normally would we're
going to do like X2 or X1 * um X1 * W1
Plus X2 * W2 all the all the way through
all the different weights inside of a
neuron and then once we get that we're
going to add a bias to that and the bias
is just going to be a single number
because of course it's a scalar value
right so it's going to be essentially
it's going to look like
this W * X we're going to do we're going
to do all of these that we need to dot
product essentially a like a like a
vector a vector vector multiplication
and we're going to add a single bias
value to that right
so the vector um Vector X is going to
look like
this and the vector W is going to look
like this it's going to be a
column so we take this column and we we
do a essentially a matrix multiplication
but they're vectors so it's like
literally what it looks like
is and you just take this element and
you you multiply with this one right so
you kind of you kind of like put like a
stick through it you go
and it's like cut up into a bunch of
little multiplications and you sum them
together and you do your
bias and we can back pop get through
that as well so that that hopefully that
just clears up some of the intuition as
to how we're actually structuring um
this part here so that rule that I just
showed you also applies for the X2 and
W2 right the point is we're just trying
to understand what the whole design of
the neuron is and how we can abstract
that up to linear algebra and then write
really really fast C and C++ and Cuda
code to to make this like run fast
instead of just considering each little
neuron operation independently we can
build we can put a layer of abstraction
up and say this is we we've proven that
this is uh this is how this works in
linear linear algebra and now we can
step forward and try to really optimize
that based on our knowledge about matrix
multiplication right this is one of the
reasons why emphasize the Mel so much is
because it's an extremely important
algorithm in all this deep learning
stuff right um
but yeah now we can uh now let's look at
how we can like you know cross entropy
loss and back propagating through all of
this all right awesome so now we next
have to do the loss function and the
loss function isn't actually too bad so
if we pop over to here notice how we
have uh this cross entropy loss right
this is our this is our loss function
once we get the we do model. forbo from
our X batch and we get the Y predict did
and then a cache right uh don't worry
about the C just worry about these this
y PR and the the batch y right so we go
over to our cross entropy loss and
inside here we're going to dissect this
thing by the way don't worry too much
inside of this thing we have batch size
um so just we essentially just take an
element from the shape do our
probabilities from the softmax function
which we did go over before we have this
piece of work here uh and then uh and
then we just finish it up by calculating
the loss right so assuming that we
understand how our softmax function
works we can actually go ahead and dig
into this
so I'm going to open
up open up a Jupiter notebook here so
going to go ahead and import
numpy then we're going
to define the cross entropy loss uh
function itself and softmax so let's go
ahead and take
these and uh pop these into
here then we're going to say set our
batch size as um as two and then we're
going to set uh
num classes to five all
right then we're going to go and make a
shape we're going to go ahe and make our
both of our um inputs to cross inoc here
the Y PR and the Y true all right so
yred we're going to set this equal to uh
this nump uh Rand n batch sized by num
classes right so that's going to be our
predictions we have a bunch of uh we
have a bunch of batch elements each with
a probability distribution about which
which uh which output it think should be
those are the predictions right and then
we have a y true which is going to be
random integers
um and I'm going to print these out so
you can
see so y looks like this we have batch
size of two so 1 two and we have a bunch
of these elements right this is our
probability uh actually these are not
our our probab probability distribution
yet these are actually called lits so I
skipped a step there but lits are the
step before the softmax right softmax is
going to make sure that everything uh is
above zero right it's going to make sure
everything is like zero between zero and
one right that that's idea there and
it's going to express with confidence
which numbers should should be high
right because it's
exponentiating um these are lits because
it's like um like the lodge it I guess
you could say it's like the log like the
log probabilities so because you have to
exponentiate up to get to softmax it's
like log because you go
down it's going to do Ln not actually
log with base two it's or log base 10
it's going to be Ln so base two base e
or
2.71 and we can go ahead and print out
our y true so this is
um this is an
array it's very yeah you're you're
you're going to see this you're going to
see why this is important in a second
here um but if we actually pop to our
next step we can go probabilities equals
softmax of Y PR so we're going to see
these values get exponentiated we can
print out our probabilities so we can
see that as a part of this which values
were the biggest right so this one was
the biggest like you know closer to
positive Infinity um and the this is
like negative negative negative negative
right so this is like the biggest this
is the second biggest right so we can
see this is the biggest number this is
the second biggest and this is like
these are these numbers are like smaller
right um and same for this one we notice
how oh this 1.95 is really big and then
we have a 1.2 so it's like this is the
biggest second biggest right that's kind
of how that plays out
then we're going to go and do correct uh
correct log probs is going to be um or
correct correct
probs we're going to do um this part
we're going to do this part here so
probabilities and then we're going to
stick these two inside of it all right
so when we do
[Music]
this we notice that what this does is it
gives us um it gives us the indices of
the correct probs inside of the
prediction in inside of the prediction
uh Matrix
right so inside of here if we actually
print out um if we print out you know
np.
arrange right and then we have our y
true
we can essentially think of this four
and one as our correct labels so in in
batch number in batch uh in in this
first batch element the correct index
the the the correct answer is uh is
number four right so it Go 0 1 2 3 4
this is supposed to be close to one if
this is close to one we're doing a good
job that means the loss is going to be
low right this is the this is the
correct answer so if everything is like
favoring this index here if this was the
correct say class to pick
um that that's what we want to optimize
for then this one is picking out the
same thing but for the second element
right so that's why we do when we go up
to Y true here we're doing um that's why
we do this batch size here so it's going
to span the elements the total number of
elements in batch size um and it's going
to just select the the indices right so
we kind of just do a random number here
because it's between zero and numb
classes so you know it goes from zero to
essentially four so one 2 3 4 5 or 0 1 2
3 4 um and so that that's what's
happening there we just initialize
things randomly um but we see that we
did number four so it's going to pluck
out number four of the first one so 1
0.165 then same thing for the second
right we have we have index one so it's
going to go to
0.227
now we have this we we have this correct
probs which I just explained here
and if we go down or sorry if we if we
pop up a little bit further we see that
we just did this part right so now if I
wrap np. log around that
term np. log we'll just say
um we'll just say correct uh log probs
we'll just do np. log of that
um and then if we do correct log
probs uh we notice that we're just doing
the log of each of these of each of
these number right so so if we go import
math and then we go
um math. log of
0.165 we get this number right so uh -
1.8 we're just doing this for each of
these elements right and then we
continue further and we go
loss is the sum
of loss is the uh sum of all of those so
the correct log problem is going to sum
these all up together so it's going to
be like uh negative 1.8 and then
negative we're on 1.5 so they're going
to add and they're going to get about -
3.3 umga 3.47 or
3.27
um and then we divide all of this by
batch size to kind of you know normalize
AC cross batch we don't want it to to
get too massive like if you increase
your batch size to like a thousand then
your loss is going to be insanely high
and you're going to get numerical
instability from that you just don't
want it so you want to normalize over
the over the amount of samples that you
actually have in the batch and that's
going to help stabilize things for us
later during the training process we
don't want things to like step up and
get worse every single training step um
so if we go ahead and print out the loss
we notice um we notice how we get this
1.64 right so go back going back up here
um this was you know this was quite off
this was a little bit less off but it's
still fairly high like these are still
like this is like 16% 177% chance and
this is 23% chance and so that's not
very good so our loss is going to be
higher but if our um if our correct
probs
array sorry our correct probs array was
um see numpy do
array and we go say
um
0.9 and
0.8 and then we uh you know continue to
go through this so correct uh correct
log probs uh equals and then and then we
do our loss right and we print out out
our loss again loss is going to be
significantly lower because these values
the the the difference between uh the
difference between our prediction
accuracy and the actual label was very
close right so we we thought there was a
90% chance that this index was going to
be it right and we were we we were we
were correct right so that's a very high
confidence that we were correct and
that's a good thing this is also quite
high confidence that we were correct so
we want to reward ourselves for that or
minimize the loss right so if we have
values like 10% chance or 5% chance our
loss is going to be stupid high but uh
if we get closer and closer to what what
we sort of minimizing the difference
between what the model thinks it is and
what the actual thing is that is a good
thing that's that's what we're trying to
optimize for
here now there's another little step
that comes along with this
and that's the derivative of the loss
right so if you go over to Gro here and
say um
what what
is what is the derivative of cross
entropy
loss so it's defined as this which we
just went over so Yi is the true label
either zero or
one and this is the predict so so Yi
without a hat is the true label and Y
hat I is the protective probability and
we run through this we do some we do
some
differentiation um we go a few steps
later I'm not going to really cover the
math behind this differentiation part
this part is you know you can you can do
that on your own if you really feel it's
necessary um but really what we care
about is just the answer so the actual
derivative so putting it all together
look at the gradient um what we what we
actually care about is
um why hat minus y and notice y hat was
uh the predicted probability so this so
that soft maxed uh the soft maxed logits
right uh the probability distribution
and then just normal Y is the true label
so if we go back to our code here um and
we look at how that's
calculated we pop down and we see it is
the softmax probability distribution
minus the true labels right so that's
exact what we want it to be um and a lot
of this what we're doing here this is
mainly just converting things to the
actual one hot Vector um so uh yeah
that's that that's pretty much that's
pretty much how you do soft Max and then
derivative or sorry cross entropy loss
and derivative of it right now going
back um what's next so now we have now
we actually have to go through and
calculate the the gradient of of our W2
our X2 even maybe possibly Ford ones and
the bias right so let's go and look at
that I'm going to do an example where we
pretty much do uh we calculate dw1 and
then we kind of just bring uh the
intuition from that into everything else
and then go ahead and apply it right so
in in dw1 I'm going to I'm actually
going to go to this in a second here
um but I'll bring my
whiteb a little closer so I don't know
if you can see this but I pretty much
did um based on you know the micr
tutorial I did uh like an output this is
a neuron output right so X1 * W1 + X2 *
W2 where it's like each of the X values
go in and
then um the the neuron will a s like two
x values go in and there's a single
neuron that has uh two weights in it um
W1 and W2 and then it outputs those by
doing um by doing a doc product between
so it does X1 * W1 and then plus that to
X2 * W2 and I just wrote this in the
context of microG grad so there's a data
and a grad attribute for this there is a
a data and a grad attribute for this so
notice how I did the the this is a plus
sign I know you can't see it because
it's yeah it's very small but ient did a
plus sign so those two added together
and the gradients are going to the this
grad right here of two that's going to
flow to both of these nodes this X1 * W1
and X2 * W2 that's going to flow to
these um the same so when you when you
like uh for example when you're try to
differentiate a constant um it it ends
up just it ends up just becoming one
right so there's actually no change when
you have um like a graph which is which
you add like a bias to it and just shift
that curve upwards it still has the same
slope right so that's essentially what's
happening here and then we continue
forward and this now becomes just a
multiplication so W2 uh or or sorry X1 *
W1 and then we have a data and a grad
attribute for those so that's just like
kind of how a neuron is going to be
structured in the context of
micrograph now uh if we pop over to
um if we pop over to this
example which
is over here so this dw1
output what I pretty much did is we go
uh 784 Time by B so let's just draw that
out really quick
um
so 784 by
by
B and then we have um B by 256
right this is an at symbol it's really
bad
drawing
B by
256 all right so how do we actually
Matrix multiply here well we take a
column of
this and we draw product with a row of
this right and notice how this is
batches right so this is going to be a
batch element this is a batch element
this is a batch element so it's going
this is we're essentially doing
um we're we're taking the first pixel
across the first batch element so if we
were to just go here that would be an
entire image right that would be the
first batch element it would be an
entire image but we're doing the first
pixel across the entire batch right so
across all the different batch elements
we're taking we're do producting the
pixel values um so like for example X
um x.
data at
index0 right and then in this context
this is B by 256 which is the same as
the uh output layer so if we did like
for example the the classical input of
um you go back to this it's like B by
784 * 784 by 256 you end up with B by
256 and that's our output gradient right
so we're we're essentially just just
taking this and we're shifting it around
so we're doing we're taking this B by
256 that stays the same but we're
transposing the input so it's like x.t
or sorry x. data
transpose um Matrix multiply that with
the output output gradient and we're
getting the gradient for the weights
right the dw1 value um so if we go back
to here
256 remember um 784 is how many weights
are in a single neuron but 256 is the
amount of neurons we actually have in
that hidden layer so 256 is going to be
like this is this these are all the
neurons laid out right but what we're
going to do is instead of taking like a
a single a single set of all the neurons
from a single batch element we're going
to take all of the all of the the index
zero gradients uh across
the uh across the
across
essentially uh batch element
no sorry not batch element zero across
we're going to take the first neurons
across the entire batch that's what
we're doing so this ends up being um
we'll just say y.
grad
um y. grad at index zero we're doing it
across the entire B batch so it's just a
single neuron right it's just a single
neuron but we're generalizing that
across the entire batch so we have this
x component generalizing across the
whole batch and this y component
generalizing across the whole batch we
use the same intuition that we got from
the microgr lecture and we just apply it
here except we get that generalization
ability from using batch processing
that's where the big thing comes in here
because we're doing we're essentially
doing uh columns here do product with
rows and notice the shapes are oriented
in a certain way
yeah
it's it it is a lot to take in but in
the end we end up with um so this is
this is like 784 by B and then B by 256
so the B's cancel out and we're left
with
um I know these shapes are out of
proportion
784 by 256 right so this 784 that's the
first pixel value so each of these or
sorry each each of these elements that's
a pixel
right that's a pixel in the whole
flatten image and these are all the
neurons so we end up calculating these
um in a way that we can that we can
actually update uh all of the weights
properly right so when all these are
laid out you have um the gradient for
each neuron across the first uh across
the first pixel value and that is the
that is the same way that our initial
weight Matrix is organized right so in
our weight matrix it's taking these
Columns of of like a single neuron of
weights and do producting that with with
a single um with a with a single image
right and it and it's doing that and
that's very intuitive and it makes sense
uh but in this example
um you know we we end up getting those
we end up getting the same ones that we
would we would want to update those with
so you can kind of Translate and see
like what is this column here what does
that consist of and what does this row
here consist of and we can plug that in
and we can see that our weight updates
are actually going to make sense here so
in this one we we essentially end up
with this thing of 256 values and that
is just going to be the essentially the
gradient of all of the neurons with
respect to a single Pixel right cuz this
is a single Pixel across an entire batch
we're again we're just using the batch
generalization idea here um we're just
like generalizing across whole batch
instead of using one specific sample
that way it's like better for
stabilizing training um and and we're
just we're taking that and we're just
laying everything out for
um for all of the neurons across a
single um across a single Pixel right
that's how we're calculating these so
this this uh it's going to be like this
row this is our pixel AC like all the
pixels for like for all all the first
pixel for all the batches and then we
have our our single
um we have our our first neuron and it's
going to go first neuron boom it's going
to put the first value there and then
second neuron boom all the way to 256
neurons and it's going to spit this out
in a column
right that's all of the neurons um for
the for the entire first
pixel and then if we look at how it goes
down
columnwise then we get um then we get
all the neurons for the second pixel and
the third pixel and the fourth one right
and so we can sort of
see that this ties back again into uh
the original forward pass example that
we were doing um if this if this doesn't
make sense I know my explanations might
be bad um you know you might want to go
back and and I mean you you could draw
this out your yourself um that does work
and just sort of visualizing it in your
head that's a good idea to do uh that is
a good idea to try to understand how
this is working um alternatively you can
you can watch my tensor uh my tensor
level back propop video I think I did a
good job on that um it's about 30
minutes long so uh
anyways well we if if this doesn't
entirely make sense we're going to use
this intuition of we have this 784
by
256 and this is the same as just our our
W um our w. dat
right so our w.g
grad and our
w. dat have the same
shape so what we can essentially do is
we can take
um say in in the grad in the gradient
for example we can take this value
multiply it by a learning rate of say LR
equal
0.1 and we can then subtract this from
the original one right so if the
gradient is really high that means
there's a lot of error and if the
gradient is really low um that means
that there's there's going to be um that
means there's going to be less error
right this is why it's called a
stochastic gradient descent cuz you're
descending the gradient um so it's going
to be essentially um w. data equals LR
times um just do X for times learning
ratees
times the grad element
right and then we do um minus
equals so that if the gradient values
really high and learning rate is 0.1
then it's going to be positive time
negative and then this is going to get
adjusted in the negative direction if
the gradient is really high um and if
the gradient is really if it's really
negative gradient is really
negative
um then this is going to this is going
to multiply with this it's going to give
a negative value and then since we're
subtracting a negative it's going to go
up and the way it's going to go up so
that's that's literally all we're doing
in gradient
descent and we're doing that for each
element now we can sort of take that
intuition and Branch it off to you know
dw2 right and we can apply that to
dx2 um you know this isn't really a
course on back propop so don't worry too
much if that doesn't completely make
sense it is important but if it doesn't
completely make sense you're still going
to be okay um cuz we're going to
implement this and you're going to
actually be able to see the network
learning and you can actually print out
things to understand what's happening
under the
hood and of course we do need these uh
these these X values for calculating the
intermediate these intermediate layers
right with activation functions um and
the activation functions like literally
if you want me to like draw out how that
would work
um Rue
it goes like this
right it's like it's like a line and
then it goes up just like that so what
you can do for this is you can say if my
value is zero or less I'm going to set
the gradient to zero because there's no
slope the slope is
zero and if it's if it's if it's greater
than that if it's greater than zero then
uh we're going to set that to one right
because if it's it's really is going to
make it remain the same if it's above
zero
um okay
awesome now let's pop into um sort of
this this python script that we have
running here and uh just dissect
everything that's happening so we can
just tie it back to uh this image that
we that that I wrote in excal draw just
so that everything kind of makes sense
on the code on on a conceptual and a
code
level all right so just kind of going
through uh this numpy script now uh we
import numpy normally um I mean I
actually already went through this part
I'm not going to review this again um
but if we go down you can see a bunch of
functions here right and these are all
these are all super useful functions
that we're going to use to essentially
uh train a single layer single hidden
layer multi-layer perceptron from
scratch um using the intuition we
previously built on that from you know
microgr Etc right so we we scroll down
and in this main function we declare
some some variables here so like hidden
size which I'll just set to like 256 in
this case um output size is 10 right so
10 different digits 0 through 9 and our
input size is 28x 28 pixels flattened
out um and then we're going to put our
bat size I'll just put eight here so we
can get speed um learning rate of
0.1 or or um alternatively 1 * 10 -3 and
then epox we're going to do five so epox
is how many times you go through the
entire training set right so you go
through it once that's like certain
number of iterations certain number of
like forward and backward passes it's
like one iteration and then you do
multiple epochs which is you know times
that you go over the train
data so inside of here we declare this
model neural network right input hidden
and output size and then we just have
this train function which is going to
actually do that for us so inside of
here we have number of epochs that we're
going to do and inside of each eoch
we're going to do we're going to train
in batches right so we have this batch
size a batch of images that are all
flattened so it's like B by 7 784 and
we're just going to step through um kind
of going through one by one here so in
the model. forward I mean we're just
we're in this this one we're just taking
um the X train is just input images and
then this is the output labels right
it's the it's the batch y so in the
model forward um we input a batch and we
get an output cache and we get a we get
y right the Y predictions the
probability distribution in a batch in
batches
right uh after we do model forward we're
going to do take the loss function of Y
PR and batch Y which we got from
here and then we're going so cross cross
entropy loss calculates the loss and
then separately we're going to take that
output again which keep in mind this is
logits so not actual um probability
distribution it's uh cross entropy loss
is going to softmax those
um and then it's going to return a loss
right so it does soft Max inside of here
so when we're actually getting the uh
derivative of the Cross entropy loss we
have to go and do that separately right
we have to get our probability
distribution and then we have to
essentially just um like I walked
through before how we actually do the
how we do the cross entropy loss
derivative I walked through that with
grock previously and uh this is
literally all we do so uh you know feel
free to like print this out but this
should be fairly intuitive if you work
with python and pytorch before um and
then we just you know do the do the
minus for our gr out output and then we
back propagate from there right so we
take our grad output and we use the
cache the
cache um so keep in mind when we do
model. forward we have ypr which is the
logits and then we have the cache which
is literally just um the inputs right so
all the different pieces of the layer
that we're going to need like for
example our dx2 the derivative of the
second um the second x value or um for
example The Rue output right so so just
stuff like this that we're going to need
to back propagate through all the layers
and not just like a single weight or
single weight here we're going to need
that whole cache of like through the
forward pass right um so that's that's
all that is it's just just a coule of
those and then of course that output the
loits right so just to clear up like
what the heck cache means there I know
that can be like sometimes misleading um
so we do model. backward and then we
just do model upd weights and we pass in
you know weights bias um weights and
bias again
so let's walk through what's happening
in forward this part I assume kind of
just makes sense we'll walk through
model. backward and then update weights
so in
forward uh model. forward over here so
inside of here we have the batch size as
x. shape at position zero so it's going
to it's going to list the shape it's
going to be B by 784 or sorry B by is
going to be um the batch that we get so
when we when we take this part we're
getting an actual batch so I and then to
I plus batch size so it gets a little
segment of like eight eight images um
and inside of here we're going to take
the first the the the leading dimension
of that which is batch size and we set
batch size here and then we do reshape
we go batch size by um and then the
essentially just the the last the last
one so it's going to be reshaped to
batch size
by um this is just a short way of doing
28 * 28 so 784 that's what this is going
to reshape to and then we go ahead and
do our our linear forwards and these are
these are should be very uh sensical
right so in our linear forwards
um we take in a weight sorry we take in
an x a weight and a bias right so we do
X at w + B right instead of w WX plus b
it's x w Plus plus b um so that's it's I
mean it's it's B by 784 we go back to
this so we go in here B by 784 * 784 by
256 and we end up with B by 256 right um
should be fairly
intuitive and then we add the we add the
bias as well which is another term I
actually did not include in this but you
can kind of just we can kind of just
think of the bias as like an extra extra
thing that it adds on um
now scroll down to relu right so relu I
mean this is self-explanatory it's just
going to do a point R it's going to be
num. maximum it's going to apply that to
every single value in there doing a you
know if it's uh if if the value is like
negative 1 then zero is going to be the
maximum it's like which one is higher Z
or negative 1 then it's going to pick
zero and if it's like one then it's
going to be like oh one is higher than
zero right so it's just kind of the
relue and then really derivative is you
know as we explained before how you have
like the chart and then goes like this D
gradient of derivative of zero then it's
going to go gradient one after after the
zero right um so that's just that's what
this is doing here um because we want to
ra you derivative right
um
now going back another linear forward we
take the Rue output so that's the new
input to the to the next line your
forward layer the the weights the
weights two and then the bias two right
so that that should also make sense and
then we just return that so forward pass
isn't actually too complicated we can
sort of just walk through and understand
how the shapes are changing this is more
a template example of how to understand
this from scratch Now we move down to
backward which is a little harder um go
to backward here we have the W1 B1 W2 B2
right so we put in the grad output so
the starting the wherever we start from
in back proper ation and go for and go
backward through the layers and then
cache as well which is the which is the
forward pass like intermediate cach
stored values right um so we go into
backward here and we see
um we get in this grad output and the
cache as we'd expect um and then we just
lay out that Tuple so fc1 input so we
just
um fc1 input fc1 output uh value output
right um so just kind of just unpacking
this again um now we go to here and it's
linear backward so if we step back to
this linear backward one is going to um
it's going to calculate both of these
right so linear backward is a bit bigger
actually um we go here taking a grad
output select the output thing the input
and then the weights right so we can
calculate both the uh the the grad
attribute for both the X and the W value
right so in here we do um grad weights
um is X is X transpose times the grad
output and so if we go to here we can
see uh X transpose and then times the
grad output which in this case and the
first layer is is derivative of the loss
um and then in this dx2 for example we
see the gr output times the transpose
weight 2
right so gr output times transpose
weight two and then the bias
um I'll break that down more so in in
the C- section but um this is this is
the grad bias right so um I can actually
just like print that out let's let's pop
into here really quick and just exit
that um so how did this go again we do
np. suum so I'll just do um NP just do I
python import numpy
as n p then we go x
equals just do torch. and um we'll do 3
by we'll say 2 by 4 right we print
out Imports import torch then go back up
print out X and we get this right so if
we do um we print out torch. suum of X
we do axis equal 0 and we go at keep
dims I think it's keep is it keep dims
How does it
go keep dims equals
true we can see that literally all this
does is it is it mushes these together
so it's going to go two + 1 and then
this is like 21 plus that so it's 3.23
and then so essentially like mushing
knees moing knees mushing knes right
right um and it's going to do this
across the the across like this the
horizontal right so it's going to Mush
cross hor vertical sorry because that is
the that is the zero axis right the the
leading Dimension here so that's that's
this vertical part so it's going to Mush
vertically
um and so that that's really all that is
um so we're just combining things across
the entire batch right but you'll see
this more intuitively in the in the C
version now we do the you know this as I
as I mentioned before and we just
essentially return those right for the
linear backward
layer we return all of our all of our
gradients and then we perform a
optimization step so we do the model.
backward and we do model. update weights
and we pass one 2 3 4 as well as the
learning rate in and inside of update
weights we'll see right here we
literally just do self. weights self
dobias weights and bias and we do minus
equals the learning rate times the
gradient right so as I was talking about
before you're trying to reduce you're
trying to essentially gr do gradient um
gradient descent that's what this is
just that the stochastic gradient
descent because it's it's doing it
constantly every single time and uh yeah
that's that's how we update the network
so you know if if if the gradient is if
the gradient is really high that means
there's a lot of error right so if we do
um learning rate times something really
high so a positive times a positive and
then subtract that from here um that's
going to mean it's contributing a lot
and then it's going to mean it's it's
initially contributing you know a lot of
error and we want to reduce that we want
to change it
significantly um and then if it's like
say lower we don't we don't we don't
want to adjust that as much right so
it's kind of just going to balance
between in the middle whichever one
gives us the most error right
um and we do this we do the same idea
for all of these and we just just do
this essentially this scalar value
multiplied by each thing in the entire
weights and the bias Matrix we do that
everywhere and that's pretty much it U
we do that for every single every single
iteration we do a we do a we get we get
whatever inputs and output uh
predictions we need we do a forward pass
we do loss function derivative of the
loss model. backward so backward pass
update weights and then if we need to we
just like print out the progress over
time right so if we go ahead and run
this
um python C friendly we can go and see
this is actually training quite well so
we this is training quite fast as well
you know numpy is bed to C which C is
really fast we can see that you know
over the first one over the first 7500
iterations we get 93% accuracy so just
to iterate a little more about this
whole linear backward um np. suum cross
axis zero where you take each column and
you squash it together the reason why we
do that is because each of those is like
across the entire batch right so this
would be like a single uh uh a single
layer right single bunch of a bunch of
biases for like all the neurons or
whatever you want to say and what we're
doing here is we're taking a single
neuron and we're squashing everything
together cuz like imagine if you have a
really big um like a really sparse
really big reward signal for a single
example and then like you do 20 other
ones and they have the complete opposite
right the idea is to like kind of
average all them together you're not
you're not like divide you're not adding
them all together and then dividing but
you're you're just like accumulating all
of them together so you end up with
something that's like close and pushes
in the direction of like where
generalization should be so I know that
sounds like really conceptually Advanced
but it's not it's you're just trying to
push in whatever way the average favors
so that's why you do it AC cross the
actual batch itself CU if you had just
this Vector laid out I mean you could do
that but training might not go as
smoothly whereas if you were to just
accumulate everything so you get like on
average what is the best way to move
what is the best way to move that bias
value then it then it helps a little bit
more so that's why we do that um but now
let's get into C this is pretty much a
port of just the last script that we ran
so this v1c you'll find this in the
naive CPU because this is a naive
algorithms these aren't like really
really fast are just like the easiest
way to write them um very like intuitive
to understand um but gives us a basis
for how we can modify this and turn turn
it to Cuda right um so inside of here we
do the same
idea we have a little neural network
thing at the top I mean it should
probably go from like top to bottom but
uh yeah so inside of here learning rate
same learning rate we have 10 hex which
is a bit different I Chang batch size to
four because have having it as 8 or 16
or 32 just took a ridiculous amount of
time to compute for through each layer
so I set this a little lower to four
input size Remains the Same it has to hi
and size 256 output size is 10 train
size 10,000 test size we're not going to
really need this but 1,000 for that um
and then we have this neural network
struct right so we can't actually do a
CL we can't do a class in C but we can
do struct we don't we don't have like
the the class and and objectoriented as
aspect that we do in C++ right this is a
functional functional language so we're
only allowed to use strs and inside of
here we just store a bunch of arrays so
all the weights and biases and then the
gradients for those right uh just to
kind of Mark everything down easily and
and use this very simple uh struct
right now we have some functions for um
for actually loading the data now I
don't want you to worry too much about
the loading data aspect um this part it
kind of just depends on like which use
case you have but in this case um I I
run the uh down downloader script so
this downloader script uh just saves
everything to a binary file um and then
inside of C we just write those back
again so or sorry we we we read them we
read from the binary so notice how we do
like file open and then the file name
and then a read binary um and then it
just turns that into into a usful format
right so uh yeah it's not not entirely
uh too too crazy um we essentially just
like directly read this into um into
bytes and then we modify that as needed
later on we do the same thing for labels
so very simple uh data loading functions
um not too crazy compared to the mest
one but this is in C right so it's
obviously going to be a bit different
now we have this interesting thing here
called initialize wage which I probably
should have shown you back here in our
um where did it go in our C friendly
script so notice in here how we have
multiple functions right we have r r
derivative initialize weights
initialized bias and then these other
ones which I already went over um
initialize initializing weights and
biases are kind of simple all right they
just follow specific guide so if we do
start off with initialized bias it's
literally just going to be um just a
bunch of zeros right it's all it's going
to be just need the bias is a bunch of
zeros that's okay we can start and we
can move up and down from there
um but the weights cuz
so so bias is bias is floating flowing
from the previous layer so having it as
a zero doesn't actually matter it
doesn't affect anything the bias the the
bias gradient are just flowing directly
from the previous layer those unmodified
the same gradients um but the weights
themselves are a little different so how
we initialize weights is I'm actually
going to go over to here we going to
search up P torch timing
initialization and this is how you
actually initialize um I'll just do I'll
just do uh torch do uh nn.
linear um we'll go to
linear
so in pytorch we do this
um where is
it yes
so the biases are initialized um in this
distribution which we we can we we can
do we don't entirely have to worry about
that it's not a big deal um but then the
then the weights themselves these are
nor these are initialized uh on this
basis right so we have um of shape
output features by input
features and we make this from uh from
negative square Ro TK of K to positive
square root of K where K is
um K is one over the input features so
if we pop back to this we're doing a
random normal distribution right and
with each of these numbers we have to we
have to Clump them to this range right
so these values are these values are in
some normally distributed range and all
we have to do there is
um we do we we initialize to this right
so K in this case
okay so if we actually go to the H
ination paper he init
paper
um this is I think this is
it climing hey so climing and hay
climing and it hey and it are the are
the same thing um but if we go into here
we go two ided by no maybe it's not
there formula is somewhere in here
um where did it go
I search up
um
Rue initialization
maybe that's a better term to look
for
yes this right
here so this leads to a zero mean G CH
distribution whose standard deviation is
square < TK of two over um over this
term and this term is the um I can't
remember exactly what this is but I
think this is length
so we have an input size here which you
could say as the length I don't know if
that's specifically what L ties to but
we'll just hold that assumption for now
that that's that's the idea there is you
would have
um standard deviation is
this um and if we continue to go forward
maybe we might find something else here
too
um if we
continue yeah so some
layers other solution is to small Factor
on the weights
right
anyways
uh yeah this is pretty much the the
inspiration from it so just looking at
like kind of the purpose of this um
this this specific initialization as
compared to the P torch one um which I
probably should have looked into
beforehand the pytorch one is a little
different um but the hay initialization
is designed to work well with railu so
it uses Square < TK of two / um input
size as a standard deviation for the
distribution that it's generated on
right
um it essentially counts out for the
rause activation to zero out negative
values so you might have these um
so-called dead neurons that come up when
you have like the Rue that just zeros
something out and then when you try to
uh like multiply that by something it
ends up just like zeroing it out and you
might like end up through the training
process with like a row of zeros that
just don't do anything and they're like
useless and so you're not actually
compressing information down into those
because they're just zero so this helps
deal with
that now jumping back to C
script
um this is what we're doing here so we
essentially have this we're we're just
we just have to use like what we're what
we're defaulted to with C we get this
weights with the size that it's in we
make this scale so square root function
you know like we were doing before um
square otk of two divided by size in
this case um which size would be um you
know size may not be appropriate I just
kind of found this to work and and
training exceptionally well with this so
we're going to stick with that um but
the size we're going to iterate through
this and essentially for each weight
value we're going to generate a value
between Rand so Rand is going to be
anywhere between zero and Rand Max so
two one whatever this is so essentially
this this in here is going to be zero
between that Max number it's going to
this is going to simplify to between a
value between 0 and one decimal floating
Point 32 number between 0 and one we're
going to multiply this by the
scale um which is which is going to be
that and then we're going to subtract it
by the um by the scale divided by uh
divided by
two and this is just going to give us a
nice normal distribution for uh for our
weights right this is going to do
essentially the same job as we were
doing
before bias initialize all these to zero
as we were doing before Ru is also very
simple
um the softmax I mean I think I showed
you the softmax in the Triton section so
um this is yeah this should be fairly
intuitive we we get this you know we get
this max value right and then when we're
actually doing the exponentiation we we
subtract the max value so we get still
remain with numerical stability um not
having that would just like give these
crazy you know e to the whatever super
crazy numbers when we have um ridiculous
arrays um with like you know th negative
a th000 negative 10 it's just it just
gets out of hand right so we want we
want Max to normalize that and just get
rid of any of those
instability
um and then we yeah we just compute the
soft Max right this is this isn't too
bad same function we looked at before we
have a matte mole so I specifically
worded these so that it would make make
the most sense so it's a map mole but
this treats it as like you're taking in
an array a and you Matrix multiply that
with B right so say for example 2x4 is a
and 4x three and so you'd end up with a
2x3 and it would organize that in row
major order right made these as simple
as possible um you can dissect these but
we already did a ton of stuff on matal
so don't I'm not going to go over this
for the like 20th time um then we have a
a * B transposed so it's going to take
in B is like say it's like a is 2x4 and
then B is a um 3x4 and so it's going to
uh do this operation as if it's
transposing B to a 4x3 so end up with a
2x3 right um and then same idea for this
one if you end up with a 4X two and then
a four four 4X two as as a and then 4 by
uh 3 as B it's going to transpose a and
it's going to make it a 2x4 and they're
going to match up you're going to get
two and three right so that that's just
kind of the idea there and then we do um
the the ru forward I probably wrote an
additional um might have
wrote yeah so this is like designed to
work in batches um I might have probably
written an additional one just like
accidentally which I'll probably remove
um oh R you there yeah so I should
probably remove this actually but um
well we'll I'll worry about that later
and this will be updated by the time
you're working on it um and then we just
just have the bias forwarded which is
going to you know add the bias um so
literally what this is doing is it's
iterating through uh it's it's going
through batch size right and then we
iterate through the actual size itself
which is
um which is the actual uh like the the
the row length so it's going to go skip
over as many number batch elements as it
needs to so it's going to skip it's
going to stride
over then it's going to add this ey
offset to it and it's just going to plus
equals bias at that that value right so
we we essentially just have this this
row of biases and it's going to um just
essentially add each of those it's for
for like a given batch element for like
batch element one um it's going to just
add you know say it's like 10 values
here it's going to add all 10 to the
bias values and it's going to go down
it's going to add those same values
again it's just applying the same bias
to each to each row right that's what
this is doing
scrolling down further I'm not going to
go into these quite yet because there's
like more happening but scroll down
to um the
actual uh train function and the where
is
this the in main function so in here we
have a a pseudo random number generator
um these are pseudo random they're not
you can actually have completely random
numbers that's like a very hard uh you
know cryptographic graic problem and
everything that's like something I'm not
going to go into um you know in this
case we're using srand to to to Generate
random numbers but in Cuda you can use Q
Rand so it's going to Generate random
numbers in parallel really fast so you
don't have to like wait for the CPU to
do this one and this one then this one
right it's kind of faster um we
initialize this neural network class
with NN or sorry struct struct got to
use the politically cor correct terms we
initialize the neuronet so we go here
and we just have this NN and then the
weight attribute right uh equals then we
do Malik just a regular C Malik so
weights one is going to be um hidden
size by input size right so that's the
256 by
784 and then the weights two which is
output size by hidden size so um this is
going to be
um what's it called 256x 10 so it's
going to take the BX 256 and then 2 6 x
10 and it's going to multiply those and
it's going to get a B by10 output right
for the after the weights um you know
bias bias one is hidden size just adding
again to that to that output of all of
those neurons each value for each neuron
IUS 2 same
idea the grad weight so just this but
the it's just a different uh it's just a
different variable right so we're
storing the gradients of those the error
um and they're just going to be the same
shape right
um and then we initialize so we have
initialized weight and initialize bias
now this is going back to um the the
climing init that we did the the hay
initialization and the initialized bias
that we did before
um now now that we've initialized those
with random values we go into here so
our X train is going to be the train
size so train size in this case is uh
you know 10,000
let me go down a little bit more train
size times input size so an image is
784 um you know flattened and then we
have the train size which in this case
is
10,000 um the Y train is just going to
be a bunch of integers that are that
span this so we don't we don't actually
need 784 there's only one integer value
per sample um which is the label and
then we have the same for for the for
the test set
right we load these in using the
previous um loading loading scripts that
I showed you before we can print the
first image in the terminal so this
going just going to print things out
using the X thing right um so if I I'm
going to compile this later and you'll
kind of see what I mean but it just kind
of shows us um like how good our our
actual predictions are going to be um so
we can actually like look at look at an
image in the terminal and see okay what
did it think this was what was the
actual label right so we can kind of
like look and sort of match things up in
our own head I don't want to use like
open CV or a custom extension to put a
window cuz that's just a bunch of extra
work it's easier to do it in the
terminal um and then just the training
labels for those as well right and then
we go through and we do the train
function which is comprehensive and then
we free everything up we don't do Cuda
free this just C we just do free and it
get gets rid of the weights uh biases
all the gradients for those the train
set and the test set
right now we go into TR inside of here
there's a bunch of things happening all
right so if I click this can see where
the end
is we have this we have this um this
hidden right here so that's going to be
you know the B by 256 as we looked at in
um the B
by where was
it batch size by hidden size so that's
like going to be the actual hidden layer
output right so so here we get a B by
256 that's the hidden layer it's the
that's the first you know mmal output
essentially and then we get the output
which is batch size by output size which
in this case is p
by10 and then we do num batches so the
number of batches we're actually going
to do is train size divided by batch
size and the reason we do this is
because we don't want to just like
offset each time we don't want to give
it the same data each sample so if we
take that total 60,000 and divide that
by batch size meaning like four
uh or sorry train size is 10,000 and
then batch size is four we're going to
get 2,500 total um total batches each
with four images in them so we're going
to do four and then four and then four
and then four this way we don't like
overlap right containing the same images
in adjacent batches we just kind of give
it new data every time and we do Epoch
over that right so we do all of the
batches and then we do another Epoch
over that so what's going to happen it's
it's going to it's going to do like up
to 50% in the first Epoch or some some
some number like that 50% and then it's
going to start the next Epoch and it's
going to learn from all the examples
that it had previously and it's going to
be like oh we saw those again we know
exactly what to do there so it's going
to it's going to get you know accuracy
is going to like it's the loss is going
to look like this it's going to figure
start figuring everything out tuning
whatever it can get its hands on and
it's going to drop because it figures
out what to optimize then it's going to
Plateau through that Epoch it's going to
sort of plateau out and then the next
next Epoch starts and it's going to it's
going to drop again because it's because
it's seen those again and it can
optimize for more it can compress more
features into that because it's seen
that already um so it's going to you
know continue dropping again and then
it's going to sort of plateau and then
it's going to drop again and and then
we're just going to end up at some place
when whenever all the epoch are done
right so we iterate through Epoch now
this is
um if I look at this actually um this
finish is here so inside of a single
Epoch this is where most of the work is
done right we just do like free hidden
and output so most of the work is
actually done in the epox loop inside of
here we do a total loss which we
initialize to zero the number of correct
answers so we also set that to zero this
is just for tracking the accuracy so we
can see the loss dropping versus what
the percent accuracy is over the over
the U over the the training samples
right so each training step we can see
which or every sorry every um every
thousand every 1,000 or or every 100
training steps we can see what the
accuracy is over the
batches then inside of here we iterate
over num batches increasing by um by
this each time right um batch batch
Plus+ and
then we use start idx this is going to
be batch times batch times batch size we
do our forward so we get essentially
inside of here we pass in our neural net
we passing our like our neural net
struct pointer um an input so that's
going to be train and it's going to be
the um the start
idx so whichever whichever this is um
whichever actual batch it is um times
the times the batch size so it's going
to skip in increments a batch size right
so it's going
to it's going to instead of uh skipping
like this isn't going to actually like
plus equals um like batch itself this is
going to add one each time so this is
just going to act as like an increment
so we're jumping right that's what
that's what that's doing is it's going
to jump four at a time instead of just
one we just plus
plus uh and
then we pass in the hidden layer
we pass in the output and then the batch
size as well right so all of the inputs
um hidden output size right um and this
is just going to do our forward pass all
the way from uh you know taking this
flattened image which we've done already
I'm just because it's just laid out in
binary it just like exists as that you
can reformat it and interpret it as
whatever you want but in see in memory
it's actually laid out as literally one
through zero you know Z through 784 or
whatever um so it's like not that hard
to actually like mess around
with we do the forward pass we calculate
our cross entropy loss right using the
uh same cross entropy loss idea that we
did in the C friendly script so we're
just porting that over to C um which if
there's like if if if this doesn't like
make sense then you can actually go in
and you can see okay well what are we
doing here versus here right you have
tools like language models and and the
internet which you can investigate these
things through through and you can kind
of see what's happening um yeah so we
calculate our loss we add um we add the
uh we add that loss to the total loss so
inside of that actual Epoch we see okay
well what was the uh what was the
average loss right um you know in here
we do total loss divided by you know
numb batches so we kind of we kind of
average that
out um
we do that every single Epoch and then
inside of
here we simply just this just acts as
little increment for the correct counter
so this is just going to see okay well
um were we close or not um
so this should be self-explanatory um
this is also just like not necessarily
part of the training run but just like
an extra feature that you can use to
print out uh what the accuracy was over
time um not the loss but the actual
percent
accuracy the backward function so this
takes in you know NN and it takes a uh
pointer to uh to the input right so this
is this is a memory address to this at
this index which is going to be um
starting index times input size right
and then inside of here we pass in a few
things meaning hidden um you know this
neural net is going to contain all of
our all of our weights and stuff so
don't this is like all contained within
that uh the input itself
um hidden output labels and batch size
so very similar structure to the forward
pass except we also include uh we also
include labels
right update weights everything is now
updated after that and then we can print
out some useful stuff okay and that's
pretty much all that happens in this
training Loop a lot of it is just like
print and keeping track of stuff um but
yeah so going
up if we actually look at our uh if we
actually look at
our let me jump up to the forward path
where did this
go okay awesome so inside the forward um
we it's very simple right 1 2 3 four
five six um not too bad now inside of
here I added the extra sof Max just
because I didn't want to be redundant
and included in the whole like training
Loop thing there was a lot happening in
there it was it was quite you
complicated to sort through
everything but yeah it's it's really
helpful when you break things up into
smaller chunks this is super manageable
I wanted to make the forward and
backward pass as as modular as possible
so that you guys could like really
performance optimize it if you wanted to
like on the side um but this is like
literally identical to what we did in or
almost identical to what we did in the C
friendly function or the C friendly
script right so in there we had this
like linear forward method which would
do the M mole and the bias um and then
the linear backward which would do you
know two mmoles and and uh and and a
bias backward um but in this one we kind
of just split it into easier more
manageable chunks so a map mole
specifically uh is like an operation
that you can optimize on its own and so
like optimizing a linear forward or or
even more generally linear backward it's
like kind of hard to do that right you
have multiple things in there you have
to like fuse kernels together it's more
complicated so I decided to keep this
like as as manageable as possible super
hackable um you know
modular but in the map mole the
ab
um yeah this
is this is literally the same as C
friendly so if I pop this over here um
actually maybe I'll bring it actually
downward um
but in here linear forward right we just
do x * W this is x * W we're not uh x *
W A and B same thing we're not
transposing anything and inside of there
and I already went over this function
but you you kind of get the idea we just
do a maple between A and B that goes um
we do a bi bias forward so that's also
going to we pop over to there yeah I
already reviewed that too don't need to
go over that again Rue forward it's just
going to apply that to each element very
simple M Mo A and B so same thing again
except it's the hidden it's it's
actually the the hidden to Output
instead of the output to Hidden so next
one and then we do the bias forward
again and then softmax right so
obviously like this is very very simple
to follow um it's more like more of the
complexity happens within the actual
function so like this is a lot
more to handle than the than the uh than
just the the for pass function itself
right so I exit on that and then
um and then go down to say the backward
function which is a little
worse to be honest go down to here
backward function so inside of here
um we're going to zerog grad everything
so what this means is previously
our gradients we're accumulating items
right so our grad um our grad bias and
our grad weights are actually
accumulating stuff so we want to just
zero those out right this is the
equivalent of zero grad and P torch when
we go here
um we do Optimizer do step so that's
like the actual update weight so you you
know do the forward and then you
calculate the loss then you do backward
and then you update the weights with
gradient descent and and then you zero
grad so you're just zeroing out every
single gradient um in the entire network
and then you're going to recalculate
those when you do the next Optimizer do
step right or sorry no loss. backward
rather when you calculate the gradients
again they're not going to accumulate
further they're just going to set them
initially and you're going to update
based on those gradients and then and
then put them down to zero again
um so that that's all we do here we zero
grad and there's actually a function for
this so mem set literally just a c
function um Set Set n bytes of s to C so
Set
n set set um so byes of s which is the
first one so
grad and then C is the value we want to
set it to so zero and then the N the
length of it is just the size of grad
right so size
is the number of numbers and then a
float is like the number of bytes
essentially so the number of bytes that
grad occupies in memory we're going to
start from the beginning of that uh and
we're going to initialize all those
values at the at those sequential memory
addresses we're going to set those to
zero that's what zero grab does on a
very low
level um so we do that with our weights
and our
biases now we do a grad output so this
is just going to a malic batch size time
output size so B * 10 right B by 10 they
compute output gradients so we go to
this Lally all this is doing is it's
taking this this grat output which we
initialize everything is like zero and
we have this output which is the um
which remember from the forward pass is
the output of the softmax which is
actually a probability distribution it
is not low jits it's not before the
exponentiation it is actually a
probability distribution with each value
between 0 and one then we have the
labels and literally all we do here is
we just element wise we set the grad
output to um the actual output value so
which which uh which floating Point
number is it right and then we subtract
one based on the actual label of it so
notice how in before in C friendly we
did um we did out grad output equals
softmax probs minus y true we're doing
the same thing here except we can't just
do a simple numpy element wise
operations we can't just be be dumb and
say this right we have to actually
we have to be explicit and we can be a
little clever by just doing the minus
equals 1 uh there so uh that's it's
literally doing the same thing we're
just using a different
trick if we just continue going through
we just did compute output gradients now
we now we can actually use those
gradients and start using like Matrix
multiple highs and bias backwards and Ru
backwards and all this stuff right so
the first one here is Matt Mo um we go
through uh we we calculate w2. grad now
w2. grad is right here so x2. T times
the derivative of the loss which is grat
output so here we do a hidden which is
X2 here in this case um or
sorry yeah X2 so the um essentially the
the input going into that um and then
times so this is times B right so B is
in this case is the grad output so we're
transposing this with this a here and
then times this and then that's going to
equal C or the grad weights 2 right so
grad weights number W2 right
um yeah so that that that that should be
fairly
intuitive now we go further we go to
bias backward bias backward isn't
actually too bad so bias
backward is uh literally just going to
we're going to iterate through um the
size I mean keep in mind we have batch
size right so we're going to iterate
through the entire size of it uh you
know iterating and incrementing I each
time gra we're going to uh store uh a
bias value a gradient bias gradient this
index as
zero and we're going to iterate through
the entire batch size and we're
literally just going to set that
specific value we're going to iterate
remember we're iterating through the
entire batch size so like we were doing
before how we were like smooshing the
numbers we're going to go through that
we're going to just um essentially do B
times
size so the entire uh the entire length
of that the entire length of of um of
like a of like a
row and then plus
I and we're just going to set um um
because this is going to increase each
time so we're essentially just going
down one one row at a time right and
we're we're smooshing it together
because we're plus equal accumulating
that value here so our grad bias is the
this is the equivalent of np.sum across
axis zero keeping dims true
right uh and then we go back
to where is
it we pop back to the backward function
awesome so now we get bias backward we
pass in the uh grad bias right so we're
calculating the the gradient bias and we
pass in the grad so that would in this
case would be the grad output and then
batch size and size right so that should
be fairly intuitive it's just the
gradients are directly flowing and we
just do an accumulate operation across
the batch because we want to generalize
over a batch right it's more useful to
do that um and then we just do since
we're done the W2 now we actually move
on to uh the DX X2 right so
dx2 uh is right
here we Malik this cuz remember this is
just temporary we don't we don't
actually need to store this this doesn't
need to be updated anywhere we're just
calculating this because it's a
prerequisite for calculating W1 so we we
can free it after we don't need to store
this in memory just be like efficient um
and inside of here we literally just go
uh grad output time W2 transpose right
so we go grad output a W2 transpose T
and we store that in dx2 right going
down further D out which is this part
here d r out is dx2 * d r of
X we allocate memory for this we go
through um we go through the entire
batch we literally just do dx2 so dx2
time
D
um d of of whatever of whatever that
value is just just going through it
right and this is going to be um if this
is this is going to evaluate to a a true
so or essentially a one if this if this
if this value is um essentially just
relue derivative right Rue derivative
that's all this is um we might not
actually even need the Rue derivative
backwards in in this whole thing but
we're going to keep it anyways um this
this does work though so this stores the
D out that's what we want right d out is
good then we update using the using the
um what's it called we calculate D out
from dx2 which we which we used up here
right we stored that stored the gradient
for that the temporary gradient there we
don't need it for later we just need it
for now calculate dout based on that and
then we use D out d
Rue out uh later and we essentially go
to calculate W1 we go x1. t time d r out
right so transpose so a tore B that's
what this is going to
be a tore B we go input
so um input X1 transpose that times D
value out and store that in we it's
one awesome
bias backward as as per usual so we just
have the uh the bias itself um and then
the the one that it's flowing uh flowing
from right so whatever it's whatever the
um whatever the previous layer gradient
was that's just going to flow directly
into bias right because um you know
adding adding does not uh change the
gradient of something it just changes
the like position the offset of it but
the slope remains same um but yeah
that's that's literally the backward
pass not too bad that might have been
like a little hard to keep up with my my
D you outs constantly it might have
confused you but uh yeah that's that's
pretty much it and then inside of um
inside of yeah so that that's backward
and then after backward after this we do
update weights then we print some stuff
out so let's just pay attention to
update weights here don't don't worry
about the rest of this you can parse
this on your own what we really care
about is the actual learning mechanics
of it right you can print anything out
any day you want it's very easy um but
we care about what the actual mechanism
is
here so if I go to update weights we
pass in the neuronet struct right the
pointer to that we access we go through
each one in here and we literally just
um we just do the same thing so hidden
size times input size so that's going to
be um you know 784 by 256 that's the
weight one we we iterate through each
index remember this is laid out
sequentially in memory so this is going
to evaluate to whatever 784 by 256 is
that's a large value just going to
iterate through that in memory it's
going to go through the lines or this
straight thing and it's just going to do
learning rate times whatever the grad
was and then it's going to minus equals
accumulate that into um weights one it's
going to do the same thing for weights
two remember weights two is um output
size times hidden size so hidden size
256 output size is 10 um bias hidden
size two out
size very
straightforward and that's pretty much
it
um let's go ahead and train this
thing so going back up let me just make
sure these are all set
correctly we'll do 256 sure we'll do
batch size of four that's fine learning
rate
0.01 that's okay as well we'll set theox
to
five just to be less
redundant or we we set it to actually
set it to three why not so now we go
into here GCC Das o V1 and then V1 doc
which is the file we're going to compile
and we do LM for link math right so
inside of here we do the math.h file we
need to link math for this to work
because if we don't right and um
unidentified reference to this these are
all the math functions right but if we
do
LM it'll work we can go and run this so
we get the first this is a five printed
out first Trend training labels is five
as we see here and then 04 1 9 2 1 31 4
and we can see the accuracy starts off
at about well the loss is about 2.3
which is uh random as we'd expect it to
so 2.3 evaluates to about 10% accuracy
and we can see that through the first
Epoch it goes through 2 200 HS and we
can see that the
accuracy goes up to about 60% which is
solid right loss is going
down and then in the next one it sees oh
my gosh wait we've seen these samples
before and it's going to drop even
further it's going to go down to 088 and
accuracy is going to fly up you know 15%
because it's already seen these samples
before um and then it's going to do that
again it's going to go up to
86% and we end up with about 88 8.6%
here um and uh yeah I mean you could
always print out the the ending samples
if you really wanted to um you could
always print out like some extra samples
and just like how it um how it matches
those up um but we're going to notice
that in our uh in our Cuda file so uh
anyways that that was a lot to unpack
there but that is the C file that's how
we transfer from numpy to see it's not
actually that crazy of a jump it's
mainly just writing the algorithm you
know the hard way um and just kind of
being more aware about things right it's
very easy to run into issues but as long
as we're careful about things it
shouldn't be too bad let's go and jump
into Cuda now okay okay everyone so this
is one of the last parts of the course
actually and this is part this part is
intended to be is intended to be a
little shorter so this is designed to
give you s of sort of a template for
continuing on this is the final project
right so uh I'm not going to give you
all the answers right away a part of
your job is to figure this out on your
own and use what we've developed
beforehand to continue and optimize
performance further right so I have this
um I have this naive GPU file right here
uh or sorry folder inside of Cuda so we
go
to we go to um go to the Cuda directory
and then we CD into n
View and inside of here um you're going
to find this file this vew one right I
just have this as like versions so you
can I'll like update more versions later
on if something breaks uh in future Cuda
releases or whatever but um yeah so this
is essentially just a direct Port from
our our C file so literally all we do
here is we we load in the same things um
we initialize way it's the same all
these are done on CPU as you can see the
only things that we actually change are
the m Kels right so we can see the well
there's more than just mapal kernels but
you can see so we have this mmal A and B
um so this is this is not
transposed uh and then this is B
transposed and then this is a transposed
right so when we're doing our backward
pass and we need to transpose certain
values uh that's what we'll use that for
right so we have certain kernels that
dedicated for that and we can actually
see based on the indexing scheme in here
um like notice how we we iterate Over N
every sing single time except this one
this one is a little different this one
is M
but uh if we go in here we can see a
this is just the normal one right so row
*
n u plus I and then if we go to this one
B it's I * k + column right and this is
different so notice how this a stays the
same but because we're changing B and
making it transpose this part this
indexing changes right and then same
idea here is uh we just transpose a so
this part I K and then column i k and
then column and um this part is going to
be different right so instead of row N I
it's I N
row and
uh yeah that's those are pretty much the
major changes the reason why we do this
for
um we do this for a is because a is
transposed um and and the m is m is a
little different but these are these are
naive kernels I expect you able to
dissect these but if we continue further
we have the ru we have our bias uh we
have a softmax kernel so this is going
to do a single softmax uh output so a
distribution for every single batch
element so it's going to go vertically
downwards each each thread is going to
do a a
row we zero our great gradiance with
this simple kernel so it's just going to
go you know it's going to go through
every single value and just set that to
zero um probably faster than mem set I'm
not sure but and then we have our D
kernel so this is just the derivative of
Ru multiply gradients um so element wise
multiplication of gradients which we can
see is
used down here in multiply
gradients and this function
is used uh is used right here so when
we're doing our when we're doing our Rue
um when we're we're doing our actual uh
we're going through D and we need to um
multiply those values it kind of makes
sense why we would put that there um
going back
up we just have our forward so the
typical a * B I don't know why this is T
um
okay
um Bim is not working all
right and we just do a ml add the bias
Ru ml add a bias then softmax right very
simple cross entropy loss is going to be
done on the host we're going to compute
our output gradients on the GPU because
there there is actually going to be a
lot of you have to consider when you're
actually writing Kel you're like what is
the how useful is it right to actually
go and write your own um actually go and
write your own so like for example this
one we could probably turn this into CPU
and it might be faster but who knows um
the kind of the idea here is like if you
have a big one if you have a big update
to do like update to gradients and you
have these big giant um you have these
giant W matrices that you're trying to
change and modify then having a thread
to do each little uh to do each little
like point update will help speed that
up but if you're doing just like a B
by10 for example which is what this is
you could probably get away with just
doing this really fast on CPU and you'd
be you'd be fine uh cuz there is like
kernel launch overhead when you have to
like literally launch this it has to
tell the GPU what to do and then it has
to trigger a bunch of threads to go and
execute that right um and then in our
backward pass we zero out the gradients
to make sure that they're not
accumulating and giving us you know mix
signals
um we have our
uh compute compute output gradient so
that's going to be the essentially the
these the output probabilities minus the
the true labels
right and then we have our our a
transpose times B so we go back to here
um this this
dw2 right we update um we update
gradients for bias 2 so there's specific
kernel for that now remember when we're
launching these there's it it seems like
there's a lot to sort through but really
all this is is looking at that previous
Technique we did where it's like you you
have to launch um say if you have 1,25
elements and you would normally only do
um like
1,024 uh threads right so what you do is
you add on add an additional block right
with a with a single um with a single
thread inside of it or or just or
another Block in general you could say
and since you have those bounds the like
that little if statement that checks if
everything is is worth so that it's not
like out of the out of the matrices that
you're working with like out like outer
outside of that memory um then you can
that that's essentially what this is
right so we're just being careful about
how we launch this stuff um and yeah
this this goes back to the you know
chapter number five on on kernels right
so uh these launch configurations can
like really mess you up and make things
look more complicated than they are but
if you can just like look through this
one bit at a time you have the uh you
have like the grid size and sorry the
grid dim and the block dim right and and
that's all you're really working with
and then of course the the arguments for
the kernel launch
itself more mmols right going back to
here this times so it's a * B
transpose a * B transpose
uh and then inside here we just do our
we just go backward through our ra
function all this is like very close to
our C file it's just like it's just run
in parallel right um same idea here I'm
just going to go further downwards
updating our weights um you know it's
kind
of I guess I have two of these
are we using
this let me
see yes we are we're using that one but
this one update
gradients yeah that's also okay so so
these are different things right yeah so
the the update gradients that's for the
bias and the update weights that is for
um that that is actually where gradient
descent itself takes place
um and then inside of this Loop
we go through uh initializing our our
device training sets so when you have
this D prefix remember that's for device
um you know Y is labels train is the
train set we C AAL all of those we mem
copy them over to device because they're
initialized as pointers on the host and
we have to copy those over with respect
to their memory addresses over to device
um and then aside of here we just
iterate over all the epochs we need to
do which in this case is Define at the
top and then number of batches right and
then we we set a starting index we make
sure to like stride a little bit so we
have whichever batch we're at here so
number of batches in the total thing
which we actually calculate by doing
train size number of divide by batch
size so if you have a th 10,000 training
uh examples and a batch size of four
you're going to have um 2500 batches
right and so when you do um whichever
batch you're at which is going to go
through you know it's essentially going
to go zero uh three
um 0 3
7 11 it's going to skip by four
right we do our forward pass so keeping
this uh this simple this nice little
concise NN struct right with all of our
our gradients and our our weights
right we calculate the uh we we C
essentially what this part is doing is
we're calculating the loss we're adding
it to the total running loss
of where is
it on this level we have we initialize
the total loss inside of the epoch Loop
right so this is for the entire Epoch
that's why we're that's what we're kind
of doing there is when we add the loss
we're just like appending it and then
we're you know dividing it accordingly
so we're just taking like the average
loss over the entire epoch
um in this case we are essentially just
like we were doing in the C file we're
just um adding to the correct counter so
however many samples we got correct
that's that percent
accuracy going into backward pass I
already walked through this there mean
you can kind of sort through all these
different
arguments uh we update we do an update
weights for each of our individual
weight matrices um so it's just going to
essentially element
wise uh it's going to element wise
multiply um the gradient times the
learning rate and it's going to
accumulate that into the weight right on
device and then in here we just print
some useful stuff right go down here
make sure that we free the training sets
uh the hidden and the D output that we
initialized
before we have our initialization of the
entire neural net so just essentially
doing our
malic initializing those so each of
these are going to be set to like random
values or in this case biases are going
to be set to zero and then we do our
Cuda Malik so we so we allocate on on
CPU we initialize everything on CPU we
allocate on device we move everything to
device um and then we're ready to run
right and then in this case all we would
do is um initialize this neural
net we we initialize it with with with
random data with random data
values uh then we load in our entire uh
training set into um into the host
memory we go and train everything and
when we're done we can free whatever we
need to on CPU and free whatever we need
to on on device so if I go ahead and
give this a run
here B1
not going to run with good
boss so variable I was used member
reference don't worry about that a
warning then we go and run this we can
see um this trains insanely fast uh we
go from uh Epoch one we have three
epochs in here total each one doing 2500
HS and we get a loss of about 2.3 which
is as we'd expect and then we see the
accuracy increase up to 60% and then it
gets even it jumps right goes up to goes
up to about 87% and then jumps even
higher and we end up at around 90% right
so that's pretty good and we can uh we
can actually run this with bigger Hye
parameters so I can go ahead and plug in
10,24 there and use a bigger batch size
maybe like maybe eight and then epox is
five we pop into here compile that we go
and run it we can see that um
um get a lot better accuracy right so
even up to 92% now so it's kind of what
what this part is is it's called
grocking so you get the first part where
it's where it's like just starting on on
its training steps and it's sort of
figuring out which weights to push in
the right direction and then you and
then it figures that out and then it
plummets the loss drops like really fast
which is what we're seeing um right here
with the loss is like 2.3 and then it's
1.72 and then boom 0.5 then all the way
down to like 2.9 0.3 is um and then
what's Happening Here is it now no it
now can no longer use the easy patterns
that it recognized and now it has to
search for more for more difficult
attributes there might be certain images
that it has a really hard time
recognizing and it has to and it has to
you know learn additional stuff which
takes more training steps to do um in
that process of deeply understanding the
data set or or generalizing over it
that's called grocking right
um hence the grock language model I was
using
before um but yeah so if we step out of
this and go over to um go over to this
this v file I named it V because it's
supposed to be fast and it's the one
that you're supposed to edit later go to
room and I was doing some comparisons
here but going remove those
compare and
compare and we have this other comparing
file which was experimental but I'll
probably remove that soon um and then we
go into this other one v1c inside of the
room file and this
one is pretty close to what we had
before now the only thing we actually
change here is instead of having uh in
we actually make this easier for you so
in the past one we kind of simplified it
and had all of the and had and did like
the map Ms a bit differently where we
transposed inside of the kernel but in
this example um we want to make it
easier for to just plug your own code
into here and have it work um so using
like the sjem the the sjem Cuda
optimizations we did before in the
faster mmal chapter like that's what you
would plug into here right um you'd have
your your own kernel and you would
launch it and from here um and then
inside
of
um and then inside of if I go
down we can see a transpose kernel up
there but if we go into backward pass
there's nothing modified in the forward
because there's no transposing there but
in the backward pass we can see that
there's just transpose Matrix function
right transpose transpose transpose
because we have to do this three times
we have to calculate uh this one this
one and this one there's no dx1 right we
we don't have to that's redundant
because we don't have a layer before it
um so we do three three of those three
transposed mammal
operations and so in here this literally
just switches it from column major to
row major that's all it does uh it's
just a cool little trick there is a
custom kernel for it that you can review
if you want to
um we where did it
go right here so there's this transpose
Matrix function that we call we pass in
these device inputs into it and then
inside of here we actually do the
transpose launch and we we make sure
that no errors happen and we synchronize
um all of the threads on on the GPU
right this is where the actual uh this
is where the actual trans uh trans
transposing happens um which isn't too
conceptually bad um but don't don't
worry about this too much it's more so
worrying about how do you speed this
thing
up so I can go Ahad and run this
actually and uh like I'll we change here
is literally just the just the transpose
oh I I had some KU stuff at the top let
me remove
that
Bloss I'll just add that in
temporarily we just
compile I was messing around with Koss
like this is a totally experimental file
so don't like I'm just kind of like
screwing around with this one um but we
could just do link Koss like
like
that and go and run this and we can see
it's it's also pretty quick too um yeah
so it trains it trains the same on 250
on hidden size 256 which is what we have
or this is 1024 actually um so 1024 and
we give it a batch size of eight only
three Epoch to learn though um it takes
you know it gets up to about 90%
accuracy which is still good um but yeah
on a reduced on a reduced um on a
reduced number of training samples so we
do batch size eight instead of four so
it gets it gets more like it gets twice
the amount of generalization because it
has double the batch size but the amount
of training samples is cut in half right
so it's actually like not that bad um
when you think about it so we could like
bump this epox number up to
six and you would see how how much of
a how much of a difference that actually
makes
so we can see that it's kind of going up
to 92 which is you know this last phase
here was it was grocking is what it was
doing there um but yeah so we got up to
about 92% um close to 90 93 in some
cases um but yeah that's decent um
that's you know I know most humans are
better than that but for 10 seconds of
training I think that's pretty good for
having no knowledge about the world at
all this neural network did fine
now over time I am going to add
optimizations to this but since you're
watching this right now this does not
exist in the current repo the version of
this course you're watching right now
whether that be 5 Years From when it was
posted whether that be two months one
day um this is the current version that
you're seeing right now and so this
might be different by the time I've
updated the GitHub repo in the future uh
I do plan to maintain this and add in
you know additional like maybe a V2 with
like you know I I'll make sure name
everything of course but uh just to just
to go in and like add some extra
features for example like I might I
might add in like a a really fast uh
like custom uh row major kernel where we
do like tensor core operations so the
warp uh the Warped Matrix multiply
accumulate the W MMA with tf32 Precision
that stuff is really fast uh and then as
well another optimization you could take
over is using Cuda streams so remember
in in uh in the concurrency chapter and
and no in the in chapter number five
where we went you know more deep deeper
into kernels and the whole Cuda
architecture you can use streams to uh
make things run concurrently right so
you could be loading in some data uh and
then you know doing say like a a forward
you could do like a forward
and um a forward and a backward pass and
then while that's happening you could be
loading in the next piece of data right
so I mean obviously this is just like a
digit digit classification and you're
not going to be super performance
limited here there's not a need for like
having super super high throughput CU
you can you can get this thing up to
like 99% accuracy if you if you make you
know deeper layers and you increase
hidden size and adjust all these things
it's pretty easy to get this thing to
perform well but this is the type of
thing you want to practice so that when
you write more more comp complex kernels
it's not as difficult to start with
right so you know there lots of
optimizations you can do you can add in
uh in this where is
it in this uh Matrix multiply kernel in
here you can switch this out with stuff
I'm not going to switch it out right now
because that's something that you kind
of want to do as a part of the final
project something you want to do
self-guided and and sort of go into it
on your own so I mean you can use this
as is but if you want to have some fun
this is just simple mamal kernel here
there's no transposing or anything this
is R major and you can have fun with it
uh so so that's that feel free to change
this kernel maybe experiment with tensor
core operations WMA stuff um and then
you know Cuda streams or something like
that feel free to use the uh ncu
profiler um and yeah hopefully this gave
you a better Insight on how to kind of
build up projects and how um and how
while they they might look Lex on the
outside you can sort of dig in and
figure out what's going
on now just really quick to run all
these again just so everything is
crystal clear that these are performing
the same um we'll go ahead and edit each
of them back to you know 56 so we'll do
256 there epox we'll do like three we'll
do bat size four learning rate is 1 *
103 and then in here we'll do
256 as
well uh batch size we'll low that down
lower that down before inside of our
CPU we
will uh turn this up to
2506 batch size is four Epoch three
that's good then we pop into our python
here set the uh torch reference script
to to
um this is 256 already uh 1 * 10-3 batch
size 4 we're looking good and then we go
to the C friendly
script I scrolled a little too far 26
good bat size four awesome so
now now we go into python I'll run
python uh torch reference
give this a second the data loading is
takes a little while in Python sometimes
it's not the most optimized thing ever
so
uh awesome so we end up with about 90%
90% accuracy in the end you know
89 here we have 87 in this case so we
end up with about 90 in the end let's
memorize that number 90 and then we go
to python C
friendly and we
get
87%
89% about 90% I had I had five ax in
there um yeah about 90 90% as well
91% and then we navigate over to the CD
into naive
CPU we go GCC compile with math we'll go
and run
this in
the this is going this is going to take
a
second um it's not used to going this
fast I know numpy probably has more
specialized Mill routine so a lot of
this is just
uh or sorry um yeah yeah numpy it
probably has more specialized routines
here so just doing it in raw C like
naively is going to take a while
um yeah so we can see
this we end up at
about give it a
second pretty close to 90% as well so
88.5 slightly worse um but that's that's
almost
negligible now
we have to what am I do CD into Cuda
slash GPU and then we'll do nvcc compile
without
Coss onun that look how much faster that
is
right new total of three Epoch and we
end up with boom 90% oh how how
convenient is that
hey and then we'll head out and we'll go
to um
the the room file
room
and pile with Koss you I just added the
kublos thing because you can add your
own kublos sjam or like the LT matol in
and just play with that um you run this
about the same speed and we end up with
about 90% as well so everything's
getting about 90% which is good shows
results are kind of consistent just like
make sure that's all cleared up
give yourself a pat on the back if you
made it this far it's pretty much the
end of the course you made it good job
um I'm just going to go over some quick
little little tips points in the right
direction if you want to continue with
this stuff um you know it it probably
was hard to grasp everything so I
understand if you don't but if you do uh
I have some extra resources for you so
inside of the read readme file here I
have a section on you know like what is
Unified memory memory architectures
which I thought would be you know kind
of useful and you might be interested in
but mainly what I what I want to cover
right now is I'm going to add to this
I'm going to add to this read me file as
well in the future um but there's
there's a section on dive deeper and
this is like if you want to take that
extra step and really figure out how you
can apply deep deep um deep
optimizations and advancements and
whatever you want to call it in in Cuda
and GPU programming uh especially in
deep learning this is this is what you
can do so there's this thing called
Quant ization which I'm going to start
with quantization is where you is where
you go from uh say
fp32 and you go down to say fp16 or int
8 you can you can actually go down you
can actually go from fp32 to int 8 and
you can still have really really good
performance and and quality of the of
the Precision on models right so there
are specific ways you can you can do
tricks around this but a lot of it has
to do with uh you know if your if your
range is is limited so if you if you can
hit like a maximum of say like I don't
know 10 and a minimum of - 10 then you
don't actually have to worry about a lot
of those exponent values right if your
weights are initialized and your
training is stable and nothing's going
to go like above or below 10 you don't
have to worry about it um you could
literally just cap that as your
Precision right and that'll be the
maximum it can go um those will be like
the the more sparse values right uh so
quantization is pretty much just the art
of doing that which is like taking
numbers that are really high precision
and then moving them down to lower
Precision doing really really fast
operations with those because I can tell
you for a fact int 8 is a lot faster
than fp32 like not just by four times
it's by quite a lot um and we saw that
in the kuo versus kubos LT section where
we compared 32-bit versus 16bit and then
performance was pretty substantial so
you can imagine what in8 would be
because it's just integers there's no
floating Point numbers to to worry about
there's no decimal places right just
inate so quantization is pretty cool
it's used a lot in current models like
uh you know say gp4 or like llama uh
llama 405b if you've heard of that one
uh like a lot of these actually use uh
quantization right so most likely like
bf16 or like fp8 or something like that
some of them even use float 4 which is
cool um then there's tensor cores which
I talked about already but I can't I
can't leave it out tensor cores are
great um I'm just not covering it in
this because this is kind kind of like
an intro it's kind of an intro course so
I triy to like pack as much as possible
into a into a certain amount of hours
that you could you know uh digest and
then if you want to continue with that
there's obviously tensor course too um
sparcity is a cool one so sparsity is
you can think of sparcity as um if I
have like an
array
um say like it would be like 0 0 0 0o um
like7
0 0 z0 0 and then say over here we'd
have like a like a six right this is
this is what sparse means so there's a
bunch of zeros and there's an occasional
like very big number that represents a
lot right based on its position maybe
based on its position relative to other
numbers um but the idea here is that you
can actually store these in much smaller
memory so it's a it's more of a memory
and compute thing more than just like is
this like what quality do you get from
this it's really performance so what we
can actually do is we can say um you
know we're going to have two matrices
one with the values and one with the
coordinates so we go
-7 and six and then this other Matrix
would be um you know 0 1 2 3 4 so this
would be um 4 and then 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 12 13 14 15
16 right and so you would end up storing
only four integers instead of instead of
16 integers and you reduce everything by
a lot now imagine this when you scale up
to you know 2D or 3D structures you're
saving like orders of magnitude of
memory and it can be really really
efficient right so this is something to
consider when you're Divi uh when you're
you know designing highly performant
neural networks is um can we capitalize
on things like sparsity right that might
be encouraged by the you know the people
who are writing the neural net outside
so when they're just writing like the P
torch architecture if it favors sparsity
if it does really well with that and
that's what it runs on then this is
really good for you this makes your job
easy um but sparity is just a
performance hack uh you you know take it
when you can
right then there's this book Cuda by
example
so um this it's literally just a book in
a general purpose GPU programming I
found this off of a Google search so
it's just like one of those Edo websites
and uh yeah it has it has a bunch of
things in it so like CPUs rise of GPU
Computing right a lot of what I covered
um so like what is the c to architecture
um pretty much a lot of a lot of what I
said or a lot of a lot of the a lot of
the important parts in here are
compressed down into the course right so
obviously not all of it is and I didn't
I haven't read this book either um 300
pages so I haven't read this book book
but a lot of what you're going to find
in here is going to be uh compressed
down into this
course
now there's this other article by Simon
the guy who works at anthropic on data
parallel distributed training of deep
learning models so that other that other
chapter where we were talking about
getting um getting uh big big algorithms
to train across multiple
instances this
this is a good example of it so
distributed training is a big problem
right now is getting like data centers
into one compact place there is research
around it and helping reduce that you
know dist distributed
aspect but when you have you
have when you have a massive data center
of a bunch of models and you have to get
them to talk to a bunch of bunch of gpus
sorry and you have to get them mod talk
to each other a certain way it's hard
right so this kind of goes into that um
I'm not going to go through this entire
thing but this does go through more
performance optimizations things like
all reduce which are used for um the
actual uh optimization process so you'll
see like an atom W all reduce or
something um there's
a yeah it's there there is a lot to
consider here but I don't even have a
cluster to train this on so I can't
really teach this
part
um we go back there's a few projects
that I found was that were really cool
one of them was mnus Cuda or CNN sorry I
did memis Cuda which was this and then
this is the actual qnn uh qnn and kublos
for training on the nness data set this
uses I believe
convolutions so if we like were to go
into yeah see it's like a V Visual
Studio code project or whatever so this
might be easier if you're on Windows but
like if you go into for example the the
network C++ file
um yeah I'm not going to dig through
this but this is a cool little project
that I found um you know feel free to do
whatever you want with it but it would
it came up in the GitHub search results
when I searched for mist Cuda so do what
you will with that
um I'm not going to go Cuda mode right
now that's I'm going to save the best
for last microad Cuda is very similar to
um microad by kpoy so this is something
I touched on earlier and this is
something you should review heavily for
understanding uh how how things like
back propagation work so it's pretty
much like a like a like a pie torch
autograd but very very small so if we
actually go into the files for it go
into the microgr files itself there's an
engine for it so the values there's like
a like a value thing for it so what like
the op operations you can do like a like
a power so when you go double asteris
it's going to call this underscore
uncore power as a method right um then
the add is just like same thing you have
the plus and that's going to all the the
add method then outside of engine you
have the actual neural net. py which is
like brings up all the abstraction of
like going from neurons to layers so you
have like a single neuron with a set of
Weights in it that taken you know all
the different X values and then dot
product and then output one that's a
neuron right so you does like a do
product there we can see that very
clearly and then there's uh you know
like a layer where it does a bunch of
neurons um and then it will and then
it'll just like a layer of neurons just
like that right a bunch of lons stacked
on top of each other and then the MLP
which is like that layer but there's
multiple of
those um and then micro Cuda is just
that but implemented in Cuda right there
there had to be one so uh yeah feel free
to like have fun with this and
everything it's it's supposed to be
faster so you can kind of just
understand things on a level of uh
compute unified device
architecture there's you like operations
all the Cuda operations so move to gpus
is like Malik and mem copy um you know
it's very simple interface you can
imagine pytorch being similar to this um
probably more performance optimal
but um you don't want want to do like a
Cuda M Copy and a malic every time you
want to move something or use a piece of
data you know you have the naive matal
kernel of course um the tanh kernel
right all this uh but yeah so bunch of
cool projects people are doing and then
there's this other interesting one I
found second second best one uh GPU
puzzles so you can use the qy library so
go qy
[Music]
python so qy open source GPU accelerated
Computing with python so it's
essentially Cuda but you get to use it
through a python interface which is
awesome um we go to the GitHub for
this
Cy
right there's a bunch of cool stuff on
this you know you just import it and
then you can you can make like shapes
and stuff and do stuff with that um
similar to something like p t or nump
right but
yeah so these GPU puzzles are just like
going through um you know solving like
essentially the logic problems where we
had a krel solve an issue for us but
doing that for a bunch of different
examples right so instead of just matrix
multiplication there's like a lot of
other things in here which you might
find fun to
practice
um and then the last one which I decided
to save for last is Cuda mode so they
have a they have a g Hub they have a
YouTube channel they have a Discord
server and pretty much a bunch of this
is it like actually contains a lot of
material and Beyond what I covered in my
course um this one was more to be like
video assistive but the community behind
Cuda mode is amazing they have really
really good engineers and researchers
here um just like building cool stuff
constantly people being super active in
the community it's a great place so uh
this is something I'd absolutely
recommend you check out
um and uh yeah there's there's a lot of
chapters like you see like flash
attention right they have everything
cutless Triton um fused kernels data
processing um tensor cores right so a
bunch of cool things um I'd recommend
that you join their Discord server you
can find that where's their Discord
server
here uh yeah bunch of
essentially bunch of cool uh bunch of
cool groups and everything it's like
beginner
section right Super Active like today
the last message was the last message
was like not even what like a few hours
ago and that's just one channel right so
you go down here the last message was
like 1 hour
ago so if you enjoyed this course um you
can totally find me on other platforms
you can find me on YouTube you can find
me on x/ Twitter you can find me on
Discord I have a Discord server full of
a lot of people uh you know there's Cuda
mode as well but I also have a server
with a bunch of people and we you know
like to learn stuff and collaborate and
all that um yeah find me on YouTube find
me on LinkedIn find me on X find me on
Discord those are all going to be either
links in the description or if they're
not in the description they'll be in the
GitHub repo um in the description below
thank you for watching